[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "The basic operations done in the food process engineering are called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) unit operations",
            "b) processing",
            "c) process management",
            "d) unit process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The study of basic operations done in the food process engineering is called as unit operation. It involves physical or chemical transformations like separation, crystallization, filtration evaporation and other reactions. The unit process is defined as one or more grouped operations in manufacturing system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the unit operations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distillation, evaporation, centrifugation",
            "b) Distillation, membrane separation, sampling",
            "c) Membrane separation, centrifugation, sampling",
            "d) Evaporation, centrifugation, sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The unit operations like distillation and membrane separation come under contact equilibrium process. The centrifugation, filtrations are under mechanical separation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Unit operation is based on ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) law of conservation of mass only",
            "b) law of conservation of energy  only",
            "c) law of conservation of mass and energy",
            "d) third law of thermodynamics only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Law of conservation of mass applies to each component entering the process. For example, amount of milk entering through pasteurization inlet should be equal to amount of milk leaving the pasteurization outlet. Similarly, law of conservation of energy applies where total energy in the material entering the process plus energy added in the process must be equal to total energy leaving the process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which of the following is untrue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Membrane separation follows the law of conservation of energy",
            "b) Membranes are used for separating components in food on a molecular basis",
            "c) Membrane separation cannot be used in ultrafiltration of blood proteins",
            "d) Reverse osmosis is an important application in membrane separation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gas absorption, crystallization are categorized under contact equilibrium processes. Contact equilibrium process is attained when the process reaches the equilibrium. Equilibrium is proportional to the concentration differences.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "In an evaporator, the heat lost by heating water must be equal to the _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sum of heat gained by the product and heat lost from the evaporator to its surroundings",
            "b) sum of heat lost from the evaporator to its surroundings in each step",
            "c) heat gained by the product",
            "d) overall heat lost from the evaporator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Membrane separation follows the law of conservation of mass and energy. The membrane separation is used to separate gaseous and liquid streams. It is also used in ultrafiltration for concentrating solutions of large polymetric molecules like blood proteins and milk molecules.Reverse osmosis is a water treatment where sufficient pressure applied against the water to force it through a semi permeable membrane, the water molecules are separated from other constituents within the water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Preliminary unit operation in any food industry includes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cleaning, sorting",
            "b) cleaning, drying",
            "c) grading, drying",
            "d) sorting, drying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Performance of unit operation depends on material handling. Optimization of time and movement of material from one unit operation to other is achieved by proper material handling techniques.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "What are the properties to be considered for designing a unit operation equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only Physical properties and mechanical properties",
            "b) Only Chemical properties and mechanical properties",
            "c) Only Physical properties and chemical properties",
            "d) Physical, chemical, mechanical properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to law of conservation of energy, the heat lost by heating water must be equal to the sum of heat gained by the product and heat lost from the evaporator to its surroundings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "The SI unit of film heat transfer coefficient is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) W K/m2",
            "b) Wm2K",
            "c) (m2K)/W",
            "d) W/ (m2K)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The SI unit of film heat transfer coefficient isW K/m2. The heat transfer through convection between a solid and a fluid is measured using heat transfer coefficient. It depends on 1) Hydrodynamic characteristics of its flow, 2)Hydrodynamic characteristics of its flow and 3) Hydrodynamic and thermal boundary conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Unit of specific gravity is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) g/cm",
            "b) g/cm3",
            "c) kg/m3",
            "d) dimensionless"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Specific Gravity of liquids and solids is defined as dimensionless unit. It is the ratio of density of a material to the density of water at a given temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "The SI unit of dynamic viscosity is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pascal-second",
            "b) pascal- minute",
            "c) poise-second",
            "d) poise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The SI unit of dynamic viscosity is the pascal-second or kilogram per meter per second. The CGS unit of dynamic viscosity is known as poise (P) which is named after Jean Leonard Marie Poiseuille.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "What is the dimension of surface tension?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MLT-2",
            "b) LT-2",
            "c) MT-2",
            "d) Dimensionless"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A quantity which does not have any physical units is called as dimensionless quantities. The relative density is the dimensionless quantity which is defined as the ratio of the density of a component to density of the given reference component. The Reynold number (R) is also a dimensionless quantity that is used to determine whether the fluid is following laminar flow (R<2300) or turbulent flow(R>4000).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "What is the full form of SI unit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) International System of units",
            "b) Indian Standards of unit",
            "c) Standard International unit",
            "d) International standard of units"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The surface tension is defined as the force per unit length. The dimensional formula of force is MLT-2 and for length, it is L. Therefore, the dimension of surface tension is MT-2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "What is the Full form of CGS unit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centimeter–gram–second",
            "b) Centralized grand system",
            "c) Centimeter gram system",
            "d) Centimeter grand system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are 7 base units in SI system. They are: kilogram (kg) for mass, kelvin (K) for temperature, mole (mol) for the amount of a substance, ampere (A) for electric current, candela (cd) for luminous intensity, second (s) for time and meter (m) for distance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "What are the base quantities ofDimensional formula?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Massand length only",
            "b) Mass and second only",
            "c) Length and second only",
            "d) Mass, length and second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The International System of Units is the contemporary form of the metric systems and is the most commonly used system of the measurement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "The analytical procedure of studying physical phenomena in variables, and corelating them to obtain a dimensionless group is known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dimensional constants",
            "b) Dimensional homogeneity",
            "c) Dimensional variable",
            "d) Dimensional analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The study of variables corelated to their physical phenomena and studying them analytically to solve problems refers to Dimensional analysis. If the equation expresses a proper relationship between the both, then dimensional homogeneity is obtained and the varying quantities are called dimensional variables, whereas the values normally held constant, are called dimensional constants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "2.The occurrence of closeness of measured values towards each other is known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accuracy",
            "b) Precision",
            "c) Measurement",
            "d) Dimensional Analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Precision is the closeness of more than one values towards each other. On the other hand, Accuracy is the closeness of the measured value to the known or standard value.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "What are the dimensions of Energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (MLT-2)",
            "b) (M-1L3T-2)",
            "c) (M L2T-2)",
            "d) (LT-2)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To verify the correctness of any given equation through dimensional analysis, we need to ensure that the sums of all exponents relating to any given dimension are equal on both sides of the equation. The exponent should be dimensionless or in other words, a pure number, although its magnitude does not necessarily have to be a whole number.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What is the ratio of inertial force to gravitational force known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weber number",
            "b) Froude number",
            "c) Reynold’s number",
            "d) Euler Number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main purpose of using dimensional analysis, is to verify whether a given equation is correct or not. It also assists the derivation of a relationship between various physical quantities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which dimensionless number is denoted by the equation Pr =\\(\\frac{μC_p}{k}\\)  ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prandtl number",
            "b) Weber number",
            "c) Reynold’s number",
            "d) Froude number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Energy is also known as work done, for which the formula is the product of force into displacement, i.e. Work = Force (mass x acceleration) X Displacement (in meters). We know that the dimensions for force and displacement are (MLT-2) and (L) respectively. Therefore, the dimensions for Energy are (M L2T-2).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "What is the ratio of inertial force to compressibility force and is also the key parameter, characterizing compressibility effects in fluids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Froude number",
            "b) Strouhal number",
            "c) Mach number",
            "d) Weber number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In fluid dynamics, inertial forces are very important and the ratio of these inertial forces to viscous, pressure, gravity, surface tension and compressibility forces lead to formation of fundamental dimensionless groups. Reynold’s number is the ratio of inertial force to viscous force and is thus, dimensionless.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "What type of energy is considered in enthalpy balance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat only",
            "b) Heat and mass only",
            "c) Mass only",
            "d) Heat and potential energy only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Enthalpy balances consider only heat energy. It is concept that is based on the first theorem of thermodynamics applied to the flow systems.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Which of the following is considered in a continuous process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass balance",
            "b) Energy balance",
            "c) Time",
            "d) Mass balance, energy balance and time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mass balances are fundamental to control the processing, particularly in the control of yields of the product. Energy balance is used in examination of each and every stage of a process, even extending over the total food production system from the farm to fork. The time unit is considered in continuous process in three periods. They are startup, continuous processing and close down.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "A processing unit is producing a product of 100kg which must contain 15% of fat and this is to be made up from component A with 23% of fat and from component B with 5% of fat. What are the proportions in which these should be mixed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 44.4 kg of component A to 55.6kg of component B",
            "b) 67.87kg of component A to 32.13kg of component B",
            "c) 55.6 kg of component A to 44.4kg of component B",
            "d) 32.13kg of component A to 67.87kg of component B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Let the proportions be X of component A to Y of component B\nThen by a mass balance on the fat,\n(X × 0.23)+ (Y × 0.05) = (X+Y) × 0.15\nA (0.23-0.15) = B (0.15-0.05)\nA (0.08) =B (0.10)\nA/B= 5/9\nTherefore, 100kg of product will have 55.6 kg of component A to 44.4kg of component B.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Which heat energy form is called as hidden energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific heat",
            "b) Latent heat",
            "c) Sensible heat",
            "d) Radiation energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Even though chemical and biological changes occur during a process, the total mass of the system will remain the same but the constituent’s parts may change. For example, in browning reaction, the total sugars may reduce but browning compounds in that product increases leading to mass balance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "What type of energy is enthalpy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal potential energy",
            "b) Kinetic energy",
            "c) Dynamic kinetic energy",
            "d) It is not a type of energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Latent heat is the also known as hidden energy. It can be defined as the heat that is released or absorbed by a system during constant temperature process called as latent heat.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "What are the properties to be considered for designing a unit operation equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only Physical properties and mechanical properties",
            "b) Only Chemical properties and mechanical properties",
            "c) Only Physical properties and chemical properties",
            "d) Physical, chemical, mechanical properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Energy conservation is the main element in the First Law of Thermodynamics where the energy cannot be created or destroyed, it can be converted from one form to another. It can be transferred from body to another. It can occur by heat flow, by transport of mass or performance of work.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "How is electric energy calculated in a unit operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Energy = power × time",
            "b) Energy= power /time",
            "c) Energy = power + time",
            "d)Energy = (power × time) + pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Enthalpy is a thermodynamic quantity and is not a form of energy. It is a measure of amount of energy stored in a system which is equal to internal energy of the system plus the product of pressure and volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "The force per unit area in a fluid is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) differential pressure",
            "b) fluid pressure",
            "c) dynamic pressure",
            "d) absolute pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The force per unit area in a fluid is called as fluid pressure. Since the fluid does not have any shape, the forces can be exerted in all directions such as gravitational force, external force on the fluid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which principle explains the buoyant force of a fluid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Archimedes principle",
            "b) Pascal’s principle",
            "c) Bernoulli’s Principle",
            "d) Newton’s second law of motion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Archimedes principle states that the object partially or fully submerged in a fluid will experience a buoyant force which is equal to the fluid weight in which object is displaced.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Hydraulic system works on the basis of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Archimedes principle",
            "b) Pascal’s principle",
            "c) Bernoulli’s Principle",
            "d) Newton’s second law of motion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hydraulic system works on the basis of Pascal’s principle. This principle states that when pressure is applied to a closed system of fluid, the pressure is transmitted to every part of the fluid and also to the walls of the container in which fluid is enclosed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which principle is used in designing the wings of airplanes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Archimedes principle",
            "b) Pascal’s principle",
            "c) Bernoulli’s Principle",
            "d) Newton’s second law of motion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fluid mechanics is a branch in physics that involves study of fluids such as liquids, plasma and gases. Fluid mechanics can be divided into 2 major categories. They are fluid statics (study based on fluids at rest) and fluid dynamics (study based on fluids in motion).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Who is the father of fluid mechanics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stephen Prokofievitch Timoshenko",
            "b) Ludwig Prandtl",
            "c) Singh Kapany",
            "d) Samuel Colville Lind"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bernoulli’s Principle is used in designing the wings of airplanes. According to the law of aerodynamics called Bernoulli’s principle, fast moving air has low pressure than slow moving air which has high pressure, so therefore pressure above wings is lower compared to pressure below the wings and this creates the lift in the plane that powers it to fly upwards.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "What are applications of fluid statics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barometers, anemometer",
            "b) Manometers, anemometer",
            "c) Manometers, hygrometer",
            "d) Manometer, barometers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The applications of Pascal law in daily life is that it is used in hydraulic pumps and hydraulic press. It is also commonly used in in braking system in the vehicles where a fluid called brake fluid is used to transmit the pressure from the brake pedal to the all the vehicle wheels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "What causes the turbulence in fluid flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kinetic energy",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Force",
            "d) Potential energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ludwig Prandtl is called as the father of fluid mechanics. Stephen Prokofievitch Timoshenko is father of engineering mechanics. Singh Kapany is the father of fiber optics. Samuel Colville Lind is father of chemical kinetics.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Viscous force is of the same character as _______ forces in solids.",
        "Options": [
            "a) shear",
            "b) impact",
            "c) gravitational",
            "d) electromagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Viscous force is the force between object and the fluid moving, in a direction to oppose the fluid flow past the object. It is similar to the shear stress forced upon a solid and they arise from forces which exist between the molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "The ratio between shear stress and shear rate in a fluid is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bulk modulus",
            "b) viscosity",
            "c) specific density",
            "d) young’s modulus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ratio between shear stress and shear rate in a fluid is called viscosity. Bulk modulus can be defined as the relative change in volume of the object produced by tensile stress acting homogenously over its surface. Specific density is the ratio of density of the substance to density of a given reference material. Young’s modulus is defined as the ratio of tensile stress to tensile strain of a given material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Viscosity is based on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) law of conservation of mass only",
            "b) law of conservation of energy only",
            "c) Newton’s law",
            "d) third law of thermodynamics only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Viscosity is based on  Newton’s law of viscosity, which states that the shear stress between adjacent fluid layers is proportional to the velocity gradients between the two layers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Shear thinning is also called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) thixotropy",
            "b) pseudoplastic",
            "c) non-newton fluid",
            "d) relative shear stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The viscosity of these fluids decreases as the shear rate increases. Blood, tomato puree are the examples of the pseudo plastic fluids. Another example is that, suspension of the corn starch in water with 1:1 concentration. Then this corn starch behaves like water when no force is applied. Still it is solidified as force is applied.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "The viscosity of gases ____________as temperature increases.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) remains same",
            "d) fluctuation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shear thinning is also called asthixotropy. It is a non-Newtonian fluid, where there is a decrease in viscosity under low shear strain and there is no flow at all until a yield stress is reached after which the flow occurs excluding time-dependent effects. Ketchup is an example of shear thinning.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "The viscosity of liquid ____________as temperature increases.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) remains same",
            "d) fluctuation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the temperature rises, the viscosity of gases also increases. This is due to increase in the frequency of the intermolecular collisions. The relationship between viscosity and temperature is velocity is directly proportional to the square root of the temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "What are examples of the rheopexy fluids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gypsum pastes, printer inks",
            "b) Gypsum pastes, ketchup",
            "c) Printer inks, ketchup",
            "d) Only ketchup"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The viscosity of liquid decreases as temperature increases. As temperature rises, there is an increase in the average speed of the molecules in the liquid and the contact time in between the molecules is also decreased.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Laminar flow and turbulent flow depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reynolds number",
            "b) Prandtl number",
            "c) Nusselt number",
            "d) Archimedes number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rheopexy is an exceptional property that is seen in some of the non-Newtonian fluids. In these fluids increase in the viscosity depends on the time. When a fluid has a longer shear force, the viscosity is also higher. Some of the examples are Gypsum pastes, printer inks and lubricants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "What type of fluid is alcohol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thixotropy",
            "b) Rheopexy fluids",
            "c) Non- Newtonian fluid",
            "d) Newtonian fluid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Reynold number (R) is a dimensionless quantity that is used to determine whether the fluid is following laminar flow (R<2300), transition flow (23004000).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Manometer is used for measuring __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pressure",
            "b) speed",
            "c) Fathometer",
            "d) density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Manometer is used for measuring pressure. Tachometer is used for measuring speed. Hydrometeris used for measuring density. Fathometeris used for measuring ocean depth.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which instrument is used to measure medium pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bourdon tube pressure gauges",
            "b) Barometric sensor",
            "c) Piezoelectric pressure sensor",
            "d) Piezoresistive pressure sensor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bourdon tube pressure gauges are widely used to measure medium to high pressure. The range of pressure it can detect is from 600mbar to 4000 bar. The measuring unit consists of curved tube with circular, spiral or coiled shape called as bourdon tube.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Which pressure instrument is used inweather networks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bourdon tube pressure gauges",
            "b) Barometric sensor",
            "c) Piezoelectric pressure sensor",
            "d) Piezoresistive pressure sensor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Barometric sensoris used in weather networks. These sensors measure the fluctuations in the pressure exerted by atmosphere. They are enclosed with a data logger and is well protected from precipitation, water ingress and condensing humidity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "_____________ measure dynamic pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bourdon tube pressure gauges",
            "b) Barometric sensor",
            "c) Piezoelectric pressure sensor",
            "d) Piezoresistive pressure sensor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Piezoelectric pressure sensors measure dynamic pressure. The dynamic pressure measurements include the blast, ballistics, turbulence and engine combustion. These sensors have the ability to measure quasi static pressures. They are fast response, extended ranges, ruggedness and high stiffness\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which instrument uses the change in electric resistance to measure the pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bourdon tube pressure gauges",
            "b) Barometric sensor",
            "c) Piezoelectric pressure sensor",
            "d) Piezoresistive pressure sensor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Piezoresistive pressure sensoruses the change in electric resistance of a material when stretched to measure the pressure. Due to the simple design and robustness, this instrument is used for wide range of applications. These are used for gauge, absolute and relative pressure measurement in both high and low pressure applications.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "One pascal is equivalent to _______ of force applied over an area of one meter squared.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one newton",
            "b) 100 newton",
            "c) 1000 newton",
            "d) 10 newton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Pressure transmitters contain pressure sensor and a signal conditioner to amplify the weak electrical signals that are sent through the pressure sensors for measuring the pressure. There are four main types of pressure transmitters. They are absolute, gauge, differential pressure, and multivariable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "The manomeric fluid density should be ______than that of flowing fluid.",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater",
            "b) smaller",
            "c) equal",
            "d) very small"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vacuum gauges designed to measure very low pressures or in a vacuum.The vacuum gauges sense the cooling effect of a heated filament on the gases in the vacuum chamber being measured. It consists of heated thin wire. These resemble as thermal flow meters, where heated wire is placed into the flow steam and infer the flow by measuring the speed with which heat is dissipated. The vacuum gauges sense the cooling effect of a heated filament on the gases in the vacuum chamber being measured.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "What is relation between PSI and Bar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 Bar = 14.5 Psi",
            "b) 1 Bar = 20 Psi",
            "c) 1 Bar = 201 Psi",
            "d) 1 Bar = 1 Psi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One pascal is equivalent to one newton of force applied over an area of one meter squared. The pascal is the unit of pressure and it is named after the scientist Blaise Pascal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "In a __________ pump, the fluid is drawn into pump and is then forced through outlet.",
        "Options": [
            "a) positive displacement",
            "b) jet",
            "c) airlift",
            "d) propeller pumps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a positive displacement pump, the fluid is drawn into pump and is then forced through outlet. These pumps can develop high pressure heads but they cannot stand blockages and throttling in the discharge outlet.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "In _________pumps, the energy of the fluid is converted into velocity energy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) positive displacement",
            "b) jet",
            "c) airlift",
            "d) propeller pumps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In jet pumps, a high velocity jet is produced in a nozzle where the energy of the fluid is converted into velocity energy. Jet pumps have low efficiencies but they have no moving parts and therefore have low initial costs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which of the following pumps can be used as vacuum pumps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive displacement",
            "b) Jet",
            "c) Airlift",
            "d) Propeller pumps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The jet pumps are used as vacuum pumps.A high velocity jet converts the energy of the fluid into velocity energy in the nozzle. This produces a low pressure area causing the surrounding fluid to be sucked into the pipe.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "The _________pump converts rotational energy of the fluid to velocity and pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) centrifugal",
            "b) jet",
            "c) airlift",
            "d) propeller pumps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Propellers are used to impart energy to the fluids. They are widely used to mix the contents of tanks and in pipes and convey the fluids. They have high efficiency and are used for low heads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "What is significance of fan law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It deals with pressure and velocity of the fan",
            "b) It deals with pressure and power consumption of the fan",
            "c) It deals with performance of the fan and power consumption of the fan",
            "d) It deals with performance of the fan velocity of the fan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The centrifugal pumps convert rotational energy of the fluid to velocity and pressure. The fluid to be pumped is taken at the center of the rotor and is passed along the spinning rotor thus producing rotational energy. This rotational energy is then converted into velocity and pressure at the periphery of the disc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "The efficiency of the pump is ratio of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) energy to velocity and pressure",
            "b) energy to velocity",
            "c) energy to pressure",
            "d) velocity and pressure to energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In airlift pumps, the air is introduced above a liquid in pressure level and that pressure is used to discharge the liquid. In case of powders, air is blown up through a bed of powder to convey it in the fluidized form. They are convenient for the materials which cannot be passed easily through valves and ports.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "What are the factors to be considered for designing a centrifugal pump?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capacity, Rotational speed only",
            "b) Rotational speed only",
            "c) Pump, Rotational speed only",
            "d) Capacity, rotational speed and pump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fan law gives the relationship between performance of the fan and power consumption of the fan. This estimates the operation conditions of the fan under different speeds, fluid density, impeller diameter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Which unit operation involves the mechanically induced establishment of a flow pattern in a liquid mixture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sedimentation",
            "b) Agitation",
            "c) Mixing",
            "d) Crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agitation is the process involving induced circular motion of homogeneous particles to prepare a liquid mixture, mechanically. Sedimentation refers to the settling down of suspension particles whereas Mixing refers to the random distribution of initially separate ingredients. Crystallization on the other hand is the formation of clumps of solid particles due to mass transfer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "The formula Np=\\(\\frac{P}{n^3Da^5\\rho}\\) denotes which number in impeller problems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weber number",
            "b) Froude number",
            "c) Power number",
            "d) Euler Number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The most common device used for agitation of liquids is the Propeller, which is a type of Impeller. Turbines are also a type of impellers, though with different fan orientations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "A flat blade turbine having six blades is centrally installed in a vertical tank. The tank is 6 ft (1.83 m) in diameter; the turbine is 2 ft. (0.61 m) in diameter and is positioned 2 ft (0.61 m) from the bottom of the tank. The turbine blades are 5 in. (127 mm) wide. The tank is filled to a depth of 6 ft (1.83 m) with a solution of 50 percent caustic soda, at 150°F (65.6°C), which has a viscosity of 12 cP and a density of 93.5 lb/ft3 (1498 kg/m3). The turbine is operated at 90 r/min. the tank is baffled. What power will be required to operate the mixer? (Given KL=403680).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.47 kW",
            "b) 6.05 kW",
            "c) 3.21 kW",
            "d) 4.00 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the process of agitation the baffles, which are one of the mechanical agitation devices used, remove stratification in the radial direction and improve mixing performance. A typical agitator vessel setup consists of 4 baffles and 1 impeller.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Which one is not the purpose of establishment of agitation in fluids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suspension of solid particles",
            "b) Blending of solids",
            "c) Blending miscible liquids",
            "d) Promoting heat transfer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Powernumber is the ratio of inertial force to viscous force. It is dimensionless and Buckingham’s Pi theorem is applied to it, thus giving the formula Np=\\(\\frac{P}{n^3Da^5\\rho}\\) , where P is the Pressure of the liquid, n is the rotation per minute of the impeller, D is the diameter and ρ is the density of the liquid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "An agitator is selected depending upon the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volume of liquid",
            "b) Height of the tank",
            "c) Power required",
            "d) Fluid viscosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: First calculate Reynold’s number. We have Da = 2 ft, n =\\(\\frac{90}{60}\\) = 1.5 r/s, μ= 12 X 6.27 X 10-4 = 8.06 X 10-3 lb/ft-s, ρ=93.5 lb/ft3 and g = 32.17 ft/s2.\nNRe = \\(\\frac{Da^2n\\rho}{μ}\\) = \\(\\frac{2^2X1.5X93.5}{8.06 X 10^{-3}}\\) = 69,600\nWe know that at low Reynold’s number for both baffled and unbaffled tanks, the relationship is given by\nNp =\\(\\frac{K_L}{N_{Re}}\\) = \\(\\frac{403680}{69600}\\) = 5.8\nP = \\(\\frac{5.8 X 93.5 X 1.5^3  X 2^2}{32.17}\\)=1821 ft-lb/s\nThe power requirement is 1821/550 = 2.47 kW (3.31 hp).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Name the type of impeller used for agitation of low viscosity fluids, on high speeds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propeller",
            "b) Concave Blade Impeller",
            "c) Straight blade turbine",
            "d) Paddles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agitation is done to suspend solid particles that might have settled down or are not distributed throughout the fluid, for the dispersion of a gas through the liquid, for promoting heat transfer and for the blending of miscible liquids.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Power consumption of agitators is a function of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impeller used",
            "b) Volumetric flow rate",
            "c) Volumetric flow rate and Kinetic Energy",
            "d) Kinetic Energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An agitator is selected depending upon the viscosity of the fluid, since that is the only way to determine the selection from the impellers of different types. This selection is independent of fluid volume, height of the tank used, and the power required in the process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "How can swirling be prevented in agitated vessels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By reducing the power provided",
            "b) By the use of turbines",
            "c) By the use of Baffles",
            "d) By lowering the shaft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Propellers are a type of impellers used for agitation of low viscosity fluids, on high speeds. They are effective in large vessels due to their persistence of flow currents. Paddles are used in slow or moderately sped vessels, whereas turbines are used over a wide range of viscosities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Ice has __________ thermal conductivity than water.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lower",
            "b) higher",
            "c) same",
            "d) very lower"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ice has higher thermal conductivity than water. This is due to the molecular arrangement in solids and liquids where solid has packed structure of molecules and stronger bonding between molecules compared to liquids. Therefore the thermal conductivity of frozen foods is higher than the foods at normal temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Which material has highest thermal conductivity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diamond",
            "b) Copper",
            "c) Silver",
            "d) Bronze"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diamond has highest thermal conductivity around room temperature along with the graphite and graphene. The thermal conductivity of diamond is 2000 watts per meter per Kelvin, which is five times higher than copper.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the best insulator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silica aerogels",
            "b) Manganese aerogels",
            "c) Potassium aerogels",
            "d) Lead aerogels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The best insulator is silica aerogels. The thermal conductivities of silica aerogel is less than 0.03 W/m*K in atmosphere.The liquid is removed from the gel without collapsing its structure, thus creating air pockets in the medium. This slows down the heat transfer and act as the insulator.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Which of the following example does not explain conduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The heat from a hot liquid makes the cup itself hot",
            "b) Walking on the beach on a hot summer day will warm the feet",
            "c) A metal spoon becomes hot from the boiling water inside the pot",
            "d) The formation of sea and land breeze"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thermal conductivity is the intrinsic property of the material. It refers to its ability to conduct heat. Heat transfer by conduction involves transfer of energy within a material without any motion of the molecules during heat transfer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which law governs the thermal conductivity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier’s law",
            "b) Pascal law",
            "c) Newton law",
            "d) Planks law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The formation of sea and land breeze is an example of convection. The other examples are due to conduction where transfer of heat in internal energy by minute collision of particles and electron movement within a body.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "What are factors of heat capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat energy, time",
            "b) Heat energy, temperature",
            "c) Heat energy, temperature, time",
            "d) Temperature, time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Fourier’s law governs the thermal conductivity. This law states that the time rate of heat transfer through a material is directly proportional to the negative gradient in the temperature and to area, at its right angle to that gradient through which the heat flows.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "According to_________ law, the conductive heat flux is linearly proportional to the temperature gradient.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier’s law",
            "b) Pascal law",
            "c) Newton law",
            "d) Stefan-Boltzmann Law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Heat energy and temperature plays an important factor in calculating heat capacity. The heat capacity is defined as the ratio of amount of heat energy supplied and change in temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Which is the slowest mode of heat transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conduction",
            "b) Convection",
            "c) Radiation",
            "d) Both radiation and convection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The thermal diffusivity is the thermal conductivity divided by density of the material and specific heat capacity at a constant pressure. It measures the ability to conduct thermal energy relative to its ability to the heat energy. High diffusivity means rapid heat transfer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which of the following example explain convection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The heat from a hot liquid makes the cup itself hot",
            "b) Walking on the beach on a hot summer day will warm the feet",
            "c) A metal spoon becomes hot from the boiling water inside the pot",
            "d) The formation of sea and land breeze"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The formation of sea and land breeze is an example of convection. During a day, the sun the sun warms the ground and sea water. Since the ground has lower specific heat compared to water and so its temperature increases more than the temperature of the water. The air above ground is heated thus forming a rise in the convection currents and the cool air from over sea flows towards shore. This is called as sea breeze. Similarly in the evening, ground cools faster than water and therefore breeze flows from shore to sea.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Which law governs the thermal convection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier’s law",
            "b) Pascal law",
            "c) Newton’s law",
            "d) Stefan-Boltzmann Law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Newton’s law governs the thermal convection especially in convection cooling. It states that rate of heat loss of a body is directly proportional to the temperature difference between the body and its surroundings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "___________ is the transfer of thermal energy through the movement of a liquid or gas.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Convection",
            "b) Conduction",
            "c) Radiation",
            "d) Evaporation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Convection is the transfer of thermal energy through the movement of a liquid or gas.Convection can be defined as the heat transfer by the movement of a fluid between areas of temperature difference.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "_________ is the currents produced only by temperature difference.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Natural convection",
            "b) Forced convection",
            "c) Conduction",
            "d) Radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Convection is faster than conduction. In convection the medium in which heat transfer takes place is in motion whereas the heat transfer through conduction takes place by collision between the atoms.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "In __________, fluid is forced to flow over a surface or in a tube by external means.",
        "Options": [
            "a) natural convection",
            "b) forced convection",
            "c) conduction",
            "d) radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The properties of heat transfer by the convection between a body and its surrounding are 1. The convection takes place when there is temperature difference between two medium. 2. It depends on the relative motion of the fluid as convection takes place only when the medium has movement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Convective heat transfer coefficients for air under natural convection is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 – 1000 (W/(m2K))",
            "b) 50 – 3000 (W/(m2K))",
            "c) 10 – 1000 (W/(m2K))",
            "d) 50 – 10000 (W/(m2K))"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Natural convection is a type of convection where the heat transfer takes place only due to density difference that leads to the temperature difference in the fluid. The gravitational force is the main driving force in the natural convection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Convective heat transfer coefficients for condensing water vapor is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 – 1000 (W/(m2K))",
            "b) 5 – 100 (W/(m2K))",
            "c) 10 – 1000 (W/(m2K))",
            "d) 50 – 10000 (W/(m2K))"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Forced convection is a mechanism of heat transfer in which fluid motion is produced by an external source such as ceiling fan, a pump and suction device. It creates uniform and comfortable temperature throughout the medium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Convective heat transfer coefficients for liquid under forced convection is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 – 1000 (W/(m2K))",
            "b) 50 – 3000 (W/(m2K))",
            "c) 10 – 1000 (W/(m2K))",
            "d) 50 – 10000 (W/(m2K))"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Convective heat transfer coefficients for air under natural convection is 0.5 – 1000 (W/(m2K)).  For liquids under natural convection is 50 – 3000 (W/(m2K)). For air under forced convection it is 10 – 1000 (W/(m2K)). For liquids under forced convection it is 50 – 10000 (W/(m2K)).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which is the fastest mode of heat transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conduction",
            "b) Convection",
            "c) Radiation",
            "d) Both conduction and convection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The fastest mode of heat transfer is radiation as it travels at the speed of light. Conduction is the slowest mode of heat transfer because it takes place from particle to particle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which law governs the thermal radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier’s law",
            "b) Pascal law",
            "c) Newton law",
            "d) Stefan-Boltzmann Law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stefan-Boltzmann Lawgoverns the thermal radiation. It statesthat the total radiant heat power emitted from a surface is proportional to the fourth power of its absolute temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "The emissivity of radiation is between__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 and 1",
            "b) 0 and 10",
            "c) 0 and 15",
            "d) 0 and 11"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermal radiation follows Planks law and also Wien’s Displacement Law. Stefan-Boltzmann Law states that the total radiant heat power emitted from a surface is proportional to the fourth power of its absolute temperature.Wien’s Displacement Law states that a hotter object will emit radiation with a shorter wavelength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "In thermal radiation, thermal energy is converted to ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) kinetic energy",
            "b) potential energy",
            "c) electromagnetic energy",
            "d) thermal energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The emissivity of radiation is between0 and 1. It can be defined as the ratio of the thermal radiation from the surface to the radiation from an ideal black surface at a constant temperature. This is derived under Stefan–Boltzmann law.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "What is the wavelength of thermal radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 μm to 1000 μm.",
            "b) 1 μm to 100 μm.",
            "c) 0.01 μm to 100 μm.",
            "d) 0.1 μm to 100 μm."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In thermal radiation, thermal energy is converted to electromagnetic energy. This is achieved by the thermal motion of the particles in the substance. All the substance with a temperature greater than absolute zero emits the thermal radiation. The motion of the particle results in acceleration of charge and dipole oscillation which produces electromagnetic energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "What are factors of thermal radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Volume",
            "d) Pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The thermal radiation is the electromagnetic radiation emitted from all the substance that is at non-zero temperature in the wavelength ranging from 0.1 μm to 100 μm. This includes part of ultraviolet rays, all of the visible and infrared rays.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "According to ___________, the wavelength of the emitted radiation is inversely proportional to its frequency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier’s law",
            "b) Pascal law",
            "c) Newton law",
            "d) Plank’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hot objects radiate infra-red electromagnetic waves, so therefore insulation against heat transfer by radiation is done by using reflective materials. The thermos bottle has a shiny material along with a lining to prevent heat conduction. This shiny material reflects heat from the radiation from inside as well as outside the bottle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "____________ gives the relationship between wavelength and temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier’s law",
            "b) Wein’s law",
            "c) Newton law",
            "d) Plank’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Temperature plays an important factor in thermal radiation. The heat capacity is defined as the ratio of amount of heat energy supplied and change in temperature. According to Stefan-Boltzmann Law, the total radiant heat power emitted from a surface is proportional to the fourth power of its absolute temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "What type of heat exchanger used in oil refineries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shell and tube Heat exchanger",
            "b) Plate heat exchanger",
            "c) Finned tube heat exchanger",
            "d) Plate fin heat exchanger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shell and tube Heat exchanger is used in oil refineries and is appropriate for high pressure applications. The hydraulic fluids and the oils in the engines are cooled by using this exchanger.  It comprises a number of tubes attached inside a cylindrical shell. The two fluids can transfer the heat where one fluid flows inside the tubes and other fluid flows over the tubes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "Air Cooled Heat Exchangers are used in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) oil refineries",
            "b) vehicles",
            "c) food industries",
            "d) dairy industries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Air Cooled Heat Exchangers are used in vehicles where stable cool water source is not available. Cool air is provided by air flow due to vehicle movement or by fans.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "What are the examples of indirect heat exchangers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shell and tube Heat exchanger, Plate heat exchangers",
            "b) Steam injectors, plate heat exchangers",
            "c) Cooling towers, Plate heat exchangers",
            "d) Steam injectors, cooling towers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Indirect heat exchanger, the two fluids can transfer the heat where one fluid flows inside the tubes and other fluid flows over the tubes. Shell and tube Heat exchanger, Plate heat exchangers are the examples of indirect heat exchangers. Steam injectors, cooling towers are the examples of direct heat exchangers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "What are the examples of direct heat exchangers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shell and tube Heat exchanger, Plate heat exchangers",
            "b) Steam injectors, plate heat exchangers",
            "c) Cooling towers, Plate heat exchangers",
            "d) Steam injectors, cooling towers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In direct heat exchangers, there is a direct contact between the two immiscible fluids for transferring the heat. Cooling towers, jet condensers, steam injectors are the examples of direct heat exchangers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "What type of heat exchanger is used in cryogenic applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shell and tube Heat exchanger",
            "b) Plate heat exchanger",
            "c) Finned tube heat exchanger",
            "d) Plate fin heat exchanger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plate fin heat exchangeris used in cryogenic applications. They use corrugated fins which are separated by flat plates. These are used in gas-to-gas applications at where it has low pressures and temperatures not above 800°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "_____________ consists of a single tube mounted inside another tube.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shell and tube Heat exchanger",
            "b) Plate heat exchanger",
            "c) Double tube heat exchanger",
            "d) Plate fin heat exchanger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Printed circuit heat exchanger is an example for indirect heat exchanger. It can be used as alternatives to shell and tube heat exchanger. It has high heat transfer surface area per unit volume of the exchanger. It also reduces the energy requirement. But it is expensive than shell and tube units and the fluid needs to be extremely clean or else blockages can occur due to the ﬁne channels. Therefore the fluids are filtered before the feeding into inlet pipe.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "_________ is used as rear header in a U-Tube heat exchanger.",
        "Options": [
            "a) M type",
            "b) A type",
            "c) U type",
            "d) D type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Double pipe heat exchanger contains of two concentric pipes of different diameters. One pipe is for cold fluid and the other one is for hot fluid.The fluid can flowin co-current direction or counter current direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "__________is used for horizontal thermosyphon reboilers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) G type",
            "b) A type",
            "c) C type",
            "d) Y type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: M typeis used as rear header in a U-Tube heat exchanger. The U-tubes permit unlimited thermal extension, the bundles of the tubes can be removed to clean. But internal cleaning of the tubes are difficult due to the small diameter, therefore the fluids are filtered before entering into the feed pipe.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "__________ uses an intermediate fluid or solid store to hold heat.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shell and tube Heat exchanger",
            "b) Plate heat exchanger",
            "c) Double tube heat exchanger",
            "d) Adiabatic wheel heat exchanger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: G typefront header is used for horizontal thermosyphon reboilers. A-Type front header is used for easy cleaning or repair of the tubes without having to disturb the pipe work. C type header is for high pressure applications. Y-Type header used as a front or rear header and is used when the exchanger is in pipe line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "What is heat economizing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The total cost of the heat exchanger and its maintenance cost",
            "b) Interchange heat among the hot and cold fluids to conserve heat energy.",
            "c) The capital cost of the heat exchanger unit",
            "d) Amount of heat produced per day"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Heat economizing can be defined as the Interchange heat among the hot and cold fluids to conserve heat energy. The heat from the hot liquid is transferred to the cool liquid thus reducing the overall cost of the heating mechanism. This is especially achieved when the arrangement is in counter flow mechanism.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Who invented the heat exchanger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dr Richard Seligman",
            "b) George Babcock",
            "c) George Brayton",
            "d) Benjamin Franklin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dr Richard Seligman invented heat exchanger. George Babcock invented boiler. George Brayton invented engine. Benjamin Franklin invented electricity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "What are the factors to be considered for designing a heat exchanger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermal analysis",
            "b) Hydraulic calculations",
            "c) Pressure calculations",
            "d) Thermal analysis and hydraulic calculations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are 2 factors to be considered for designing a heat exchanger. They are Thermal analysis and hydraulic calculations. The thermal analysis is a study of the physical and chemical properties of the fluid with respect to temperature under controlled temperature program. Hydraulic analysis refers to the study of fluid under different conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What are main advantages of continuous heat exchanger over batch heat exchanger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficiency and cost",
            "b) Quantity and cost",
            "c) Efficiency and quality",
            "d) Efficiency and quantity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Regenerative heat exchangers are also known as capacitive heat exchangers. The flow path consists of the matrix where heat from the hot fluid is captured in the matrix and then it is released to the cold fluid. Regenerators are commonly used in gas/gas heat recovery applications mainly in power stations. Static and dynamic are the two types of regenerators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "The deposition of any undesired material on heat transfer surfaces is called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fouling",
            "b) debris",
            "c) scaling",
            "d) rubble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The two important merits of continuous heat exchanger over batch heat exchanger are efficiency and quantity. The efficiency of the continuous heat exchanger depends on the continuous cleaning and calibration. The quantity depends on the feed rate which is higher than the batch process. But continuous heat exchanger is expensive than a batch system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Which is the common fouling mechanism seen when untreated water is used as the coolant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biological Fouling",
            "b) Chemical Fouling",
            "c) Corrosion Fouling",
            "d) Freezing Fouling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Two-phase heat exchangers undergo phase change during the heat transfer process. The phase change occurs in either or both the fluids thus resulting in liquid to gas or gas to liquid change. The two-phase heat exchangers includecondensers, boilers and evaporators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "___________ results from a chemical reaction involving the heat exchanger surface material.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biological Fouling",
            "b) Chemical Fouling",
            "c) Corrosion Fouling",
            "d) Freezing Fouling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The deposition of any undesired material on heat transfer surfaces is called fouling. It refers to the deposit collected on the surfaces of the heat exchanger. It contains organic particles, inorganic particles, microorganisms. This increases the risk of corrosion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of the portholes on the plates of plate heat exchangers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To have a even flow of the fluid throughout the plate",
            "b) To drain the excess liquid from the plate",
            "c) To maintain the pressure inside the heat exchanger",
            "d) To stack the plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main purpose of the portholes on the plates of plate heat exchangers is to ensure that flow of the liquid is even throughout the plate. It also increases the heat transfer efficiency and reduces the fouling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "The corrugation of V shape embossed on the plates is termed as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reflex angle",
            "b) V angle",
            "c) Z angle",
            "d) chevron angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The corrugation of V shape engraved on the plates is known aschevron angle. It is measured with horizontal direction. This is normally used to produce the turbulence effect to the flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which heat exchanger is most efficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel flow",
            "b) Cross flow",
            "c) Counter flow",
            "d) Tangent flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A counterflow heat exchanger works on the principle that the hot fluid enters at one end of the exchanger and thecold fluid enters at the other end. Counter flow is the widely used in liquid-liquid heat exchanger, as it is the most efficient flow compared to others.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Air conditioner evaporator coil uses _______ in the heat exchanger.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel flow",
            "b) cross flow",
            "c) counter flow",
            "d) tangent flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In parallel flow, both the fluids enter at one end and exit at the other end.the temperature difference between the two fluids is large at the entrance end, but it becomes small at the exit end. The log mean temperature difference is greater for counter flow. So the surface area of the parallel flow heat exchanger should be larger than for a counter flow heat exchanger.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What is main advantage of Brazed Plate Heat Exchanger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermal efficiency",
            "b) Quality",
            "c) Leak proof",
            "d) Easy cleaning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Car radiator and air conditioner evaporator coil uses crossflow heat exchangers. Crossflow heat exchangers are widely used for transfer of heat between a gas and a liquid. In air conditioner evaporator coil, the air flows past the evaporator coils are cooled by the cold refrigerant that is flowing inside the tubes of the coil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "In ________, pressure is applied in between the plates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) pillow plate exchangers",
            "b) plate fin exchangers",
            "c) plate and shell heat exchangers",
            "d) spiral plate heat exchangers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A Brazed Plate Heat Exchanger has the highest level of thermal efficiency and durability, low-cost unit. It also works under high temperature and pressure conditions. It is used in boilers, heat pumps, district heating, domestic water, radiant, air conditioners.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Which exchanger is called as modified floating-head shell-and-tube exchanger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pillow plate exchangers",
            "b) Plate fin exchangers",
            "c) Lamella plate heat exchangers",
            "d) Spiral plate heat exchangers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In pillow plate exchangers, pressure is applied in between the plates. This is an additional benefit to increase the heat transfer efficiency across the surface of the plate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "What method is used to manufacture panel coils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Die stamping process",
            "b) 3 D printing process",
            "c) Cold bonding process",
            "d) Hot bonding process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lamella plate heat exchanger is called as modified floating-head shell-and-tube exchanger. One fluid flows inside the lamella whereas the other flows longitudinally in the spaces between them. There are no baffles on the shell side. The flow arrangement is generally counter flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "_______ are also referred toas a matrix heat exchanger.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pillow plate exchangers",
            "b) Plate fin exchangers",
            "c) Lamella plate heat exchangers",
            "d) Spiral plate heat exchangers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Die stamping process is usedfor manufacturing panel coils. In this process, flow channels are die stamped on either one or two metal sheets. When one sheet is engraved and joined to a flatplate, it forms a one-sided embossed panelcoil. When both sheets are stamped, it forms a double sidedembossed panelcoil. Finally the two plates are joined by electric resistance welding.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Specific Heat (kJ/kg K) of apple is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.88",
            "b) 1.67",
            "c) 1.76",
            "d) 1.42"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specific Heat (kJ/kg K) of apple is 1.88. Specific Heat (kJ/kg K) of beef is 1.67, Specific Heat (kJ/kg K) of banana is 1.76 and Specific Heat (kJ/kg K) of bread is 1.42.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "The specific heat of a material can be determined by ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) calorimetry",
            "b) manometers",
            "c) barometers",
            "d) anemometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The specific heat of a material can be determined by calorimetry. Manometer, barometers are used in measuring the pressure of the fluid. Anemometer is used in measuring the wind speed and also the direction of the wind.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Thermal energy is transported through the molecules due to _______and _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) lattice waves, free electrons",
            "b) lattice waves, free protons",
            "c) free protons, free electrons",
            "d) lattice waves, longitudinal waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thermal energy is transported through the molecules due to lattice waves and free electrons. In pure metals, the conduction of heat is based on the flow of free electrons and the effect of lattice waves is considered as negligible. In alloys and nonmetallic solids, since they are only few free electrons, conduction of heat is due to lattice vibrations in between the molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "4.________ is the heat content in a system per unit mass.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific heat",
            "b) Enthalpy",
            "c) Entropy",
            "d) Latent heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enthalpy is the heat content in a system per unit mass. Its unit is J/kg in the SI system. It is a thermodynamic property that is governed by the state of the system and it is expressed as H=U+PV, where H is the enthalpy, U is internal energy, and P is pressure and V is volume.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "The effect of ______on the system is seen only as a phase change like the melting of ice.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific heat",
            "b) Enthalpy",
            "c) Entropy",
            "d) Latent heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Latent heat is the also known as hidden energy. It can be defined as the heat that is released or absorbed by a system during constant temperature process is called latent heat. The effect is seen only as a phase change like boiling of water or the melting of ice.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a thermal property in foods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface heat transfer coefficient",
            "b) Thermal diffusivity",
            "c) Specific volume",
            "d) Entropy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Specific heat of ice is 2.1 kJ/kg K and specific heat of water. 4.218 kJ/kg K. Therefore the specific heat of ice is half of the specific heat of water. Specific heat of foods decreases during freezing as there is a continuous phase change from water to ice.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "8.______ is the ability of a material to transmit a thermal disturbance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific heat",
            "b) Thermal diffusivity",
            "c) Entropy",
            "d) Latent heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The surface heat transfer coefficient is not a thermal property. It is required to design heat transfer equipment for processing foods where convection is involved. It depends on the fluid velocity, product size and shape, surface roughness, arrangement and packaging.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Who discovered latent heat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joseph Black",
            "b) Josiah Willard Gibbs",
            "c) Henri Becquerel",
            "d) Stephen Gray"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermal diffusivity is the ability of a material to transmit a thermal disturbance. It determines heat propagation and diffusion through a material. It helps in estimating the process time of canning, cooking and cooling. Water content, composition, temperature and porosity affect thermal diffusivity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which liquid has highest latent heat of vaporization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Alcohol",
            "c) Oil",
            "d) Mecury"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Joseph Black discovered latent heat. Josiah Willard Gibbs discovered enthalpy. Henri Becquerel discovered radiation. Stephen Gray discovered electrical conduction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which describes the level of microbial destruction obtained by thermal treatment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F0 value",
            "b) Thermal death time",
            "c) D value",
            "d) Z value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The level of microbial destruct that is obtained by thermal treatment is known as sterilizing value (F0) of the given food product. The results are calculated at 121.1°C temperature. The unit is minutes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "________ relates the resistance of an organism to differing temperatures.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F0 value",
            "b) Thermal death time",
            "c) D value",
            "d) Z value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Z- value is defined as the temperature (in degree) at which a tenfold reduction in D-value is attained. The main application of Z- value is in the calculating the thermal death time of a microorganism.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "_________ is defined as the time taken at a given temperature to eliminate at least 90% of the exposed microorganisms.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F0 value",
            "b) Thermal death time",
            "c) D value",
            "d) Z value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: D valueis defined as the time taken at a given temperature to eliminate at least 90% of the exposed microorganisms. It is suitable to examine the efficiency of thermal inactivation of different microbes under different conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "________ is the time taken to kill a specific bacterium at a specific temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F0 value",
            "b) Thermal death time",
            "c) D value",
            "d) Z value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermal death time which is also known as TDT is defined as the time taken to destroy a specific microbe at a particular temperature. TDT is used in regulating the sterilization procedures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "_______ of a microorganism is the lowest temperature at which all microbes are killed in a 10-minute exposure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F0 value",
            "b) Thermal death time",
            "c) D value",
            "d) Thermal death point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thermal death point is be defined as the lowest temperature at which all the microorganisms are killed in a 10-minute exposure and it varies depending on the microbes. Thermal death point gives the idea of the effect of heat on the microbes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "__________ is used mainly in low acid canned foods.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12 D concept",
            "b) 1 D concept",
            "c) 10 D concept",
            "d) 100 D concept"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: D value is defined as the time taken at a given temperature to eliminate at least 90% of the exposed microorganisms. It is suitable to examine the efficiency of thermal inactivation of different microbes under different conditions. D-value for the same microbes differs depending on the food type. In acid foods, the D value is lower and higher in protein rich foods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "______ is the better way of stating thermal death time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F0 value",
            "b) F value",
            "c) D value",
            "d) Z value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 12D concept is used generally in low acid canned foods. It refers to thermal processing to reduce the probability of survival of the C. botulinum spores to 10-12 which is high resistant microbe at 121oC.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "_________ is equal to the reciprocal of the slope of the thermal death time curve.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F0 value",
            "b) F value",
            "c) D value",
            "d) Z value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermal death time which is also known as TDT is defined as the time taken to destroy a specific microbe at a particular temperature. F value is defined as the time required killing all spores or vegetative cells at 1210oC. Therefore F value is the better way of stating thermal death time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Heat resistance of microorganisms and their spores can be expressed in terms of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) F0 value",
            "b) thermal death time",
            "c) D value",
            "d) thermal death point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Z-value is used in the microbial thermal death time calculations. It is defined as the temperature (in degree) at which a tenfold reduction in D-value is attained. It is equal to the reciprocal of the slope of the thermal death time curve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "The pasteurization process was named after ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Louis Pasteur",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Nicolas Appert",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pasteurization process was developed by Louis Pasteur. Charles Chamberland developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Nicolas Appert is the father of food technology. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of the following is called as cold pasteurization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freeze drying",
            "b) Heating under low pressure",
            "c) Irradiation",
            "d) Heating at low temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The calcium absorption is not changed during the pasteurization process. Similarly, niacin , riboflavin, vitamin A and vitamin D are not affected by the this process. There is a minimal loss of thiamine and vitamin B12.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Pasteurization processes are fully effective in destroying __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) campylobacter",
            "b) thermus",
            "c) bacillus",
            "d) thermoplasma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The irradiation is also known as cold pasteurization as it destroys the foodborne disease caused by pathogenic microorganisms and parasites. Unlike pasteurization, this method does not use any heat in the process instead uses the high energy rays to kill the microbes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "A pasteurization process operates to ________reductions of the target organism.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12 log",
            "b) 9 log",
            "c) 6 log",
            "d) 3 log"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pasteurization processes are fully effective in destroying campylobacter. Other bacteria like thermos, bacillus and thermoplasmaare thermophiles which can grow at high temperature and cannot be destroyed by pasteurization process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Vat Pasteurization is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) batch pasteurization",
            "b) HTST pasteurization",
            "c) UHT pasteurization",
            "d) coldpasteurization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A pasteurization process usually operates to 6 log reductions of the target organism. The sterilized foods have to achieve at least 12 log reductions in case of Clostridium botulinum spores. The pasteurization has lower log reductions because of the reduced risks linked with the target microbial species when associated with the botulinum toxin.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "One pasteurization unit is the microorganism death that occurs in a product held at _______for 1 minute for beer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60°C",
            "b) 70°C",
            "c) 80°C",
            "d) 50°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pasteurization kills the pathogens and reduces the number of spoilage causing microbes while maintaining food quality. Raw milk is hazardous because it can contain pathogens like E. coli,tuberculosis bacillus, salmonella, listeria and campylobacter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "What is the pasteurization temperature of egg?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 140F for 2 minutes",
            "b) 145F for 2 minutes",
            "c) 145F for 3 minutes",
            "d) 140F for 3 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vat Pasteurization is also known as the holding method or batch pasteurization. Every particle of milk or cream is heated in equipment at 145°F (63°C) and hold for 30 minutes. Agitation is needed to achieve the appropriate consistency and texture and uniform heating or else it causes churning.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "Where should a sterilization indicator placed in an autoclave?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At the center",
            "b) Close to lid of the autoclave",
            "c) Sides of the autoclave",
            "d) Anywhere inside the autoclave"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The best place to keep the biological indicator in the autoclave is at center of the load. Autoclave tape is used in autoclaving to indicate whether a specific temperature has been reached.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following is target microbe in commercial sterilization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudomonas aeruginosa",
            "b) Bacillus anthracis",
            "c) Salmonella typhi",
            "d) Clostridium botulinum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Commercial Sterilization is defined as the thermal process intended to ensure safety of a shelf stable food product. In most cases, the process is applied to a food after the product is packed in a container. Clostridium botulinum is target microbe in commercial sterilization.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "____________ is used for sterilizing inoculating loops.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flaming",
            "b) Incineration",
            "c) Hot air oven",
            "d) Steam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flaming is used for sterilizing metallic devices like needles, scissors. Incineration is used particularly for inoculating loops used in microbe cultures. The hot air oven is appropriate for dry material like glass ware, powders and metal devices.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Who developed steam sterilizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Louis Pasteur",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Nicolas Appert",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sterilization process consists of 3 phases. They are i) Heating Phase where the product temperature is increased from ambient to the required sterilization temperature. ii) Holding phase where the temperature is maintained for a defined time. iii) Cooling phase where the temperature in the can is decreased by using cold water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "_______ is the quickest way to sterilize solutions without heating.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filtration",
            "b) Chemical method of sterilization",
            "c) Steam Sterilization",
            "d) Chlorine dioxide gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pasteurization process was developed by Louis Pasteur. Charles Chamberland developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Nicolas Appert is the father of food technology. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "_______ is used for sterilizing metallic devices like needles, scalpels.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flaming",
            "b) Incineration",
            "c) Hot air oven",
            "d) Steam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sterilization can be achieved by using irradiation, high pressure, chemicals, chlorine dioxide gas, heat, filtration, ultraviolet radiation. The UV rays, X-rays, gamma rays are exposed on the packed materials for sterilization. The UV radiation has low penetration power. It is less effective but is safe compared to other rays.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "The sterilization of ________ is generally carried out by retorts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) low carbohydrate foods",
            "b) low acid foods",
            "c) high acid foods",
            "d) medium acid foods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Filtration is the fastest way to sterilize solutions without heating. In this method the filters with a pore diameter of 0.2 um are used for the removal of bacteria. But they cannot be used to remove fungi and virus as they are in smaller size compared to bacteria.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Who designed refrigerator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oliver Evans",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Nicolas Appert",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oliver Evans designed refrigerator. Charles Chamberl and developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Nicolas Appert is the father of food technology. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "The first ice making machine used brewing was invented by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) James Harrison",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Nicolas Appert",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first ice making machine used brewing was invented by James Harrison. Charles Chamberland developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Nicolas Appert is the father of food technology. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Modern refrigerators usually use a refrigerant called ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HFC-134a",
            "b) CFC-134a",
            "c) HFC-1a",
            "d) HC-13a"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Modern refrigerators use a refrigerant called HFC-134a. IUPAC name of HFC-134a is 1,1,1,2-Tetrafluoroethane. This is generally accepted because of its nature, it does not deplete the ozone layer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "___________ is the difference between the boiling point temperature of the refrigerant in the evaporator coil and the actual temperature of the refrigerant gas as it leaves the evaporator.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superheat",
            "b) Critical point",
            "c) Supercool",
            "d) Drastic point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Superheat is the difference between the refrigerant‘s boiling point temperature in the evaporator coil and actual temperature of the refrigerant when it leaves the evaporator. This is also known as metastable state. In this state the boiling can happen at any time, depending on the internal or external effects.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "_____________ freezers are used for deep freezing fish fillets.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air blast",
            "b) Slow type",
            "c) Normal",
            "d) Low velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Air blast freezers are used for deep freezing fish fillets. In these freezers, the freezing process at a desired temperature takes place rapidly which varies from product to product. The micro crystallization takes place and thus preserving all the nutrients of the food. Once defrost is done, then there is no loss of firmness, liquid, and flavor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "The principle of flash cooling is achieved in _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) thermoelectric refrigeration",
            "b) steam-jet refrigeration",
            "c) evaporative cooling",
            "d) absorption refrigeration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Some of the natural refrigerants are water, air, CO2, ammonia and hydrocarbons like propane, isobutene and propene. Natural refrigerants are the chemicals which are obtained from nature’s bio-chemical processes. They do not deplete the ozone layer and make a negligible contribution to global warming.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "In the _____________, an electric current sent through a junction of two dissimilar materials results in either a heating or cooling of the junction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peltier effect",
            "b) See-beck effect",
            "c)Joule effect",
            "d) Thomson effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Steam-jet refrigeration is employed by chemical agent machines to achieve mechanical refrigeration. Water is used as refrigerant. These are used where chilled water is required where the temperature is more than 5°C. The principle of flash cooling is achieved in steam-jet refrigeration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Dry ice is the solid form of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbon dioxide",
            "b) Sulphur dioxide",
            "c) ammonium choride",
            "d) carbontetraoxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the Peltier effect, which is the inverse of the See-beck effect, an electric current is sent through a junction of two dissimilar materials results in either a cooling or heating of the junction. When the current flows in the direction of the potential drop of the junction, then the junction’s temperature decreases and thus has a refrigerating effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "What are ideal conditions for evaporative cooling system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hot and humid conditions",
            "b) Hot and dry conditions",
            "c) Cold and humid conditions",
            "d) Cold and dry conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dry ice is the solid form of carbon dioxide. It is widely used as cooling agent. The advantages of using dry ice are that it has lower temperature compared to water ice and it does not leave any residue.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Who invented chillers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Louis Pasteur",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Willis Carrier",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pasteurization process was developed by Louis Pasteur. Charles Chamberland developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Willis Carrier invented the chillers. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "_________ is used for cooling of products, mechanisms and factory machinery under control temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chiller",
            "b) Ice",
            "c) Alcohol",
            "d) Ice or alcohol according to the product"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chillers are used for cooling of products, mechanisms and factory machinery under control temperature. These follow absorption refrigerant cycle or vapor compressionfor cooling a fluid. The basic principle is that heat always flows from hot to cold.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "What is the ideal chilled water temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 42°F",
            "b) 52°F",
            "c) 49°F",
            "d) 50°F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 42°F is the ideal chilled water temperature. The temperature of chilled water can range from 35 to 45 °F (2 to 7 °C), depending upon requirements.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "__________ invented the quick freezing method in 1924.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clarence Birdseye",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Willis Carrier",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Clarence Birdseye invented the quick freezing method. Charles Chamberland developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Willis Carrier invented the chillers. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "______ chillers are also called as centrifugal chiller type refrigeration systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low-pressure",
            "b) Low-temperature",
            "c) Low-velocity",
            "d) High-pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Low-pressure chillers are also called as centrifugal chiller type refrigeration systems. It works under vacuum in the evaporator section of the system. If there is any leaks in the low pressure portions of the system, it will draw in the atmospheric air and moisture from the surroundings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "________ chiller is powered by a heat source like steam and uses no moving parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absorption",
            "b) Reciprocating",
            "c) Centrifugal",
            "d) Screw driven"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In absorption chillers, the refrigerant is absorbed by a liquid sorbent. The refrigerant  used are water and ammonia and liquid sorbents arelithium bromide or water. At high temperatures, the refrigerant is desorbed from solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "________ chillers are volume displacement units.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absorption",
            "b) Reciprocating",
            "c) Centrifugal",
            "d) Screw driven"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Centrifugal chillers are volume displacement units. The advantages are compact size, high operational efficiency at full load. It is not suitable for air cooled condenser options and requires cooling water tower and water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Freezer burn is a condition that occurs when frozen food has been damaged by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dehydration",
            "b) oxidation",
            "c) dehydration and oxidation",
            "d) dehydration and reduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Freezer burn occurs when frozen food is damaged by dehydration and oxidation. It is normally due to improper of storage of food. Therefore, it should be securely wrapped in air-tight packaging to prevent oxidation and dehydration. The food appears grayish brown leathery spots on the frozen foods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "_______ is used to freeze particulate foods like peas, cut corn.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluidized bed freezer",
            "b) Plate freezer",
            "c) Cryogenic freezers",
            "d) Belt freezer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fluidized bed freezer is used to freeze particulate foods like peas, cut corn. The foods are placed on a mesh and moved through a freezing zone where cold air in upward direction is directed through the mesh belt and the food particulates begin to float. This leads to uniform freezing in all directions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "_______ is used to freeze food at a tremendously fast rate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluidized bed freezer",
            "b) Plate freezer",
            "c) Cryogenic freezers",
            "d) Belt freezer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cryogenic freezing is used to freeze food at a tremendously fast rate. The food is moved through a spray of liquid nitrogen. It can also be directly immersed in liquid nitrogen. The liquid nitrogen boils at a temperature of −196 °C around the food and thus extracts a huge amount of heat at faster pace.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Lyophilization is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) freezedrying",
            "b) sundrying",
            "c) tunneldrying",
            "d) mechanicaldrying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lyophilization is also called as freeze drying. It is a process where biological material is preserved by removing the water from sample. It is a twostep process, first the sample is freeze and then dry it under a vacuum at low temperatures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "What is a triple point of pure water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -0.01°C",
            "b) 0.01°C",
            "c) 0.1°C",
            "d) -0.1°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The triple point of pure water is at 0.01°C. The triple point is the condition in which the temperature and pressure of all three phases (gas, liquid and solid) can coexist in equilibrium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Phase diagram is a graphical representation of the ________ states of a substance under different conditions of temperature and pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) physical",
            "b) chemical",
            "c) electromagnetic",
            "d) mechanical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phase diagram is a graphical depiction of the physical conditions of a matter under different conditions of temperature and pressure. It has temperature on the x-axis and pressure on the y-axis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "__________ diagrams represent the phase behavior of mixtures containing three components.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ternary phase",
            "b) Tertiary phase",
            "c) Tri phase",
            "d) Term phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ternary phase represents the behavior of three components in a mixture with a triangular diagram. These diagrams provide the data which is precise and accurate of the various components.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "The effect of ______on the system is seen only as a phase change.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Latent heat",
            "b) Specific heat",
            "c) Enthalpy",
            "d) Entropy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Latent heat can be defined as the heat that is released or absorbed by a system during constant temperature process. The effect is seen only as a phase change like boiling of water or the melting of ice.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "The term triple point was coined by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rudolf Clausius",
            "b) Thomas Young",
            "c) Joseph Black",
            "d) James Thomson"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rudolf Clausius invented the term entropy. Thomas Young invented the term enthalpy. Joseph Black invented the term latent heat. The term triple point was coined by James Thomson.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "What is the critical point of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 374°C",
            "b) 157.5°C",
            "c) 31.0°C",
            "d) 240.9°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The critical point of water is 374°C. The critical point of sulphuric acid is 157.5°C. The critical point of supercritical carbon dioxideis 31.0°C. The critical point of ethanol is 240.9°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "What are factors depending on rate of drying?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial moisture content of the product",
            "b) Composition of raw material",
            "c) Temperature, relative humidity",
            "d) Initial moisture content, composition, temperature, relative humidity of the product."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Drying rate is defined as the mass of water removed per unit time per unit area. It depends on initial moisture content, composition, temperature, relative humidity of the product, Size, shape and arrangement of stacking of the raw material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Who discovered critical point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joseph Black",
            "b) Charles Cagniard de la Tour",
            "c) Henri Becquerel",
            "d) Stephen Gray"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Joseph Black discovered latent heat. Charles Cagniard de la Tour discovered critical piont. Henri Becquerel discovered radiation. Stephen Gray discovered electrical conduction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "_____________ is the amount of moisture a material will absorb relative to ambient temperature and humidity conditions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lyophilization",
            "b) Hygroscopic action",
            "c) Hydrophobic action",
            "d) Hydrophilic action"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hygroscopic action is the amount of moisture a material will absorb with respect to the temperature and humidity conditions. Due to hydroscopic action, the sample will continuously increase/ decrease in weight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "The measure of moisture content during thermogravimetric analysis is by the process of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) water vaporization",
            "b) freezing",
            "c) oven drying",
            "d) sun drying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In thermogravimetric analysis, the moisture is determined by the loss of mass of a substance (normally moisture) when heated. This can be achieved by the water vaporization process. It is a complete, precise and approachable method to determine moisture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Halogen and infrared drying are the examples of _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) thermogravimetric analysis",
            "b) freeze drying",
            "c) non thermal analysis",
            "d) pressure based analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Halogen and infrared drying are the examples of thermogravimetric analysis. Halogen drying is up to twice as fast as traditional infrared technology. It is a complete, precise and approachable method to determine moisture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "The oven drying methodology consists of heating by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) conduction",
            "b) convection",
            "c) radiation",
            "d) both radiation and convection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most commonly used method for commercial purposes is oven drying methods for commercial purposes. The oven drying methodology consists of heating by convection. The demerits of this process are time and non-portability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "______________ of moisture measurement is based on chemical reactions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lyophilization",
            "b) Karl Fischer method",
            "c) Halogen drying",
            "d) Infrared drying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Karl Fischer Method of moisture measurement is based on chemical reactions. A chemical reaction happens where the water is separated chemically from the rest of the sample.  The water is then moved to other cell where it is measured.  That measurement is equated with the initial mass of the sample and then moisture content is calculated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "_________ method id based on dielectric principle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric moisture meter",
            "b) Karl Fischer method",
            "c) Lyophilization",
            "d) Infrared drying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electric moisture meter method id based on dielectric principle. The electricity is measured by capacitance, conductance and radio frequency. They are inexpensive, easy to use and portable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "What is best method to use when the product have multiple layers that may have very different moisture levels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lyophilization",
            "b) Karl Fischer method",
            "c) Halogen drying",
            "d) Microwave moisture meter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Microwave moisture meter is best method to use when the product have multiple layers that may have very different moisture levels.In microwave method, the microwave is generally transmitted entirely through the samples.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is non-destructive moisture measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karl Fischer method",
            "b) Nuclear moisture meter method",
            "c) Loss on drying moisture method",
            "d) Lyophilization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the Nuclear moisture meter technology, the energy is radiated into the sample and the amount of energy absorbed by the sample is measured. Beta radiation and gamma radiations are used for moisture determination. The relationship between absorbed energy and moisture content is then calculated to generate a calibration curve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "__________ uses reflectance & absorbance principles for calculating the moisture content.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karl Fischer method",
            "b) Nuclear moisture meter method",
            "c) Loss on drying moisture meter method",
            "d) Near infrared moisture meter method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Near infrared moisture meter method uses absorbance and reflectance principles for determining the moisture content. This meter focuses a beam of light on the product and then the light is filtered to a wavelength that excites the moisture molecules. The higher the amount of moisture content, higher is the amount of light absorbed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "The fundamental principle behind Karl Fischer method is based on the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bunsen reaction on iodine in an aqueous medium",
            "b) bunsen reaction between iodine and sulphuric acid in an aqueous medium",
            "c) bunsen reaction between iodine and carbon dioxide in an aqueous medium",
            "d) bunsen reaction between iodine and sulfur dioxide in an aqueous medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The fundamental principle behind Karl Fischer method is based on the bunsen reaction between iodine and sulfur dioxide in an aqueous medium where a primary alcohol like methanol is used as the solvent, and a base such as pyridine is used as the buffering agent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "What is psychometric chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the graphical representation of thermodynamic properties",
            "b) It is the graphical representation of chemical properties",
            "c) It is the graphical representation of drying properties",
            "d) It is the graphical representation of mechanical properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Psychometric chart is a graphical representation of thermodynamic properties of moist air at one atmosphere like wet bulb temperature, dry bulb temperature, dew point temperature, humidity ratio, relative humidity, specific volume and enthalpy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Who invented the psychometric chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dr Richard Seligman",
            "b) George Babcock",
            "c) George Brayton",
            "d) Willis H. Carrier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dr Richard Seligman invented heat exchanger. George Babcock invented boiler. George Brayton invented engine. Willis H. Carrier invented psychometric chart.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Which lines indicate wet bulb temperatures in the psychometric charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagonals lines",
            "b) Vertical lines",
            "c) Horizontal lines",
            "d) Curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The temperature read by the thermometer where the bulb of thermometer is enclosedwith a wet cloth is called as wet bulb temperature. If the reading of the wet bulb temperature is lower, this indicates that the surroundings have lower humidity.When the relative humidity is 100%, then wet bulb temperature is equal to the air temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Which lines indicate dry bulb temperatures in the psychometric chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagonals lines",
            "b) Vertical lines",
            "c) Horizontal lines",
            "d) Curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:The dry-bulb temperature is defined as the temperature of air which is measured by a thermometer that is freely exposed to the air, but protected from radiation and the moisture content. It is the true thermodynamic temperature.Dry bulb temperatures in the psychometric charts areindicated by vertical lines.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Which lines indicate relative humidity in the psychometric charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagonals lines",
            "b) Vertical lines",
            "c) Horizontal lines",
            "d) Curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The relative humidity is defined as the amount of water vapor present in air.It is normally expressed as a percentage of the amount needed for saturation at the same temperature. Relative humidity in the psychometric charts is indicated by curves.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "What is another name for humidity ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixing ratio",
            "b) Water ratio",
            "c) Relative humidity ratio",
            "d) Bound water ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Humidity ratio is the fraction of mass of water vapor per unit mass of dry air at the given conditions thermodynamic conditions. It is known as the moisture content or the mixing ratio. It is typically plotted as the ordinate on the vertical axis of the graph.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Who invented the sling psychrometrer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sir John Leslie",
            "b) Leonardo da Vinci",
            "c) George Babcock",
            "d) George Brayton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sir John Leslie invented the sling psychrometrer. A sling psychrometer is an instrument that measures the dew point and relative humidity in an area. It has two thermometers, they are a wet bulb and a dry bulb.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "What is wet bulb depression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference between dry bulb temperature and wet bulb temperature at any point",
            "b) Difference between relative humidity and wet bulb temperature at any point",
            "c) Difference between dew point and wet bulb temperature at any point",
            "d) Difference between dry bulb temperature and dew point temperature at any point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The wet bulb depression is defined as the difference between dry bulb temperature and wet bulb temperature at any point. It indicates relative humidity of the air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "What is dew point depression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference between dry bulb temperature and dew point temperature of air",
            "b) Difference between wet bulb temperature and dew point temperature of air",
            "c) Difference between relative humidity and dew point temperature of air",
            "d) Difference between wet bulb depression and dew point temperature of air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dew point depression is defined as the difference between dry bulb temperature and dew point temperature of air. As the dew point depression deals with the moisture in the atmosphere, it is very important in forest, agricultural and particularly in forecasting wildfires.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "The capillary condensation theory plays a major role in ________ equation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kelvin",
            "b) Harkins-Jura",
            "c) Chung-Pfost",
            "d) Henderson"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Kelvin equation depends on the relationship between vapor pressure of water present in capillary and saturated vapor pressure at same temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Henderson equation is based on ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) gibbs adsorption",
            "b) enthalpy",
            "c) latent heat",
            "d) entropy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gibbs adsorption relates to the change in concentration of a component in contact with surface with change in surface tension, which results in corresponding change in surface entry which is explained in Henderson equation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "The _______is the average material moisture content at which the drying rate begins to decline.",
        "Options": [
            "a) critical moisture content",
            "b) equilibrium moisture content",
            "c) free moisture content",
            "d) bound moisture content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The critical moisture content is the average material moisture content at which the drying rate begins to decline. It depends upon the ease of moisture movement through the solid, and hence, upon the pore structure of the solid, sample thickness and drying rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "What is hysteresis effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference between desorption and adsorption curve",
            "b) Difference between desorption and absorption curve",
            "c) Difference between relative humidity and adsorption curve",
            "d) Difference between relative humidity and absorption curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hysteresis effect is defined as the difference between desorption and adsorption curve. This effect is detected due to the shrinkage effect during desorption that changes the water binding properties of the food product. Therefore, same path of EMC is not observed during adsorption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "__________ was used to describe relationship between the water activity and equilibrium moisture content.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kelvin model",
            "b) Harkins-Jura model",
            "c) Chung-Pfost model",
            "d) GAB model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: GAB modelwas used to describe relationship between the water activity and equilibrium moisture content. In Guggenheim, Anderson, de Boer (GAB) model, the sample is kept in the desiccators which contains saturated Potassium nitrate solution to maintain the relative humidity at 90% at 40°C and are kept in a temperature controlled chamber.  Moisture content and water activity of each sample is determined using hot air oven and water activity meter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "__________ equation is based on potential field theory.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kelvin",
            "b) Harkins-Jura",
            "c) Chung-Pfost",
            "d) Henderson"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moisture sorption isotherm is a graph where it indicates water activity where the water is adsorbed into and desorbed from a product held at constant temperature. This relationship is complex and unique for each product. Water activity almost always increases as moisture content increases, but the relationship is not linear.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Harkins-Jura equation does not predict satisfactory EMC values when relative humidity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) more than 30%",
            "b) more than 40%",
            "c) more than 50%",
            "d) more than 60%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chung-Pfost equation is based on potential field theory. This equation provides fairly accurate EMC values of grains between 20 to 90% relative humidity values.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "The __________ helps to decide the stability of food at particular moisture content in the given environment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) equilibrium moisture content",
            "b) psychometric charts",
            "c) equilibrium moisture content and psychometric charts",
            "d) chemical properties and psychometric charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Harkins-Jura equation does not predict satisfactory EMC values when relative humidity is more than 30%. In this equation, it deals with the work required to absorb or desorb a water molecules, the sum of work required to overcome vapor molecule to come on the surface and work necessary for condensation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "What is the relationship between equilibrium moisture content (EMC) and free moisture content (FMC)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FMC=Total water content -EMC",
            "b) FMC=Total water content + EMC",
            "c) FMC=Total water content × EMC",
            "d) Total water content = EMC × FMC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The equilibrium moisture content helps to decide the stability of food at particular moisture content in the given environment. It depends on the partial pressure of the water vapor in the surrounding air and relatively weak on the air temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "What happens to the drying rate when it reaches critical moisture content?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Declines",
            "b) Increases gradually",
            "c) Stops",
            "d) Becomes constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rate of drying depends on 1) equilibrium vapor pressure of water in the food 2) moisture of the food 3) vapor pressure of water at drying temperature and 4) vapor pressure in the external environment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "What is the independent factor of the constant rate period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moisture content",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Pressure",
            "d) Humidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Latent heat of vaporization is necessary as it converts its liquid into vapor and the moisture must be transported out from the food to obtain dehydrated product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "At what stage the case hardening of a material takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant rate period",
            "b) Falling rate period",
            "c) Initial rate period",
            "d) Equilibrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The critical moisture content is defined as the average material moisture content at which the drying rate begins to decrease. The point that shifts to the Declining drying period from Constant drying period is known as critical moisture content\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Name the phenomenon which transfers moisture during second falling drying rate period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid diffusion",
            "b) Capillary movement",
            "c) Vapor diffusion",
            "d) Liquid diffusion, capillary movement, and vapor diffusion."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The constant rate period is independent of moisture content in the rate of drying curve. In this period, diffusion of moisture takes place where the droplet maintains saturated surface conditions and the evaporation takes place at constant rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "What type of drying takes place when the food has high fat contents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slow",
            "b) Fast",
            "c) Constant",
            "d) Quick"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The case hardening is defined as the formation of a hard skin on the surface of foods which slows down the drying rate and may leads to the mold growth. It is due to quick drying during the constant rate period and this can be stopped by using cooler drying air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "How does humidity affect drying rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No effect",
            "b) Directly proportional",
            "c) Indirect proportional",
            "d) Linear increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During second falling drying rate period, the moisture transfer is due to the liquid diffusion, capillary movement, and vapor diffusion because the drying rate becomes independent of conditions outside the solid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "What is drying constant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanisms of heat and mass transport phenomena",
            "b) Mechanism of heat phenomena",
            "c) Mechanism of mass transport phenomena",
            "d) Mechanism of drying phenomena"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Higher fat contents results in the slower drying rate as water is trapped within the food. The size of the food affects the drying rate in both the constant and falling rate periods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "What happens to the drying rate during constant rate of drying period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It reduces",
            "b) It increases",
            "c) Constant",
            "d) Becomes negligible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of evaporation depends mainly on the relative humidity than on the temperature. But both the relative humidity and temperature are correlated. When the air temperature increases, it absorbs more liquid and the relative humidity decreases. Low relative humidity helps in faster drying.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Why meats are not recommended for out-of-doors drying?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meats are high in protein, making them ideal for microbial growth",
            "b) Meat gets decomposed easily",
            "c) Meat absorbs the outdoor odours",
            "d) Vitamin B12 is lost during sun drying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Meats are high in protein, making them ideal for microbial growth. Along with the microbial spoilage it can also undergo oxidation and enzymatic autolysis which further decreases the quality of the meat.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "What is hybrid solar dryer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is designed and constructed using direct solar energy and a heat exchanger.",
            "b) It represents solar dyer but uses irradiation instead of sun rays",
            "c) It is designed and constructed using direct solar energy and irradiation rays",
            "d) It is used for only hybrid and genetically modified foods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A hybrid solar dryer was designed and constructed using direct solar energy and a heat exchanger. The dryer was operated during normal sunny days as a solar dryer. Drying is carried out at night with stored heat energy in water which was collected during the sun-shine time and with electric heaters.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "What is the lower limit of moisture content by sun drying method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15%",
            "b) 10%",
            "c) 8%",
            "d) 13%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lower limit of moisture content by sun drying method is approximately 15%. For sun drying of foods, hot days are required with minimum temperatures of 35°C and also with the low humidity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "What are the modes of heat transfer employed in solar drying systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiation and convection",
            "b) Conduction and convection",
            "c) Conduction and radiation",
            "d) Radiation and conduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In sun drying, the product is exposed directly to solar radiation and more or less effectively to the wind. In solar drying, the produce is contained in an enclosed space, and the air in contact with it is heated by solar radiation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "What type of air temperature and humidity do the solar driers generate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highair temperature, lowhumidity",
            "b) Lowair temperature, high humidity",
            "c) Lowair temperature, lowhumidity",
            "d) Highair temperature, highhumidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The location for the sun drying is selected to take the maximum advantage of climatic conditions. Low lying swampy areas with a high relative humidity should be avoided and racks should be sited away from forests or high buildings which will reduce the air movement or cast a shadow over the racks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "What are advantages of sun drying?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Economical and environmentally friendly",
            "b) Fast drying and environmentally friendly",
            "c) Environmentally friendly",
            "d) Economical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Solar drying systems can be categorized mostly on the basis of the mode of transfer of heat engaged. These are radiation and forced convection. Drying is a twofold process which includes 1.The heat transfer to the product from a heating source and 2.Mass transfer of moisture from the interior of the product to its surface and from the surface to the surrounding air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an important parameter in sun drying rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Convective heat transfer coefficient",
            "b) Conductive heat transfer coefficient",
            "c) Mass transfer coefficient",
            "d) Dynamic mass transfer coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solar dryer is designed to collect and enhance solar radiation. This drier is faster than sun drying and also requires less drying area but cannot be used on cloudy days.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "What is alternative name for freeze drying?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lyophilisation",
            "b) Cold pasteurization",
            "c) Irradiation",
            "d) Liposuction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The freeze drying is also known as lyophilisation where a low temperature dehydration process takes place. This involves 1.Freezing the product 2. Lowering the pressure and then removing the ice by the sublimation process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "What is cryodesiccation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freeze drying",
            "b) Cold pasteurization",
            "c) Irradiation",
            "d) Dehydration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The freeze drying is also known as cryodesiccation. In this process, dehydration takes place at a very low temperature. This is divergence to the dehydration by all the conservative methods that vaporize water using the heat.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "During the primary drying phase in freeze drying, What is necessary to calculate amount of heat required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By using latent heat of sublimation",
            "b) By using latent heat of vapourization",
            "c) By using enthaply",
            "d) By using specific heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the primary drying phase in freeze drying, the pressure is lowered and heat is given to the product for the ice sublimation. The amount of heat necessary is calculated using the latent heat of sublimation of the sublimating molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Which of the following governs the process in secondary drying in freeze drying?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Latent heat of sublimation",
            "b) Latent heat of vapourization",
            "c) Enthaply",
            "d) Adsorption isotherms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The secondary drying phase of the freeze-drying process is overseen by the adsorption isotherms of the material. In this phase, the temperature is raised greater than in the primary drying phaseto disrupt any physicochemical interfaces that have formed between the frozen material and water molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "At what point the ice crystal formation takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the material is cooled below itstriple point",
            "b) When the material is cooled below its freezing point",
            "c) When the material is cooled below its dew point",
            "d) When the material is cooled above its triple point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the freezing stage, the product is cooled below its triple point, this is achieved to ensure that melting does not takes place. Triple point is the lowest temperature at which the liquid, solid and gas stages of the material can coexist.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "What is the main advantage of annealing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is done to achieve largeice crystals",
            "b) It is done to achieve smallice crystals",
            "c) It is done to achieve microscopicice crystals",
            "d) It is done to achieve mixture of large and small ice crystals all"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The large ice crystals promote faster removal of water vapor due to formation of a network within the product during sublimation. Therefore annealing is done to achieve larger crystals where the product is slowly frozen.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known to result in the highest quality of foods amongst all drying techniques?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freeze drying",
            "b) Cold pasteurization",
            "c) Osmotic dehyradtion",
            "d) Evaporation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Freeze drying produces highest quality of foods amongst all other drying techniques. This is mainly due to structural integrity and preservation of flavors of the product during the freezing process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "How long does freeze drying take?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 40 hours",
            "b) 20 to 40 hours",
            "c) 30 to 50 hours",
            "d) 5 to 20 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It takes between 20 to 40 hours to complete the process. Food type, quantity, thickness affects the freeze-dry cycle. Products like peas, meat, corn dry quickly whereas squash can take longer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "What foods cannot be freeze dried?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Foods with high fiber content",
            "b) Foods with high Vitamin B12 content",
            "c) Foods with high protein content",
            "d) Foods with high fat content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Most of the foods are suitable for freeze drying like fruits, vegetables, dairy products, meat, dry liquids like soup or yogurt and instant coffee. Foods with high fat are not suitable for freeze drying as the fat melts damages the equipment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Who discovered freeze drying?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jacques-Arsened’Arsonval",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Willis Carrier",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jacques-Arsened’Arsonval discovered freeze drying. Charles Chamberl and developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Willis Carrier invented the chillers. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following dryer is used for pureed raw ingredients that are dried at relatively low temperatures over rotating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluidized bed dryer",
            "b) Drum dryer",
            "c) Cabinet tray dryer",
            "d) Pneumatic dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the drum dryer, the pureed raw ingredients are dried at low temperatures over rotating. The additional advantage of this drier is that product is milled to produce powder or flakes form.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Which of the following dryer is used to produce powder from the solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spray dryer",
            "b) Cabinet tray dryer",
            "c) Pneumatic dryer",
            "d) Fluidized bed dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spray dyer is used to produce powder from the solution. It dries the solution stream and separates the solute and evaporates the solvent and forms vapor. The solid particles are collected in a cyclone or drum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Who invented spray dryer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Samuel Percy",
            "b) Fritz Winkler",
            "c) John A",
            "d) Jacques-Arsened’Arsonva"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Samuel Percy invented spray dryer. Fritz Winkler invented fluidized bed dryer. John A invented drum dryer. Jacques-Arsened’Arsonva invented freeze dryer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "What is the alternative name for batch-in-bin dryer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat bed dryer",
            "b) Cabinet tray dryer",
            "c) Pneumatic dryer",
            "d) Fluidized bed dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Batch-in-bin dryer is also known as flat bed dyer. Its capacity is of 1-3 tons per day with 6-12 hours of drying times. The batch-in-bin dryer is easy to construct and is inexpensive and simple to operate and require unskilled labor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "What is full form of LSU dryer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Louisiana State University dryer",
            "b) Low simple universal dryer",
            "c) Low and slow unit dryer",
            "d) Level steady unit dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Louisiana State University dryer, the drying section contains vertical compartment across which rows of air channels are fitted. Alternate rows are closedwhere the moving stream of grain from the top descends thus providing considerable mixing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "What does Fritz Winkler invented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluidized bed dryer",
            "b) Drum dryer",
            "c) Spray dryer",
            "d) Freeze dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: LSU is a continuous flow mixing type of dryer. LSU dryer is mainly used to dry the grains. It is popular in India and USA. The capital investment is high. The recommended air flow rate is 60-70m3/ min/ ton.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Which dryer is used to dry the material almost instantaneously in a turbulent stream of hot air?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluidized bed dryer",
            "b) Drum dryer",
            "c) Cabinet tray dryer",
            "d) Pneumatic dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:Samuel Percy invented spray dryer. Fritz Winkler invented fluidized bed dryer. John A invented drum dryer. Jacques-Arsened’Arsonva invented freeze dryer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Which of the following dryer is the convectional drying equipment with enclosed insulated chambers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluidized bed dryer",
            "b) Drum dryer",
            "c) Cabinet tray dryer",
            "d) Pneumatic dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In pneumatic dryer, the material is dried almost instantaneously in a turbulent stream of hot air. This can also acts as conveyor system. It is applicable to powdered, granular, and flaky materials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "What type of dryer is used for the drying of substances which are hygroscopic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluidized bed dryer",
            "b) Drum dryer",
            "c) Cabinet tray dryer",
            "d) Vacuum dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cabinet tray dryer is conventional drying equipment with enclosed insulated chambers. The trays are placed on top of each other in a trolley. The mode of heat transfer is forced convention.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "What are modes of heat transfer in evaporators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conduction and convention",
            "b) Conduction and radiation",
            "c) Radiation and convention",
            "d) Conduction, convention, radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heat transfer in evaporators is governed by conduction and convention. Calculations on evaporators can be supported by combining mass and energy balances with the principles of heat transfer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "What controls the overall heat transfer coefficient in falling film evaporators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Film thickness",
            "b) Velocity",
            "c) Liquid properties",
            "d) Film thickness, velocity, liquid properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Falling film evaporators controls the overall heat transfer coefficient by difference in temperature, thickness of the film, properties of the liquid, velocity across the film layer. These are important design modules which help in high heat transfer rates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "What is the cause of convection heat transfer in evaporators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Convection is heat transfer by neutrons",
            "b) Convection is heat transfer by mass motion of a heat source",
            "c) Convection is mass transfer by mass motion of a fluid",
            "d) Convection is heat transfer by mass motion of a fluid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Convection is heat transfer by mass motion of a fluid like water, air. Due to this movement the heated fluid moves away from the source of heat and thus carrying energy with it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "What is conduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conduction is heat transfer by means of molecular agitation",
            "b) Conduction is mass transfer by means of molecular agitation",
            "c) Conduction is heat transfer by means of electron agitation",
            "d) Conduction is heat transfer by means of atom agitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is heat transfer by molecular agitation within a material without any motion of the material as a whole. If one end of a metal rod is heated, the energy transfers toward the colder end as the higher speed particles collides with the slower ones with a net transfer of energy to the slower ones.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "What is evaporation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process of substance in a liquid state changing to a gaseous state",
            "b) Process of substance in a solid state changing to a gaseous state",
            "c) Process of substance in a liquid state changing to a solid state",
            "d) Process of substance in a gaseous state changing to a liquid state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Evaporation is the process of a substance in a liquid state changing to a gaseous state due to an increase in temperature and pressure.When the molecules of the liquid collide, they transfer energy to each other.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "What are the principle functions of evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat exchanger and separator",
            "b) Heat exchanger",
            "c) Heat exchanger",
            "d) Evaporate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The basic factors that affect the rate of evaporation are i) Rate of heat transfer to the liquid, ii) Quantity of heat required to evaporate each kg of water, iii) Maximum allowable temperature of the liquid, iv) Pressure at which the evaporation takes place, v) Changes that occur in the product during the evaporation process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "What is meant by heat transfer coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The heat transfer coefficient is the heat transferred per unit volume per kelvin",
            "b) The heat transfer coefficient is the heat transferred per unit area per kelvin",
            "c) The heat transfer coefficient is the heat transferred per unit volume per Celsius",
            "d) The heat transfer coefficient is the heat transferred per unit area per Celsius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heat exchanger and separator are the two main principle functions of evaporator. Evaporation is used to pre-concentrate food, to increase the solid content of food and to reduce the water content of a liquid product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "How do you increase heat transfer coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By increasing Reynolds number",
            "b) By decreasing Reynolds number",
            "c) By increasing velocity",
            "d) By increasing Reynolds number and velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the heat transferred per unit area per kelvin. The area included in the equation represents the area over which the heat transfer takes place. The areas for each flow are different as they signify the contact area for each fluid side.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "What factors affect heat transfer coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscosity, density, specific heat",
            "b) Viscosity",
            "c) Density",
            "d) Specific heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To increase the heat transfer coefficient by increasing Reynolds number and velocity of fluid when it flows through a pipe. This is due to higher velocity increases turbulence, which in turn provides a more efficient radial transport of heat.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "What are the three functional sections present in evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat exchanger, evaporating section",
            "b) Heat exchanger, separator",
            "c) Separator, evaporating section",
            "d) Heat exchanger, evaporating section, separator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The evaporator is made up of three functional sections. They are the heat exchanger, the evaporating section, where the liquid boils and evaporates, and the separator in which the vapour leaves the liquid and passes off to the condenser or to other equipment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "What are the advantages of multiple effect evaporators over single effect evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suitable for large scale operation",
            "b) Suitable for continuous operation",
            "c) Maximize the energy input required for evaporating",
            "d) Suitable for large scale and for continuous operation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Advantages of multiple effect evaporators are suitable for large scale and for continuous operation. It is highly economical when compared to single effect.  Multiple effects are used to minimize the energy input required to evaporate undesirable water content.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Who invented the multiple-effect evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Norbert Rillieux",
            "b) Justus von Liebig",
            "c) Nils Wallerius",
            "d) Rudolf Clausius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Norbert Rillieux invented multiple-effect evaporator. Justus von Liebig invented water cooled condenser. Nils Wallerius discovered evaporation. Rudolf Clausius invented the term entropy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Who discovered evaporation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Norbert Rillieux",
            "b) Justus von Liebig",
            "c) Nils Wallerius",
            "d) Rudolf Clausius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In forward feed, the most concentrated liquids will occur in the last effect. The liquid feed progress is simple as it passes from effect one to otherand therefore it does not require pumping for the feed to flow. But in backward feed, the liquid is pumped from one effect to the next against the pressure drops.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "What is the steam economy of single effect evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8",
            "b) 1.3",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 5.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Norbert Rillieux invented multiple-effect evaporator. Justus von Liebig invented water cooled condenser. Nils Wallerius discovered evaporation. Rudolf Clausius invented the term entropy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "What are the different modes of feed in multiple effect evaporators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forward feed arrangement",
            "b) Backward feed arrangement",
            "c) Forward feed arrangement and backward feed arrangement",
            "d) Perpendicular feed arrangement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steam economy of the evaporator is defined as the number kilogram of water vaporized from all the effects per kilogram of steam used. The steam economy of single effect evaporator is about 0.8 (<1).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Where is the feed introduced in climbing film evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bottom",
            "b) Top",
            "c) Middle",
            "d) Anywhere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The different modes of feed in multiple effect evaporators are forward feed arrangement, backward feed arrangement, mixed feed and parallel feed arrangement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "How to increase the economy of multi effect evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease the usage of steam",
            "b) Increase the steam capacity",
            "c) Reuse the latent heat of the water vapor",
            "d) Reuse the latent heat of the liquid feed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The climbing film plate evaporator is designed to produce a thin film. In the climbing film evaporators, the feed is introduced at the bottom of the tubes and thus vapor due to evaporation expands which results in rise of the liquid along the tubes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Which law governs theboiling point elevation in evaporators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rauolt’s law",
            "b) Boyle’s law",
            "c) Charle’s law",
            "d) Duhring’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Duhring’s law is the ratio of temperature at which two solutions exert the same temperature is constant which can be used to determine boiling point elevation in evaporators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Why does boiling point elevation occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Due to addition of solute",
            "b) Due to addition of solution",
            "c) Due to change in humidity",
            "d) Due to change in pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Boiling point elevation is the temperature change of the boiling point of a solvent caused by adding a solute. If the vapor pressure is lowered, the relative number of particles becoming a gas is decreased.  In order to reach equilibrium between vapor pressure and atmospheric pressure, more energy is added to force the particles at the surface of the liquid to release to the gaseous state. This increase results in the liquid boiling at a higher temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "What is boiling point elevation constant of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.12°C/m",
            "b) 51.2°C/m",
            "c) 0.512°C/m",
            "d) 0.0512°C/m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The boiling point elevation constant of water is 0.512°C/m. It is a constant that is equal to the change in the boiling point for a 1-molal solution of a nonvolatile molecular solute so therefore it is called as the molal boiling-point elevation constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "What is the boiling point of sugar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1,465°C",
            "b) 100°C",
            "c) 102.82°C",
            "d) 78.37°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:The boiling point of sugar is 102.82°C. The boiling point of salt is 1,465C°. The boiling point of pure water is 100°C. The boiling point of ethanol is78.37°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "How does boiling point depend on pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Indirectly proportional",
            "c) Not dependent",
            "d) Depends on the solute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The boiling point relates to the temperature when the vapor pressure of the liquid equals the surrounding environmental pressure. Thus, the boiling point is dependent on the pressure. The boiling point increases with increase in the pressure up to the critical point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which liquid has lowest boiling point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helium",
            "b) Water",
            "c) Ethanol",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The boiling point cannot be reduced below the triple point. Since the boiling point is dependent on the pressure. It decreases with decreasing pressure until the triple point is reached.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Which of the following are factors that regulate the boiling point of the solute?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration of solute in the solution",
            "b) Concentration of solvent",
            "c) Type of solute",
            "d) Type of solvent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:Helium has the lowest boiling point which is -268.9°C. Water has boiling point of 100°C. Ethanol has the boiling point of78.37°C. Nitrogen has boiling point of -195.8°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "What is the alternative name for boiling point elevation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vapor pressure lowering",
            "b) Vapor pressure elevation",
            "c) Latent heat",
            "d) Entropy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The boiling point of a solution is a colligative property  therefore it depends on the concentration of solute in the solution, but not on type of solute or solvent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which is the suitable source for heating the evaporators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steam",
            "b) Direct heating",
            "c) Electric resistance",
            "d) Heaters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steam is the best source as it is inexpensive where as in direct heating, it is difficult to control the heating temperature and high cost in case of electricity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Which of the following is called wiped film evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Falling film evaporator",
            "b) Agitated thin film evaporator",
            "c) Shell and tube evaporator",
            "d) Climbing film evaporator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agitated thin film evaporator is also known as wiped film evaporator. It is the ideal apparatus for continuous processing of concentrated material to dry solids.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of the following is called calandria evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Falling film evaporator",
            "b) Agitated thin film evaporator",
            "c) Short tube vertical",
            "d) Climbing film evaporator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The short tube vertical evaporators are the widely used especially in sugar industry for evaporation of the juice from the cane sugar. It contains short tube bundle which is walled by cylindrical shell. The feed is given to upper tube sheet whereas the steam is fed to the shell.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "How is steam economy calculated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass of evaporated liquid/Mass of heating steam",
            "b) Mass of evaporated liquid+Mass of heating steam",
            "c) Mass of evaporated liquidxMass of heating steam",
            "d) Mass of heating steam/Mass of evaporated liquid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Falling film washes away the deposition on tubes that minimize the chances of fouling on surface of the tube. It responds fast to heat source and feed quality supplied. It is efficient to operate across small temperature differences that results in maximum efficiency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "What is the principle behind rising film evaporators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermo-siphon",
            "b) Thermostatic",
            "c) Thermodynamic",
            "d) Pareto"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steam economy is the number kilogram of water vaporized from all the effects per kilogram of steam used. For single effect evaporator, the steam economy is about <1. It is calculated as the ratio of mass of evaporated liquid to mass of heating steam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which of the following evaporator is used to avoid crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Falling film evaporator",
            "b) Agitated thin film evaporator",
            "c) Shell and tube evaporator",
            "d) Forced circulation evaporator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thermo-siphon is a technique of passive heat exchange which is based on natural convection. It circulates a fluid without the requirement of a mechanical pump. Feed enters the bottom of the heating tubes and the steam begins to form. The mounting force of this steam produced during the boiling causes liquid and vapors to flow upwards in parallel flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which of the following evaporator is mainly used when the feed is almost saturated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forward feed",
            "b) Backward feed",
            "c) Parallel feed",
            "d) Antiparallel feed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Forced circulation evaporators are used to avoid due to the fouling characteristics of the product and also to avoid crystallization. The liquid is heated for each pass through heat exchanger. This is also used in crystallizing applications because there is no evaporation and therefore no increase in the concentration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Which of the following evaporator has low compression ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum evaporator",
            "b) Agitated thin film evaporator",
            "c) Shell and tube evaporator",
            "d) Forced circulation evaporator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Parallel feed in multiple-effect  evaporators  involves  the  adding  of  fresh  feed  and  the  withdrawal of concentrated product from each effect. The vapor from each effect is still used to heat the next effect. This method of operation is mainly used when the feed is almost saturated and solid crystals are the product. For example, this can be used in evaporation of brine to produce salt.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "What are conditions to achieve maximum retention of volatile constituents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short residence time and low pressure",
            "b) Short residence time and high pressure",
            "c) Long residence time and low pressure",
            "d) Long residence time and high pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Under short residence time, the contact between product and evaporator is less and under the low pressure, the boiling point is also reduced therefore volatile components are retained in the product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "What type of evaporators used for heat sensitive materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum evaporators",
            "b) Vertical type evaporators",
            "c) Climbing film type evaporators",
            "d) Forced circulation evaporators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pressure is directly proportional to boiling point and vacuum evaporators work under low pressure or at high vacuum which results in reduced boiling point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "What are the applications of agitated thin-film evaporators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purification of sensitive organic chemicals",
            "b) Vapor recompression for energy recovery",
            "c) Devolatilization of thermoplastics",
            "d) Devolatilization of thermoplastics and purification of sensitive organic chemicals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Purification of sensitive organic chemicals like natural oils, fatty acids, herbicides and insecticides and isocyanates, and devolatilization of thermoplastics, phenolicresins, acrylic resins, silicone polymers and nylon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be evaporated in plate-and-frame or agitated thin-film evaporator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High viscosity, heavy solids, high tendency to foul",
            "b) Heavy solids, high tendency to foul",
            "c) High viscosity, heavy solids,",
            "d) High viscosity, high tendency to foul"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gasketed plate-and-frame evaporator is constructed by mounting a number of embossed plates with corner openings. These systems are operated as rising-film, falling-film evaporators. It is used for heat-sensitive, viscous and foamy materials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Which of the following evaporator is not used for heat sensitive materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum evaporators",
            "b) Vertical type evaporators",
            "c) Plate-and-frame type evaporators",
            "d) Agitated thin-film evaporators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Car radiator and air conditioner evaporator coil uses crossflow heat exchangers. Crossflow heat exchangers are widely used for transfer of heat between a gas and a liquid. In air conditioner evaporator coil, the air flows past the evaporator coils are cooled by the cold refrigerant that is flowing inside the tubes of the coil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following evaporator separates volatile and nonvolatile compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Falling film evaporators",
            "b) Vertical type evaporators",
            "c) Climbing film type evaporators",
            "d) Forced circulation evaporators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enough liquid should be passing through the evaporator to keep the heated walls wet. Lack of wall wetting and fluid velocity may cause serious fouling and salting of solids on the heat transfer surfaces, leading to degradation of product quality. In processes where high distillate-to-concentrate ratios are required, recycling of concentrate is done.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "What is the important factor which is employed for heat sensitive materials in an evaporator ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High pressure",
            "b) Vacuum",
            "c) High residence time",
            "d) High temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vacuum evaporators, plate-and-frame type evaporators and agitated thin-film evaporators are used for heat sensitive materials. Vertical type evaporators have long residence time and high pressure which can degrade the quality of the product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of the following evaporator cannot be used for milk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scraped surface evaporators",
            "b) Fluidized bed evaporators",
            "c) Plate-and-frame type evaporators",
            "d) Batch Pan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In falling film evaporators, the liquid product usually enters the evaporator at the head of the evaporator. The liquid enters the heating tube and forms a thin film on the tube wall where it flows downwards at boiling temperature and is partially evaporated. In most cases, steam is used for heating the evaporator.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "What is the principle behind paper chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is based on partition chromatography",
            "b) It is based on ions and its charge",
            "c) It is based on charges only",
            "d) It is based on ions only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The principle involved in paper chromatography is partition chromatography where the substances are partitioned between liquid phases. One phase is the mobile phase water which moves over the paper and other is the water which is held in the pores of the filter paper used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "What is Rf value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ratio of the distance moved by the solvent and the distance moved by the solute",
            "b) Ratio of the distance moved by the solute and the distance moved by the solvent",
            "c) Ratio of the concentration of solute and the concentration of the solvent",
            "d) It Ratio of the concentration of solvent and the concentration of the solute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Rf value is defined as the ratio of the distance moved by the solute and the distance moved by the solvent along the paper, where both distances are measured from the common application Baseline.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "What is the best solvent for paper chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Alcohol",
            "c) Vinegar",
            "d) Methanol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Paper chromatography is an inexpensive method for analyzing some types of chemical mixtures. Water is polar in nature and is commonly used as solvent in paper chromatography.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "What does a high RF value mean in paper chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Substance is very non-polar",
            "b) Substance is medium non-polar",
            "c) Substance is polar",
            "d) Substance is neutral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A high Rf would refer to a substance that is very non-polar where substance moved. A low Rf value would refer to a substance that is very polar.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "What are the two main types of chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid chromatography and paper chromatography",
            "b) Liquid chromatography and gas chromatography",
            "c) Liquid chromatography and solid chromatography",
            "d) Solid chromatography and gas chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chromatography utilizes phase equilibrium partitioning principles to isolate proteins, nucleic acids in complex blends and has stationary phase and a mobile phase. There are two main types of chromatography: Liquid chromatography and gas chromatography.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Why acetonitrile is used as solvent in HPLC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improve chromatographic peak shape",
            "b) Provide a source of protons in reverse phase LC/MS",
            "c) Provide a source of electrons in reverse phase LC/MS",
            "d) Improve chromatographic peak shape and provide a source of protons in reverse phase LC/MS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In High pressure liquid chromatography, the B solvent used is HPLC grade organic solvent like acetonitrile, methanol with 0.1% acid. This acid is used for improving the shape of chromatographic peak and to provide source of protons in the reverse phase LC/MS.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "What causes peak tailing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depends on the concentration of solvent",
            "b) Occurrence of more than one mechanism of analytic retention",
            "c) Depends on the concentration of solute",
            "d) No occurrence of more than one mechanism of analytic retention"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TFA (trifluoroacetic acid) is a commonly used as mobile phase additive used in reversed phase HPLC separations of proteins and peptides. TFA restrictsconsiderablyto reduces the LC/MS signal, thus lowering the sensitivity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "What is the soluble component called in absorption equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solute",
            "b) Solvent",
            "c) Liquid phase",
            "d) Solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Absorption is the process by which a gas is dissolved in a liquid. The soluble component is called the solute and is transferred from the gas mixture to the liquid. The liquid consists of the solvent and absorbate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "What are the heat effects that cause temperatures to vary from point to point in a gas absorber?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The heat of solution",
            "b) The heat of vaporization or condensation of the solvent",
            "c) The heat of solution and the heat of vaporization or condensation of the solvent",
            "d) No effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Operating pressure should be high and temperature low for an absorber, to minimize stage requirements and absorbent flow rate to lower the equipment volume required to accommodate the gas flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "At what conditions will the solute is absorbed more per stage or packing segment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When L/G ratio is increased",
            "b) When L/G ratio is decreased",
            "c) When L/G ratio is negligible",
            "d) When L/G ratio is reduced to very low level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The heat effects that cause temperatures to vary from point to point in a gas absorber are heat of vaporization or condensation of the solvent, the heat of solution, the loss of sensible heat from the fluids to internal or external coils and the exchange of sensible heat between the gas and liquid phases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "What is stripping in absorption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operation of removing the absorbed solute from the solvent",
            "b) Operation of removing the solvent from the absorbed solute",
            "c) Operation of removing the unwanted solution",
            "d) Operation of removing the catalyst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the L/G ratio is increased, the operating line moves away from the equilibrium line and more solute is absorbed per stage or packing segment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "What is use of gas absorption column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To study hydrodynamic process",
            "b) To study absorption processes in packed columns",
            "c) To study hydrodynamic and absorption processes in packed columns",
            "d) To hold the gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a component of the gas mix, transferred to liquid and is a gas at operating condition of mass transfer, then it is called as absorption. If a component transferred to liquid and is a vapor at operating condition of mass transfer, then it is called as scrubbing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "What is NTU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of transfer units",
            "b) Number of transport units",
            "c) Neutral transfer units",
            "d) Neutral tons units"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Absorption is the process which is used for separating gas mixtures and removing impurities. It is used for recovering the valuable chemicals. The process of eliminating the absorbed solute from the solvent is known as stripping.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "What is channeling in gas absorption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Down in the bed, the liquid tends to flow toward the wall",
            "b) At the top of the bed, the liquid tends to flow toward the wall",
            "c) Down in the bed, the liquid tends to flow away from the wall",
            "d) At the top of the bed, the liquid tends to flow away from the wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gas absorption column is a scale unit. It is intended to study the hydrodynamic and the absorption processes in the packed columns. In this system, it absorbs CO2 and ammonia from an air mixture in a watery solution that move along the column.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What process takes place when water is used as absorbent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stripping",
            "b) Dilution",
            "c) Distillation",
            "d) Dissolving"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NTU is called as number of transfer units. It is the measure of the difficulty of the separation of the substance.The height of a transfer unit (HTU) is a measure of the effectiveness in separation of the packings for a particular separation process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "What is the alternative name for stripping?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas absorption",
            "b) Gas desorption",
            "c) Adsorption",
            "d) Liquid desorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gas desorption is also called as stripping. In gas desorption, the mass transfer is from the liquid phase to the gas phase. The principles for both gas absorption and gas desorption are the same.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "What are types of absorption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical absorption",
            "b) Chemical absorption",
            "c) Physical absorption and chemical absorption",
            "d) Physical absorption, chemical absorption and microbial absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spray dyer is used to produce powder from the solution. It dries the solution stream and separates the solute and evaporates the solvent and forms vapor. The solid particles are collected in a cyclone or drum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "What is reactive absorption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical absorption",
            "b) Physical absorption",
            "c) Microbial absorption",
            "d) Ion absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a strong base like aqueous sodium hydroxide is used as the absorbent to dissolve an acid gas, the absorption process is accompanied by a rapid and irreversible neutralization reaction in the liquid phase and the process is known as chemical absorption or reactive absorption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Who invented the absorption refrigerator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Albert Einstein",
            "b) Ferdinand Carre",
            "c) Robert Wilhelm Bunsen",
            "d) Schuyler Skaats Wheeler"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Albert Einsteininvented the absorption refrigerator. Ferdinand Carreinvented an electric light regulator. Robert Wilhelm Bunsen invented the spectrometer. Schuyler Skaats Wheeler invented fans.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "What is the principle of absorption spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bound atoms in the ground state can absorb light of a certain wavelength",
            "b) Free atoms in the ground state can absorb light of a certain wavelength",
            "c) Bound atoms in the excited state can absorb light of a certain wavelength",
            "d) Free atoms in the ground state can absorb radiation energy of a certain wavelength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Absorption spectroscopy is based upon the principle that free atoms in the ground state can absorb light of a certain wavelength. Absorption is specificfor each element, and thus, no other elements can absorb this wavelength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors that affect the selection of absorbent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscosity should be low",
            "b) Viscosity should be high",
            "c) Low pressure drops",
            "d) Low pressure drops and viscosity should be low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Absorbent is defined as the material having ability to absorb another substance. Absorbents should usually be having low pressure drops in absorption tower and low viscosity for rapid absorption rates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example for absorption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reaction of oxygen by fermentation broths",
            "b) Removal of carbon dioxide from water-gas by absorption in water or in solutions of alkalis or amines",
            "c) Reaction of hydrogen by petroleum fractions in processes to remove sulphur as hydrogen sulphide.",
            "d) Liquid ammonium in air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Examples of absorption are i. Absorption of nitrous gases in water or nitric acid, during nitric acid manufacture. ii. Removal of carbon monoxide from water-gas by absorption in solutions of copper complexes. iii. The production of hypochlorite by absorbing chlorine through alkaline solutions. iv. Absorption of hydrogen by petroleum fractions in processes to remove sulphur as hydrogen sulphide.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "What is law behind absorption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nernst’s distribution law",
            "b) Henry’s law",
            "c) Raoult’s law",
            "d) Dalton’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the absorption is reactive then it is called as chemical absorption.  There will be a chemical reaction between the absorbed and the absorbing substances. It depends on the stoichiometry of the reaction and the concentration of its reactants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "What is VLE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vapor liquid equal",
            "b) Vapor liquid equilibrium",
            "c) Vapor liquid estimation",
            "d) Vapor liquid enthalpy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The vapor liquid equilibrium (VLE) defines the distribution of chemical substances between the vapor phase and liquid phase. The equilibrium vapor pressure of a liquid is in overall intensely reliant on temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "What is the quality in percentage of saturated vapor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 100%",
            "d) 200%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vapor quality is the mass fraction in a saturated mixture that is vapor. It has a quality of 100%. Vapor quality is an intensive property. It is used only for single constituent mixes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "What is the quality in percentage of saturated liquid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 100%",
            "d) 200%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vapor quality is the mass fraction in a saturated mixture that is vapor. It has a quality of 0%. Vapor quality is an intensive property. It is used only for single constituent mixes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not vapor liquid phase diagrams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boiling point diagrams",
            "b) Txy, Pxy diagrams",
            "c) Ternary diagrams",
            "d) Freezing point diagrams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Boiling point diagrams, Txy, Pxy diagrams, ternary diagrams and solubility diagrams are the vapor liquid phase diagrams. These diagrams signify a binary mix and all the compositions are expressed as mole fractions of the more volatile component.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "What is the alternative name for bubble point temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dew point",
            "b) Initial boiling point",
            "c) Final boiling point",
            "d) Bubble ruptures point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bubble point temperature is also called initial boiling point. It is the temperature at a given pressure, when a liquid consisting of two or more components is heated the first bubbles of the vapors are formed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "What is the alternative name for dew point temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bubble point tempertaure",
            "b) Initial boiling point",
            "c) Final boiling point",
            "d) Bubble ruptures point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The alternative name for dew point temperature is Final boiling point. It is the temperature to which air is cooled to become saturated with the water vapor. It is always lower than the air temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Which of the gas will not follow Henry’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HCl gas",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) Hydrogen gas",
            "d) Helium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Solubility of a gas in a liquid is directly proportional to the pressure of the gas under equilibrium. Henry’s law is applicable only when the pressure of the gas is not too high and temperature is not too low. The gas should not undergo association or dissociation in the solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of the following law is applied in respiratory physiology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Raoult’s law",
            "b) Henry’s law",
            "c) Boyle’s law",
            "d) Dalton’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HCl gas does not follow Henry’s law as in solution HCl dissociate into ions H+ and Cl–. HCl is a strong acid and it interrelates with solvent and readily dissociate into its constituent ions. While Helium, oxygen gas and hydrogen gas do not dissociate on interaction with water so they follow Henry’s law.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the application of Henry’s Law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase the solubility of carbon dioxide gas in soda water",
            "b) In deep sea scuba diving",
            "c) In respiratory physiology",
            "d) To estimate the contribution of individual components by the system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The main application of Henry’s law in respiratory physiology is to forecast gas dissolving in the alveoli and bloodstream during the gas exchange. The amount of oxygen that dissolves into bloodstream is proportional to the partial pressure of oxygen in alveolar air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "At what point does liquid and solid exist at equilibrium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double point",
            "b) Triple point",
            "c) Dew point",
            "d) Freezing point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The point at which the lines of liquid, solid and gas intersect represents the triple point. At the pressure and temperature of the triple point, all the phases exist in equilibrium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Who coined the term triple point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) James Thomson",
            "b) Daniel Gabriel Fahrenheit",
            "c) Carrier",
            "d) Rudolf Clausius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of equilibrium constant is independent of initial concentrations of the reactants and products. It is applicable only when concentrations of the reactants and products have attained their equilibrium state and is temperature dependent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of freezing point depression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salt in water",
            "b) Cooling the hot water",
            "c) Alcohol in water",
            "d) Mixing of impurities into a fine powder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: James Thomson coined the term triple point. Daniel Gabriel Fahrenheit invented thermometer. Carrier discovered that law of constant dew-point depression. Rudolf Clausius coined the term entropy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "What is peritectic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A reaction between solid phase and gas phase to form a second solid phase",
            "b) A reaction between solid phase and liquid phase to form a second solid phase",
            "c) A reaction between gas phase and liquid phase to form a second solid phase",
            "d) A reaction between solid phase and liquid phase to form a second liquid phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The freezing point depression is the decrease of the freezing point of a solvent on the addition of a non-volatile solute. Examples like alcohol in water, salt in water and the mixing of two solids such as impurities into a finely powdered drug.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "What is the temperature at which the solid and liquid phases are at equilibrium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal melting point",
            "b) Bubble point",
            "c) Dew point",
            "d) Equilibrium point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A reaction between solid phase and liquid phase to form a second solid phase is called peritectic reaction. These reactions are slow as the product phase form at the boundary between the two reacting phases thus it separates them and slows down the further reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "At equilibrium, the concentrations of N2=4.0 x10-3M, O2 = 5.2 x 10-3M and NO=3.9×10-3M in a sealed vessel at 800K. What will be Kc for the reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.731",
            "b) 0.073",
            "c) 7.31",
            "d) 0.0007"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the system of ice and water is in dynamic equilibrium it can be concluded that both opposing processes occur at the same time and two processes occur at the same rate therefore the amount of ice and water remain constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "What is the other alternative name for equilibrium phase diagram?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-v-T diagram",
            "b) Bubble point diagram",
            "c) Dew point diagram",
            "d) Equilibrium point diagram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  For any pure substance at atmospheric pressure, the temperature at which the solid and liquid phases are at equilibrium is called the normal freezing point or normal melting point of the component.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "What is equilibrium constant expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ratio of the concentrations of the reactants and molar constant and products",
            "b) The ratio of the concentrations of the products and reactants",
            "c) The ratio of the concentrations of the reactants and products",
            "d) The ratio of the concentrations of the catalyst and products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ratio of the concentrations of the reactants and products is called as equilibrium constant expression. When the reaction reaches equilibrium, the association between the concentrations of the reactants and products termed by the equilibrium constant expression is always same.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "How does increase in concentration affect equilibrium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will shift towards the products.",
            "b) It will shift towards the reactants.",
            "c) No change",
            "d) It will shift according to pressure change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When there is increase in concentration the equilibrium will shift towards the products. There will be increase in product formation and there will be decrease in concentration of the reactants as the concentration of the products increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "What affects equilibrium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Changes in concentration",
            "b) Changes in and pressure",
            "c) Changes in temperature",
            "d) Changes in concentration, temperature, and pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Changes in concentration, temperature, and pressure can affect the position of equilibrium of a reversible reaction. If the forward reaction is endothermic, then there is an increase in temperature that causes the system to shift toward the products.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "What is the relation between Kp and K?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kp=K(RT)Δn",
            "b) Kp=K-(RT)Δn",
            "c) Kp=K+(RT)Δn",
            "d) Kp=K/(RT)Δn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The catalyst speeds up the forward and back reaction to the same extent and addition of a catalyst does not affect the relative rates of the two reactions and cannot affect the position of equilibrium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "What is use of law of mass action in equilibrium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Predicts behaviors of solutions in dynamic equilibrium",
            "b) To calculate the concentration of products",
            "c) To calculate the concentration of reactants",
            "d) Predicts behaviors of solutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relation between Kp and K  is Kp=K(RT)Δn. An equilibrated system that contains products and reactants in a single phase is a homogeneous equilibrium where as a system whose reactants, products are in more than one phase, it is called as heterogeneous equilibrium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Who discovered law of mass action?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Guldberg and Waage",
            "b) Newton",
            "c) Henricus",
            "d) Gyarmati"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This reaction has 2 moles of gaseous product and 4 moles of gaseous reactants, so Δn=(2−4)=−2. We know K, and T=745K.\nKp=K(RT)−2\n0.95 x {[0.08206(L⋅atm)/(mol⋅K)][745K]}-2 = 2.54×10-4.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "What method is used for the separation of organic compound from a mixture of compound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distillation",
            "b) Extraction",
            "c) Sieving",
            "d) Boiling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the main applications of extraction method is 1. It is used in separation of organic compound from a mixture of the compounds. 2. It selectively dissolves one or more components into ansuitable solvent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "What is the principle of solvent extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nernst’s distribution law",
            "b) Henry’s law",
            "c) Raoult’s law",
            "d) Dalton’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the solute is add to a unrelated system of two immiscible liquids, the solute dispenses between the two liquids. This distribution governed by Nernst distribution law.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Who discovered extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Samuel Percy",
            "b) Fritz Winkler",
            "c) Franz Ritter von Soxhlet",
            "d) Jacques-Arsened’Arsonva"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Samuel Percy invented spray dryer. Fritz Winkler invented fluidized bed dryer. Franz Ritter von Soxhlet discovered extraction. Jacques-Arsened’Arsonva invented freeze dryer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "What is not the type of extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid/ liquid",
            "b) Liquid/ soild",
            "c) acid/base",
            "d) Gas/gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Extractions are a way to discrete a desired substance when it is mixed with others. The three most common types of extractions are liquid/liquid, liquid/solid, and acid/base.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as a chemically active extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid/ liquid",
            "b) Liquid/ soild",
            "c) acid/base",
            "d) Gas/gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are three types of extractions; i. Liquid in liquid, ii. Liquid in solid, and iii. Acid in base Acid in base type of extraction is also called as chemically active extraction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "What method of extraction is used for fatty acids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid/ liquid",
            "b) Liquid/ soild",
            "c) acid/base",
            "d) Gas/gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Liquid/ liquid extraction is used for the extraction of fatty acids. Folch method has been used to extract lipids containing fatty acids from biological samples, using chloroform, water and methanol to separate lipids from aqueous-soluble compounds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "How to break emulsion in extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By adding NaCl",
            "b) By adding HCl",
            "c) By adding alcohol",
            "d) By adding benzene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One method that is often used to break up an emulsion is to add some salt like NaCl to increase the ionic strength of the aqueous layer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "What is the major disadvantage of using ether as an extracting solvent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highly flammable",
            "b) Highly volatile",
            "c) Highly flammable and highly volatile",
            "d) Cold environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Washing is method of selectively removing unwanted compounds from mixture using a solvent. For successful washing, the unwanted materials must be more soluble in the solvent than in the mixture. Moreover, the solvent and mixture must be immiscible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "What are the classifications of extraction equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By gravity",
            "b) By centrifugal forces",
            "c) By centrifugal forces and size of the particle",
            "d) By centrifugal forces and gravity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Classification of extraction equipment is based on centrifugal forces and gravity, the methods used for bringing together and separating the phases and is sub-classified according to type of contact.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "What is basic principle behind packed towers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By gravity",
            "b) By centrifugal forces",
            "c) By centrifugal forces and size of the particle",
            "d) By centrifugal forces and gravity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Packed columns always have nozzles for the initial distribution of each phase and droplets are present. Thus packed towers are considered as droplet extractors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "What are the main factors considered for the operation of extraction column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Droplet size, axial dispersion",
            "b) Droplet size distribution, axial dispersion",
            "c) Droplet size, droplet size distribution",
            "d) Droplet size, droplet size distribution and axial dispersion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main factors considered for the operation of extraction column are droplet size, droplet size distribution and axial dispersion. Axial dispersion follows from different phenomena like turbulence or differences in the droplet sizes, and results in lower column efficiency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "What are methods for regeneration of solvents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectification",
            "b) Evaporation",
            "c) Crystallization",
            "d) Rectification, evaporation, crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rectification, evaporation, crystallization are the methods for regeneration of solvents. By these processes the pure products are produced and the solvent can be recycled in the extraction process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Separate an organic substance from a mixture",
            "b) Separate an inorganic substance from a mixture",
            "c) Separate both organic and inorganic substance from a mixture",
            "d) Separate dust from a mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In centrifugal extractors no discrete stages can be recognized. The principle of this design is to introduce the heavy phase close to the axis of a rotating container, while the light phase is introduced close to the periphery. The applied centrifugal force causes the two phases to move radially in a countercurrent mode in such a way that the heavy phase is moved to the periphery and the light phase to the rotation axis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "What are the methods of extraction used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressing",
            "b) Distillation",
            "c) Solvent extraction",
            "d) Solvent extraction, distillation method, pressing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Extraction is the recovery of a substance from a mixture by bringing it into contact with a solvent, which dissolves the desired material. It is a suitable method for separating organic substance from a mixture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "What is percolation extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A method of extraction by gravity",
            "b) A method of extraction by filtration",
            "c) A method of extraction by sedimentation",
            "d) A method of extraction by distillation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Extraction is the initial step for separating the desired natural products from the raw compounds. Some of the examples are distillation, solvent extraction, sublimation and pressing. These are divided according to the compound to be extracted and the extraction principle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "What advantages does the Soxhlet extraction have over other extraction processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete extraction and high efficiency",
            "b) Complete extraction and small solvent dosage",
            "c) Small solvent dosage and complete extraction",
            "d) Small solvent dosage, high efficiency and complete extraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The active compound from a product is derived through percolation method.The solvent is passed over a bed of substance which helps in the liquid extract, and this liquid extract is then recirculated through the bed for a period of time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "What solvent is used in phytonics extraction process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrofluorocarbon -134a",
            "b) ammnia",
            "c) CFCs",
            "d) Alcohol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The advantage of Soxhlet extraction is that it can be extracted multiple times. Compared with the other extraction method, it has small solvent dosage, high efficiency and complete extraction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "What are the classifications of membrane separation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pore size",
            "b) Separation driving force",
            "c) Separation driving pressure",
            "d) Separation driving force and pore size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Membrane separations are classified by pore size and by the separation driving force. It is a technology which selectively separates materials via pores and minute gaps in the molecular arrangement of a continuous structure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "What is pore size of RO membranes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0005 microns",
            "b) 0.005 microns",
            "c) 0.05 microns",
            "d) 0.5 microns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pore size of RO membrane is 0.0005 microns, this is smaller than the size of the sodium chloride molecule which has the size of 0.0007 micron and will not let it through membrane.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "What are the applications of membrane separation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nano filtration",
            "b) Microfiltration",
            "c) Ultrafiltration",
            "d) Microfiltration, ultrafiltration, nano-filtration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The membrane processes are used in microfiltration, gas separation, ultrafiltration, membrane distillation, nanofiltration, reverse osmosis, electrolysis, dialysis, electro dialysis and membrane contactors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "What is filter membrane made up of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thin layer of collodion, cellulose acetate",
            "b) Thick layer of collodion, cellulose acetate",
            "c) Thin layer of collodion",
            "d) Thin layer of cellulose acetate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The membrane filter is a filter which is made up of a thin film of collodion, cellulose acetate, available in a wide range of defined pore sizes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "What is permeate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluid that has retained in semi-permeable membrane",
            "b) Fluid that has passed through semi-permeable membrane",
            "c) Fluid that has to be passing through semi-permeable membrane",
            "d) The residue after filtration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The membrane separation system splits stream into two fold effluent streams. They are permeate and concentrate. Permeate is defined as the fluid that passes through the semi-permeable membrane.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "What are classification of membranes from a structural point of view ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asymmetrical and pore size",
            "b) Symmetrical and pore size",
            "c) Symmetrical and asymmetrical",
            "d) Symmetrical and concentration of solute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Advantages of membrane separation process are appreciable energy saving, clean technology with operational ease and it replaces the conventional processes like filtration, ion-exchange and chemical treatment systems and finally greater flexibility in designing systems.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "What are the driving forces in membrane separation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Osmotic pressure",
            "b) Electrical field",
            "c) Partial pressure",
            "d) Osmotic pressure, electrical field and partial pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  From a structural point of view membranes are broadly divided into two types. They are Symmetrical and asymmetrical which is also called as anisotropic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of the following are in the order of descending order?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nano filtration, ultrafiltration, Reverse osmosis and microfiltration",
            "b) Reverse osmosis, nano filtration, ultrafiltration and microfiltration",
            "c) Microfiltration, ultrafiltration, nano filtration and reverse osmosis",
            "d) Ultrafiltration, microfiltration, nano filtration and reverse osmosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The driving forces in membrane separation are transmembrane (hydrostatic) pressure (TMP), concentration or electrochemical gradient, osmotic pressure electrical field and partial pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "What is pervaporation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process to separate a volatile liquid from a non-volatile liquid",
            "b) Process to mix a volatile liquid from a non-volatile liquid",
            "c) Process to a evaporate a non-volatile liquid",
            "d) Process to separate water molecules from a non-volatile liquid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pervaporation is a process to separate a volatile from a non-volatile liquid. The driving force is a vacuum on the gaseous side of the membrane. It is a tool for separation of liquid mixtures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which method is used for removing hardness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nanofiltration",
            "b) Pervaporation",
            "c) Electrodialysis",
            "d) Reverse Osmosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nano filtration is used for removing hardness. It removes organic compounds and selected salts at the lower pressure than RO system. It separates at the molecular level, removing all suspended solids and most dissolved solids.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Which method is used separation of azeotrope mixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nano filtration",
            "b) Pervaporation",
            "c) Electro dialysis",
            "d) Reverse Osmosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pervaporation is a process to separate a volatile from a non-volatile liquid. The driving force is a vacuum on the gaseous side of the membrane. It is a tool for separation of liquid mixtures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which of the following uses aromatic polyamide as membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas separation",
            "b) Pervaporation",
            "c) Electro dialysis",
            "d) Reverse Osmosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reverse Osmosis uses aromatic polyamide as membrane where it is used in separation of salts and micro-solutes from solutions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "What is other name for polymeric membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organic membrane",
            "b) Inorganic membrane",
            "c) Cation and anion membrane",
            "d) Neutral charge membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cation and anion exchange membrane is used in electro dialysis where the membrane is made of sulfonated cross-linked polystyrene and is used in desalting the water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "What is flux rate for filters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ratio of flow to the membrane area",
            "b) Ratio of concentration to the membrane area",
            "c) Ratio of membrane area to the flow of the solution",
            "d) Ratio of viscosity to the membrane area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polymeric membranes are also known as organic membranes. In order of the coarsest separation to the finest are microfiltration, ultrafiltration, nanofiltration and reverse osmosis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "What is membrane processing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process that concentrates and separates without the use of heat",
            "b) Process that removes dust without the use of heat",
            "c) Process that remove water without the use of heat",
            "d) Process that remove alcohol without the use of heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A membrane’s flux is defined as ratio of flow to the membrane area. It is used for calculating scalability. Ultrafiltration membranes are used in the purification of expensive biomolecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "What are cleaning techniques for the removal of membrane fouling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air flushing and chemical flushing",
            "b) Alcohol flushing and chemical flushing",
            "c) Air flushing and alcohol flushing",
            "d) Air flushing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Membrane processing concentration and separation without the use of heat. Particles are separated on the basis of size of the molecules and shape with the help of pressure gradient and uses semi-permeable membranes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to remove yeast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nano filtration",
            "b) Micro filtration",
            "c) Electro dialysis",
            "d) Reverse Osmosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are various cleaning techniques to remove membrane fouling. These are forward flushing, backward flushing, air flushing and chemical cleaning.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "What are the two processes in distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distilling and freezing",
            "b) Distilling and condensation reflux",
            "c) Freezing and condensation reflux",
            "d) Only condensation reflux"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Distillation is the process where it consists of two processes of distilling and condensation reflux. It is usually carried out in distillation column, the gas-liquid two-phase flow through the countercurrent contact.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "What are the basic methods of distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fractional distillation and simple distillation",
            "b) Fractional distillation, destructive distillation and simple distillation",
            "c) Steam distillation, simple distillation and gas distillation",
            "d) Steam distillation and destructive distillation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Simple distillation, fractional distillation where different volatile fractions are collected as during the process and destructive distillation where a material is heated so that it decomposes into compounds for collection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Who discovered distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jabir ibn Hayyan",
            "b) Guldberg and Waage",
            "c) Charles Chamberland",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jabir ibn Hayyan discovered distillation. Guldberg and Waage recognized that chemical equilibrium. Clarence Birdseye developed freezing process. Charles Chamberland developed steam pressure sterilizer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "What apparatus is used in distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distillation flask, condenser, collection vessel",
            "b) Distillation flask, condenser",
            "c) Condenser, collection vessel",
            "d) Distillation flask, column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Distillation apparatus consists of three units, they are distillation flask which is used for heating the mixture and volatizing the components. Next is condenser for cooling the vapors back to liquid state and lastly collection vessel for collecting the end product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Where is the double distillation method used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To prepare distilled water for laboratory purposes",
            "b) To produce distilled water for commercial purposes",
            "c) To produce wine for commercial purposes",
            "d) To produce coffee for commercial purposes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Double distillation consists of flak with heating elements. It is used for carrying out the reactions under stirred conditions besides furnishing for reflux distillation. It is used to prepare distilled water for laboratory research.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "What is the distillate in distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vapor collected from the mixture",
            "b) Liquid present in the distillation column",
            "c) Vapor introduced during distillation process",
            "d) Liquid introduced during distillation process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A distillate in the distillation process is defined as the vapor in a distillation column that is collected and condensed into a liquid and collected in the collecting flask.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Why is steel wool used in fractional distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases the surface area",
            "b) Improves the separation between the liquids",
            "c) Increases the surface area and improves the separation between the liquids",
            "d) Increases the surface area and the quality of the distillate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fractionating column is filled with a packing material like glass, steel wool and plastic beads. It increases the surface area and improves the separation between the liquids being distilled.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Which of the following is produced by triple distillation method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coffee",
            "b) Beer",
            "c) Whisky",
            "d) Wine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The vacuum distillation happens at a considerable reduced pressure, therefore reduces the boiling point of a substance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Why porcelain pieces are used in distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To have uniform boiling",
            "b) To hasten the process",
            "c) To add weight for the substance",
            "d) To absorb excess heat from the flask"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Triple distillation is defined as the process where smooth whiskies are manufactured. Through refining the spirit over three distillations, it concentrates a particular fraction of flavorful compounds and aromatic substance that results in a very smoother taste.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "How to calculate partial pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sum of the pressures of each individual gas",
            "b) Total pressure multiplied by the mole fraction of that gas",
            "c) Sum of the mole fraction of each individual gas",
            "d) Total concentration multiplied by the mole fraction of that gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total pressure of the mixture of gases is the sum of the individual pressures of each gas. The partial pressure of an individual gas is equivalent to the total pressure multiplied by mole fraction of that individual gas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "What is the use of partial pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To predict the movement of gases",
            "b) To predict the concentration change",
            "c) To predict the pressure change",
            "d) To predict the mole fraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Partial pressure is the force exerted by a gas. Partial pressure is very important in predicting the movement of gases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "What is partial pressure of water vapor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 23.8 mm Hg",
            "b) 230.8 mm Hg",
            "c) 2.38 mm Hg",
            "d) 0.238 mm Hg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water vapor pressure is the partial pressure of water vapor in any gas mixture in equilibrium with solid or liquid water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "What is r value in pV= nRT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8314 J/mol•K",
            "b) 831.4 J/mol•K",
            "c) 83.14 J/mol•K",
            "d) 8.314 J/mol•K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ideal gas law is pV = nRT, where n is the number of moles, and R is universal gas constant. The value of R depends on the units involved, and S.I. unit is 8.314 J/mol•K.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of the following component is constant in Boyle’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At constant temperature, the volume of a given mass of a dry gas is indirectly proportional to its pressure is known as Boyle’s law.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "What is the limitation of Dalton’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It implies only for real gases at low pressure",
            "b) It implies only for real gases at high pressure",
            "c) It implies only for real gases at low concentration",
            "d) It implies only for real gases at high concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As temperature increases the molecular activity at the surface of the water also increases. An increase in temperature would increase the partial pressure where the volume of the container remains constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "In an experiment,the barometric pressure of gas is 1.043 atm, Some H2 was collected over water at 27.0°C.  What is the partial pressure of the dry H2 in the container?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1021 atm",
            "b) 102.1 atm",
            "c) 10.21 atm",
            "d) 1.021 atm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Dalton’s law is good for real gases at low pressure, but at high pressure, it deviates considerably. The mixture of gases is non-reactive in nature. Another assumption is that the interaction between each individual gas molecules is same as the molecules in the mixture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "The pressure of a 2.74moles of a gas in a container was 432.0 torr.  What would the pressure inside the container be if 5.05 moles of the gas was in it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 896.20 torr",
            "b) 796.20 torr",
            "c) 596.20 torr",
            "d) 696.20 torr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The partial pressure of each gas in a mix is proportional to its mole fraction. The pressure exerted by each gas in a gas mix is not dependent on the pressure exerted by all other gases present. Partial pressure of each gas is the product of the mole fraction and total pressure of that gas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "What is distillation reflux ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ratio between the boil up rate and the take-off rate",
            "b) Product of boil up rate and the take-off rate",
            "c) Sum of boil up rate and the take-off rate",
            "d) Ratio between the take-off rateand boil up rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Reflux ratio is the ratio between boil up rate and take-off rate. It is the relation between the amount of reflux that goes back down the distillation column and the amount of reflux that is collected in the collection flask.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "What factors affect distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solubility",
            "b) Relative volatility",
            "c) Surface area",
            "d) Solubility, relative volatility and surface area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Binary distillation is a method used in chemical process industries to purify mixtures into their two separate components. In this process, the component mixture is separated by their phases. The lighter species is vaporized and leaves the column through the distillate. Whereas heavier species is in liquid form and collected at bottom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which of the following is explained by using McCabe-Thiele plot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distillation",
            "b) Crystallization",
            "c) Molecular separation",
            "d) Freezing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Distillation is affected by activity coefficient, solubility, relative volatility, maximum achievable concentration and surface area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "What is Q in McCabe Thiele method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mole fraction of liquid in the feed",
            "b) Concentration",
            "c) Viscosity",
            "d) Temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The McCabe-Thiele plot is a basic tool to assist distillation. It is a method to calculate the number of theoretical trays required for the distillation process of a binary mixture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "What are the limitations of McCabe Thiele method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cannot analyze mixtures containing more than 2 components",
            "b) Cannot analyze freeze dry product",
            "c) Cannot analyze mixtures at high temperature",
            "d) Cannot analyze mixtures at low temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The parameter q is known to be mole fraction of liquid in the feed and the typical McCabe-Thiele diagram uses a q-line which represents partially vaporized feed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "What does high reflux ratio mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher purity of the distillate",
            "b) Lower purity of the distillate",
            "c) Collection rate will be higher",
            "d) Does not depend on purity and collection rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Murphee efficiency is the ratio of the actual change in vapor composition when the vapor passes through the liquid on a tray to the composition change of the vapor if it were in vapor liquid at equilibrium with the tray liquid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Which of the following trays are used in distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bubble cap tray, sieve deck tray",
            "b) Bubble cap tray, pore sieve tray",
            "c) Sieve deck tray, pore sieve tray",
            "d) Bubble cap tray, multi-flow tray"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main drawback of the McCabe-Thiele Method is that it is not very beneficial for analyzing the distillation of mixtures comprising more than 2 components. However, the method is still valuable as a teaching tool and a conceptual tool.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Which of the following shape represents the number of theoretical stages in McCabe-Thiele plot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical line",
            "b) Circle",
            "c) Triangle",
            "d) Square"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The higher the reflux ratios, more contact of vapor/liquid occur in the distillation column. Therefore a higher reflux ratio means higher purity of the distillate and also means that the distillate will have slower collection rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "What are the applications of steam distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extract the inorganic compounds",
            "b) To clean the equipment",
            "c) Extract and isolate essential oils",
            "d) To purify drinking water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The steam Distillation is used to extract and isolate essential oils from plants for use in natural products. From an inlet, steam is inserted through the plant material comprising the desired oils, where the plant’s aromatic molecules are released and changed them into vapor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "What is the advantage of steam distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduces decomposition of temperature-sensitive compounds",
            "b) Reduces decomposition of inorganic compounds",
            "c) Increases the decomposition of temperature-sensitive compounds",
            "d) Increases the decomposition of inorganic compounds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The advantage of steam distillation is that the reduction of decomposition of temperature-sensitive compounds due to lower boiling point. It is useful for the purification of organic compounds\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Who invented steam distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Avicenna",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Nicolas Appert",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Avicenna invented steam distillation. Charles Chamberland developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Nicolas Appert is the father of food technology. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "How to extract oil from cinnamon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steam distillation",
            "b) Hydro distillation",
            "c) Fractional distillation",
            "d) Boiling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Limonene is a high-boiling liquid which decomposes under the high heat therefore steam distillation is used to obtain essential oils, as distillation of co-mixture of oil and water at a lower boiling point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "How long is steam distillation takes place for lavender?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 hours",
            "b) 3 hours",
            "c) 4 hours",
            "d) 5 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steam distillation is used in isolation of organic compounds that tend to decompose at high sustained temperatures. When the substances are very sensitive to heat, then steam distillation is applied under reduced pressure, thereby reducing the operating temperature further.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "What is still in distillation terminology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the apparatus to be used for distillation",
            "b) It is the liquid that is collected in collection flask",
            "c) It is the end product obtained in distillation",
            "d) It is the liquid injected during distillation process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steam distillation is used to extract oil from cinnamon. This is due to the reduction of decomposition of temperature-sensitive compounds due to lower boiling point in this process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "What are variants of the steam distillation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry steam distillation",
            "b) Hydro-distillation",
            "c) Direct steam distillation",
            "d) Dry steam distillation, direct steam distillation and hydro-distillation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lavender can be fully distilled in 2 hours. The process is conducted in a distillation until it uses water to remove the essential oil from the plant material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true of steam distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very long extraction times",
            "b) High energy consumption",
            "c) No need for subsequent separation steps",
            "d) Very short extraction times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The distillation apparatus is normally called a still that consists of a vessel for plant material and water, which is condenser for cooling and condensing the vapor produced and a collection flask,.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "What is use of Raoult’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calculate the concentration of an unknown solute",
            "b) Calculate the molecular mass of an unknown solute",
            "c) Calculate the molecular mass of an unknown solution",
            "d) Calculate the concentration of an unknown solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Raoult’s law states that vapor pressure of a solution is equal to the sum of the vapor pressures of each volatile component if it were pure multiplied by the mole fraction of that component in the solution. Raoult’s law can be used to calculate the molecular mass of an unknown solute.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "What is the use of vacuum distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mix components at lower temperature",
            "b) Separate components at higher temperature",
            "c) Separate components at lower temperature",
            "d) Mix components at higher temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The main principle is that the compounds boil at lower Temperature when pressure is reduced. Therefore vacuum distillation is useful to separate components at lower temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "What is atmospheric distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Separate low boiling fraction of mixture",
            "b) Separate high boiling fraction of mixture",
            "c) Concentration of low boiling fraction of mixture",
            "d) Concentration of high boiling fraction of mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Atmospheric distillation is used to separate low boiling fraction of mixture whereas vacuum distillation allows the components to be separated easily by lowering the boiling point of a high boiling fraction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "What are the different methods of extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2 Extraction",
            "b) Solvent Extraction",
            "c) Steam Distillation",
            "d) Steam Distillation, Solvent Extraction, CO2  Extraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Different methods of extraction are steam Distillation, solvent Extraction, CO2  extraction, maceration, enfleurage, cold press extraction and water distillation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "What are the steps of distillation in alcohol manufacturing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fermentation, Distillation, and Finishing",
            "b) Fermentation, Finishing",
            "c) Fermentation, Distillation",
            "d) Distillation, Finishing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Batch processes are economical for small volumes. These are flexible in changing production rate. These are flexible in accommodating changes in product formulation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "What are benefits of vacuum distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faster processing time",
            "b) Slower processing time",
            "c) Low quality",
            "d) Low feeding rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The overall process of alcohol distillation can be briefed into 3 parts. They are fermentation, distillation and finishing. In this distillation process, the liquid purification is done for removing the diluting components such as water from the liquid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "What are the benefits of hydro distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low temperature distillation method",
            "b) High temperature distillation method",
            "c) Low concentration distillation method",
            "d) Highconcentration distillation method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Benefits of vacuum distillation are faster processing time and effective distillation while under the maximum temperature of the distillation unit.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "How are crystals classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) According to the place of origin",
            "b) According to the position of the unit cells",
            "c) According to the symmetry of the unit cells",
            "d) According to the purity of the unit cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The crystals structures are classified according to the symmetry of the unit cells. There are in 7 groups, collectively called Crystal Systems, they are monoclinic, tricinic, orthorhombic, tetragonal, trigonal, cubic and hexagonal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "What is crystallography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Description of arrangement of atoms",
            "b) Description of the purity of crystals",
            "c) Description of the sign language",
            "d) Description of the crystals history"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lattice point is a point in a crystal with specific arrangement of atoms, replicated many times in the crystal. A primitive unit cell contains one lattice point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "What is crystal basis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disposition of the atoms around each lattice point",
            "b) Description of the purity of crystals",
            "c) Description of arrangement of atoms",
            "d) Description of the crystals history"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The crystal structure is given in the form of description of the ordered arrangement of atoms, ions or molecules in a crystalline material is called as crystallography.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "What is the most common crystal structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Face-centered cubic and square packed structures",
            "b) Face-centered cubic and hexagonal close-packed structures",
            "c) Square packed structures and hexagonal close-packed structures",
            "d) Square packed structures and parallelogram packed structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The actual nature of the atoms or ions around each lattice point is called the crystal basis. From the provisional details of the bonding and the crystal chemistry, it can contain more than one stoichiometric unit.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "What is the strongest crystal structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diamond",
            "b) Cubic boron nitride",
            "c) Silicon carbide",
            "d) Graphite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A Face-centered cubic (FCC) unit cell contains atoms at all the corners of the crystal lattice and also at the center of all the faces of the cube whereas hexagonal close-packed (hcp) arrangement has a unit cell which consists of three layers of atoms. The top and bottom layers contain six atoms at the corners of a hexagon and one atom at the center of each hexagon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Who discovered crystal structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Max von Laue",
            "b) Erasmus Jacobs",
            "c) Nicholas-Jacques Conte",
            "d) A.L. Lavoisier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diamond is a crystal form of carbon. The particular crystal structure is face-centered cubic and often called as diamond cubic crystal structure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "What are Miller indices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Set of three numbers used to indicate the position of a face of a crystal",
            "b) Set of four numbers used to indicate the position of a face of a crystal",
            "c) Set of five numbers used to indicate the position of a face of a crystal",
            "d) Set of six numbers used to indicate the position of a face of a crystal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diamond is the hardest material and cubic boron nitride is the second-hardest. Silicon carbide is very structurally complex and has at least 70 crystalline forms.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "What is meant by crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration of atoms into a highly structured form",
            "b) Solidification of atoms into a highly structured form",
            "c) Solidification of solution",
            "d) Concentration of solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Crystallization is solidification of atoms into a highly structured form called a crystal. It is the solid-liquid separation and purification technique where mass transfer occurs from the liquid solution to a pure solid crystalline phase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "When is supersaturation attained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the solvent contains more solute",
            "b) When the solute contains more solvent",
            "c) When the solvent contains less solute",
            "d) When the solute contains less solvent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Supersaturation is defined as the state in which the solvent contains more dissolved solids (solute) than can usually be accommodated at that temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Which of the following is crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid-solid separation",
            "b) Solid-liquid separation",
            "c) solid-gas separation",
            "d) Liquid- gas separation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Crystallization is solidification of atoms into a highly structured form called a crystal. It is the solid-liquid separation and purification technique where mass transfer occurs from the liquid solution to a pure solid crystalline phase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "What is purpose of recrystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To purify chemicals",
            "b) To dissolve crystals",
            "c) Continuous process of crystallization",
            "d) To clean crystallizers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Recrystallization is a technique used to purify chemicals. By dissolving both impurities and a compound in an appropriate solvent, either the desired component or impurities can be removed from the solution, parting the other behind.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "How does concentration affect crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in concentration leads to large crystals",
            "b) Decrease in concentration leads to large crystals",
            "c) Increase in concentration leads to small crystals",
            "d) Decrease in concentration leads to small crystals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the water evaporates faster the concentration increases. The larger crystals can accommodate larger the surface where more molecules can be added.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "What are crystallization techniques?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradual cooling and diffusion",
            "b) Diffusion and sharp cooling",
            "c) Gradual cooling and sharp cooling",
            "d) Sharp cooling and crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crystallization is a technique used to for solids purification. The two common methods of crystallization are gradual cooling and diffusion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Why is a supersaturated solution unstable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration is higher than equilibrium concentration",
            "b) Concentration is lower than equilibrium concentration",
            "c) Concentration is equal to equilibrium concentration",
            "d) Contains impurities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The solute in a supersaturated solution is present in concentration higher than equilibrium concentration; therefore the supersaturated solutions are unstable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "What are factors affecting crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Degree of agglomeration",
            "b) Crystal shape",
            "c) Particle size distribution",
            "d) Particle size distribution, crystal shape, degree of agglomeration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors affecting crystallization are particle size distribution, crystal shape, degree of agglomeration, purity and caking behavior.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "How does temperature affect nucleation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When temperature increases the nucleation decreases",
            "b) When temperature increases the nucleation increases",
            "c) Nucleation is not dependent on Temperature",
            "d) When temperature increases the nucleation increases and then decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the nucleation decrease drastically as the temperature increases. Thus, the decrease in nucleation at higher temperature leads to the decrease in supersaturation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "What happens when supersaturated solution is cooled down?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid crystals will dissolve into the water",
            "b) Solid crystals remain as it is in water",
            "c) Solid crystals will grow in bigger size",
            "d) Solid crystals will shrink into smaller size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The solid crystals dissolve into the water in the hydrated crystals forming a supersaturated solution. Adding small crystal in the supersaturated solution causes the liquid to change to the solid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "What is supersaturation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Has a higher vapor pressure than that of vapor pressure of that compound",
            "b) Has a lower vapor pressure than that of vapor pressure of that compound",
            "c) Has equal pressure similar to vapor pressure of that compound",
            "d) Does not depend on vapor pressure of that compound"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Supersaturation is defined as to a vapor of a compound which has a higher pressure than vapor pressure of that compound. It is also defined as the solution containing more of the dissolved material than equilibrium by the solvent at standard conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "What is the principle of supersaturation in vapor phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poynting effect",
            "b) Gibbs–Thomson effect and Poynting effect",
            "c) Kelvin equation and Gibbs–Thomson effect",
            "d) Kelvin equation, Gibbs–Thomson effect and Poynting effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The supersaturation in vapor phase is based on the surface tension of liquids through Kelvin equation, Gibbs–Thomson effect and Poynting effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which of the industry uses the In vivo supersaturation phenomenon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fashion industry",
            "b) Pharma industry",
            "c) Food industry",
            "d) Cement industry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pharma industry uses In vivo supersaturation phenomenon as orally administered components that undergo supersaturation as they move through the gastrointestinal tract.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "How can supersaturated solution used in marine ecologist?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To study the activity of organisms",
            "b) Tostudy the concentration of water",
            "c) To study the patterns of the organisms",
            "d) To detect the populations adaption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The supersaturated solutions are used for marine ecologists to study the activity of organisms and populations. Photosynthetic organisms release O2 gas into the water. Therefore, area of the ocean is supersaturated with O2 gas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "What is the other name for super-cooling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Undercooling",
            "b) Overcooling",
            "c) Cooling",
            "d) Super cooling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Super-cooling is also termed as under-cooling. In this process, the temperature of the of liquid or gas is lowered below its freezing point devoid of it changing to solid state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "What is the first step in crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleation",
            "b) Cooling",
            "c) Super-cooling",
            "d) Pre-crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nucleation is the first step in the formation of crystals. The liquids and solutions are cooled down where the liquid or solution is considerably less thermodynamically stable than the crystal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "What is classical nucleation theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To study the kinetics of nucleation",
            "b) To study the nucleation statists",
            "c) To study the concentration of nucleation",
            "d) To study the nucleation temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Study of the kinetics of nucleation uses the classical nucleation theory which is the most common theoretical model. Homogeneous nucleation is fewer than heterogeneous nucleation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "What affects crystal growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Evaporation",
            "d) Evaporation, pressure and temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Seed crystal provides a nucleation site on which crystals begin to grow. The recrystallization of the excess dissolved solute in a supersaturated solution can be originated by adding small crystal of solute is called a seed crystal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "What is co-crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel arrangement in crystallization",
            "b) Catalysts",
            "c) Cross arrangements in crystallization",
            "d) Seeding agents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Co crystallization or seedling agents are the process by which a solid forms, where the molecules are very organized and forms into a structure known as a crystal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "What is the mechanism of crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleation, crystal maturation and growth",
            "b) Nucleation and growth",
            "c) Nucleation, growth, and crystal maturation",
            "d) Nucleation and crystal maturation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mechanism of crystallization includes in the order of nucleation, growth and finally maturation of the crystals, thus leading to the crystalline lattice.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "What is crystallization temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature at which the brine solution is partially saturated",
            "b) Temperature at which the brine solution is fully saturated",
            "c) Temperature at which the solute and solvent is fully saturated",
            "d) Temperature at which the solute and solvent is partially saturated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The thermodynamic crystallization temperature which is also called as true crystallization temperature is defined as the temperature at which the brine solution is completely saturated with respect to the least soluble salt.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Who invented crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jabir ibn Hayyan",
            "b) Charles Chamberland",
            "c) Willis Carrier",
            "d) Clarence Birdseye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Under crystal nucleation, the process follows the number of formed crystal nuclei increases with supersaturation. When the temperature of crystallization process changes therefore the crystal size is also changed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "What is special form of cooling crystallization process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freeze crystallization",
            "b) Slow crystallization",
            "c) Melt crystallization",
            "d) Quick crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In evaporative crystallization, the process is due to the evaporation of solvent. So, therefore this process creates vapor and suspension of crystals in mother liquor. The evaporation heat is added in the captured vapor stream.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which process is called as a counter-current cascade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fractional crystallization",
            "b) Cooling crystallization",
            "c) Precipitation",
            "d) Evaporative crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jabir ibn Hayyan invented crystallization. Charles Chamberland developed the first pressure steam sterilizer. Willis Carrier invented the chillers. Clarence Birdseye developed processes for freezing fish based on quick freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "What is nucleation in crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the initial step in crystallization",
            "b) It is the final step in crystallization",
            "c) It is the step where nucleus is added",
            "d) It is the sub category crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nucleation is the initial process that occurs in the formation of a crystal from a solution, a liquid, or a vapor, in which a small number of molecules arranged in a pattern.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "How to initiate crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adding seed crystals",
            "b) Adjusting temperature",
            "c) Adjusting pressure",
            "d) Adjusting concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crystallization can be spontaneous or can be done by addition of small amount of the seed crystal or the pure compound to the saturated solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "How does temperature affect nucleation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleation is directly proportional to temperature",
            "b) Nucleation is indirectly proportional to temperature",
            "c) Nucleation and temperature are always at equilibrium",
            "d) Nucleation and temperature does not depend on each other"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The decrease in nucleation centers at high temperature interprets that decrease in supersaturation, would increase in critical size of nucleus and free energy of nucleus formation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "What is nucleation in freezing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process of gathering of molecules into tiny clusters",
            "b) It is the final step in freezing",
            "c) It is the step where nucleus is added",
            "d) It is the sub category freezing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nucleation is a process where the molecules or the atoms in a liquid start to gather into tiny clusters, arranging to form the crystal structure of the solid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "What is homogeneous nucleation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spontaneously generated nuclei",
            "b) Randomly generated nuclei",
            "c) Orderly generated nuclei",
            "d) Randomly and spontaneously generated nuclei"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The time until the presence of the first crystal is called primary nucleation time, it refers to the first nucleus to form. It describes the transition to a new phase which does not rely on the new phase which is already present.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "What is seeding in crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the initial step in crystallization",
            "b) It is the final step in crystallization",
            "c) It is the step where nucleus is added",
            "d) It is the sub category crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Homogeneous nucleation is the process by which nuclei that are randomly and spontaneously generated grow irreversibly to form a new phase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "What are the factors that affect crystallization seedling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature and pressure",
            "b) Polymorphism of the crystals and pressure",
            "c) Crystal size distribution and temperature",
            "d) Crystal size distribution and polymorphism of the crystals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Crystal seeding is the process of adding homogeneous or heterogeneous crystals to a crystallizing solution to nucleate and grow more crystals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "What causes crystal growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vapor",
            "b) Solute",
            "c) Melt",
            "d) Vapor, solution and melt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Crystals grow in one of three major ways; they are from a vapor, from a solution and from a melt where few molecules or ions come near each other in an appropriate orientation to form a stable submicroscopic aggregate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Why is crystal growth important?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase the value of the product",
            "b) Increase the size of the compound",
            "c) Information about the structure of compounds",
            "d) Information regarding the quality of product"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Crystals are very important and one of the reasons for the importance is that they give us information regarding the structure of compounds and also the function of the crystals and its effect on other compounds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Which crystal grows the fastest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Table salt",
            "b) Epsom salt",
            "c) Ferro sulphate salt",
            "d) Sea salt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The simplest and fastest crystals to grow are the Epsom salt (magnesium sulfate) crystals. These salts are used as healing agent and pain reliever.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of seed crystal in crystal growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleation center",
            "b) Catalyst",
            "c) Solvent",
            "d) Solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Warm temperature helps in water evaporation which causes the crystals to grow more quickly. Crystals will still grow in cooler temperatures, but take longer time for the water to evaporate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "What happens when a crystal grows in size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It becomes softer",
            "b) It becomes smoother",
            "c) It becomes rough",
            "d) It becomes coarsely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The seed crystal acts as a nucleation center for the crystal and it promotes the growth of crystal. The orientation of seed crystal regulates the orientation of crystals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "At what temperature do ice crystals form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower than 0°C",
            "b) More than 0°C",
            "c) At 0°C",
            "d) At 4°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When water freezes, the water molecules slowed down arrange themselves into fixed positions. Water molecules freeze in hexagonal pattern and the molecules are further apart than they were in liquid water. The molecules in ice vibrate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "How to prevent sugar from crystallizing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By evaporating",
            "b) By boiling",
            "c) By adding an interferent",
            "d) By adding an humectant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As a crystal grows, new atoms attribute easily to the rougher and less stable parts of the surface, but less easily to the flat and stable sides. Therefore, the flat surfaces tend to grow larger and smoother, until the whole crystal surface consists of these plane surfaces.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "What is the main feature of circulating liquid crystallizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficiency is high",
            "b) Supersaturation is created in a separate region",
            "c) Low capital cost",
            "d) Easy maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specialty of circulating liquor crystallizer is that supersaturation is produced in a separate region before the liquor flows into crystal suspension vessel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "What is evaporative crystallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporation of the solvent",
            "b) Separate components at higher temperature",
            "c) Separate components at lower temperature",
            "d) Mix components at higher temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crystallization is due to evaporation of the solvent. It creates a vapor and a suspension of crystals in the mother liquor. The evaporation heat is added in the vapor stream.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which of the manufacturing unit use melt crystallizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ice creams",
            "b) Automobiles",
            "c) Salt preparation",
            "d) Semiconductor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Crystals form in these crystallizers is from the high-quality melts which has large yields, pure and defect free crystals. These are typically used for semiconductor manufacture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "How are crystals in precipitation vessels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small size",
            "b) Large size",
            "c) Medium size",
            "d) Very large size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In precipitation vessels, the feed streams entering the vessel produce high supersaturation levels by chemical reaction and therefore produces very rapidly a large numbers of small crystals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "What is salting out process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition of salt to precipitate the product from solvent",
            "b) Addition of salt to precipitate the product from solution",
            "c) Removal of salt to in the product",
            "d) Removal of salt to precipitate the product from solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A crystallizer’s design sequence involves the basic data collection following selection of the supersaturation generation method and choosing the batch/continuous operation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "How is product purity increased?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boiling",
            "b) Sweating",
            "c) Freezing",
            "d) Adding solute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Salting out is the process where salt with common ion is added to precipitate product from solution. This is similar to the characteristics of reaction crystallization.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "What are the key parameters of rate of generation of supersaturation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cooling and addition rate",
            "b) Evaporation and addition rate",
            "c) Cooling and evaporation",
            "d) Cooling, evaporation or addition rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The purity of is increased by sweating process. In this process, the impurities are removed out of the solidified crystals before recovery process. The period of released pressure from the substance is used as sweating time\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "What are the advantages of vacuum crystallizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low yield of crystals",
            "b) Small crystals",
            "c) Increase in color formation",
            "d) Reduced color formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Advantages of vacuum crystallizers are controlled crystallization and bigger and more uniform crystals. Reduced color formation and high yield of crystals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "What is the principle behind forced-circulation crystallizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporative crystallization",
            "b) Cooling crystallization",
            "c) Perceptive cooling crystallization",
            "d) Freezing crystallization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Forced circulation crystallizers are evaporative crystallizers. They create a super saturated solution by evaporating solvent of the saturated solution. The solute of this supersaturated solution cools down, thus forming the crystals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "What is the name of the unwanted crystals in draft tube baffle crystallizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fines",
            "b) Powder",
            "c) Soap",
            "d) Low quality crystals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Advantages of membrane separation process are least expensive type of crystallizer and high rate of circulation reduces particle deposits on vessel walls and limitation is that difficult to control crystal size.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "What is residence time for draft tube baffle crystallizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 3 hours",
            "b) 4 to 6 hours",
            "c) 7 to 9 hours",
            "d) 10 to 11 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The draft Tube Baffle crystallizers are used where excessive nucleation occurs. Small, and unwanted crystals called as fines are removed from larger particles using gravitational settling method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "What is surface-cooled crystallizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combination of draft tube baffle crystallizer body with a heat exchanger",
            "b) Combination of forced circulation crystallizer body with a heat exchanger",
            "c) Combination of vacuum body with a heat exchanger",
            "d) Combination of crystallizer body with a heat exchanger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The draft tube baffle crystallizers usually have circulation rates of 1 to 4 times/min and a total residence time of 4 to 6 hours.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "What is not true about scraped surface crystallizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low energy",
            "b) Low cost",
            "c) Ideal for small scale operation",
            "d) Less consumption of time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Disadvantages of draft tube baffle crystallizers frequent flushing required minimizing deposits on the crystallizer wall and cannot effectively handle a high density slurry whereas the merits are easy control of crystal size and more energy efficient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "What is crystallizer used for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid-solid separation",
            "b) Solid separation",
            "c) Liquid – liquid separation",
            "d) Gas – solid separation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The surface cooled crystallizer is the combination of a draft tube baffle crystallizer body with a heat exchanger. The slurry is strained from the crystallizer body and then cooled before being pumped back into crystallizer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Where is sedimentation used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water treatment",
            "b) Oil production",
            "c) Essential oil production",
            "d) Salt production"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sedimentation is the physical water treatment process using gravity to remove suspended solids and other impurities from the water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "What are benefits of sedimentation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective in removing fine particles",
            "b) Effective in removing viruses",
            "c) Effective in removing bacteria",
            "d) Effective in removing yeast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sedimentation is the process where by using coagulant the time required to settle out suspended solids is reduced and is very effective in removing fine particles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "What is sedimentation principle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centrifugal acceleration",
            "b) Gravity",
            "c) Electromagnetism",
            "d) Gravity, centrifugal acceleration and electromagnetism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sedimentation is the affinity for components in suspension to settle down against a barrier. This is due to forces acting on them. These forces are gravity, centrifugal acceleration and electromagnetism.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Where does sedimentation value used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bread",
            "b) Chocolate",
            "c) Salt",
            "d) Sugar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sedimentation value is the degree of sedimentation of flour suspended in a lactic acid solution through a standard time interval and it is a measure of the baking quality.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "What are the factors affecting sedimentation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration, particle size",
            "b) Temperature, particle size",
            "c) Pressure, concentration",
            "d) Pressure, particle size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Factors affecting sedimentation rate are particle size, density and concentration, and fluid viscosity, convection currents in the surrounding fluid, particle shape and orientation, and chemical pretreatment of the feed suspension.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Which law is related to sedimentation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gauss’s law",
            "b) Stroke’s law",
            "c) Dalton’s law",
            "d) Newton’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sedimentation velocity is an analytical ultracentrifugation process which measures the rate of molecules movement in response to centrifugal force produced in a centrifuge. It provides information about both the shape of molecules and molecular mass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "What is Zeleny test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quality of pulses",
            "b) Quality of wheat",
            "c) Quality of sugar",
            "d) Quality of oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sedimentation investigation is established on stokes law permitting to which the velocity at which the particles settles down depends on size, shape and weight of grain.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Who invented sedimentation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Newton",
            "b) G.G. Stokes",
            "c) Antonin Prandtl",
            "d) Al-Kindi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Zeleny sedimentation test is used for evaluating the quality of wheat for the baking strength of the flour. This method is applicable only to Triticum aestivum L. wheat.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "What should be the velocity for the sedimentation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Does not depend",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In sedimentation tank, the continuous flow through the equipment is commonly desired, so therefore the flow velocities have to be low enough to avoid unsettling of the sediment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "What is flotation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removal of fine particles by air bubbles",
            "b) Removal of fine particles by sedimentation",
            "c) Removal of fine particles by chelating agents",
            "d) Removal of large particles by air bubbles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In some cases, where it is difficult to remove fine particles, therefore floatation equipment is used where these are floated to the surface with the help of air bubbles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Which of the following food industry uses floatation equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sugar industry",
            "b) Oil industry",
            "c) Bakery industry",
            "d) Salt industry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the food industry, floatation is used in the separation of small particles of fat from water. The air dissolved in water under pressure produces the froth. When the pressure suddenly released, the air comes out of solution in the form of bubbles which rise and carry the fat with them to surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "What is limitation of large sedimentation tank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regarding contact time",
            "b) Regarding efficiency",
            "c) Regarding quality",
            "d) Regarding quantity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disadvantages of large sedimentation tank are the slow rate of sedimentation, it requires large chamber areas and the long contact times between particles and the heated air that results in deterioration of heat-sensitive products.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "What is the accumulated at the bottom in sedimentation tank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solute",
            "b) Solvent",
            "c) Solution",
            "d) Sludge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the sedimentation tank, a layer of accumulated solids is formed at the bottom of the tank and is periodically removed. This is known as sludge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "What are clarifiers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal basin sedimentation tank",
            "b) Circular basin sedimentation tank",
            "c) Vertical basin sedimentation tank",
            "d) Square basin sedimentation tank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ballasted flocculation is a high-rate, physical-chemical sedimentation process involving the fixing of flocs, or suspended solids, onto ballast generally sand with the help of a polymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "How is sludge removed from sedimentation tank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scraper",
            "b) Air",
            "c) Vacuum devices",
            "d) Scraper and vacuum devices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Circular basins are called as clarifiers. These basins are similar to rectangular basins,   but are more prone to short circuiting and particle removal problems.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "What is the largest portion of the sedimentation basin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sludge zone",
            "b) Settling zone",
            "c) Inlet zone",
            "d) Outlet zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Sludge is removed from the sludge zone in sedimentation tank by scraper or vacuum devices which move along the bottom. Low flow velocities are allowed to enter the sludge zone, or else the sludge could be swept up and out of tank.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "What is the principle of centrifugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sedimentation principle",
            "b) Filtration principle",
            "c) Evaporation principle",
            "d) Size reduction principle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Centrifuge works using the sedimentation principle, due to centrifugal acceleration denser substances move outward in the radial direction and that are less dense are displaced and move to the center.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "What is called centrifugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Separated through spinning",
            "b) Separate components at higher temperature",
            "c) Separate components at lower temperature",
            "d) Separated through evaporation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Centrifugation is the process where a mixture is separated through spinning. It is used to separate skim milk from whole milk, washing machine and blood cells from your blood plasma.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Who invented centrifugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Newton",
            "b) G.G. Stokes",
            "c) Antonin Prandtl",
            "d) Al-Kindi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: G.G. Stokes invented sedimentation. Newton discovered gravity. Antonin Prandtl invented centrifugation. Al-Kindi invented distillation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "What is use of density gradient centrifugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To purify viruses, ribosomes, membranes",
            "b) Toremovedirt",
            "c) To remove fine particles",
            "d) To remove large particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Density gradient centrifugation is used to purify viruses, ribosomes, membranes. A sucrose density gradient is created by gently overlaying lower concentrations of sucrose on higher concentrations in centrifuge tubes where particles of interest are placed on top in ultracentrifuges. The particles move through the gradient until they reach the same sucrose density and fraction is removed and analyzed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "What is other name for zonal centrifugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isopyniccentrifugation",
            "b) Gradient centrifugation",
            "c) Density gradient centrifugation",
            "d) Differential centrifugation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Differential pelleting centrifugation is the most common type of centrifugation used. Tissue like liver is homogenized.After sedimentation, the bottom is called pellet and an overlying solution called supernatant. The overlying solution is then placed in another centrifuge tube for progressing steps.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Which centrifugation depends on buoyant densities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isopynic centrifugation",
            "b) Gradient centrifugation",
            "c) Density gradient centrifugation",
            "d) Differential centrifugation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Zonal centrifugation is also known as band or gradient centrifugation and relies on the concept of sedimentation coefficient. In this process, a density gradient is created in a test tube with sucrose and high density at the bottom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "What are applications of centrifugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To separate two miscible substances and analyze the hydrodynamic properties of macromolecules",
            "b) To separate two miscible substances and water treatment",
            "c) Purification of mammalian cells and water treatment",
            "d) Analyze the hydrodynamic properties of macromolecules and water treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Isopynic centrifugation depends on buoyant densities, not on the velocities. CsCl, NaI gradients are the self-forming gradients for macromolecules and nucleotides under centrifugal force.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "What is maximum speed of low speed centrifuge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000-2000rpm",
            "b) 3000-4000rpm",
            "c) 4000-5000rpm",
            "d) 5000-6000rpm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most laboratories have a low-speed centrifuge used for routine sedimentation of heavy particles and the low-speed centrifuge has a maximum speed of 4000-5000rpm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Which of the following used for sedimentation of red blood cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low speed centrifuge",
            "b) High speed centrifuge",
            "c) Ultra centrifuge",
            "d) Vacuum centrifuge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Low speed centrifuge is used for sedimentation of red blood cells until the particles are tightly packed into a pellet and supernatant is separated by decantation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "What is maximum speed of high speed centrifuge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10000-20000rpm",
            "b) 15000-20000rpm",
            "c) 30000-50000rpm",
            "d) 50000-60000rpm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High-speed centrifuges are used in biochemical applications. The high-speed centrifuge has a maximum speed of 15,000 – 20,000 RPM.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "What are factors that affect high-speed centrifuges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed and temperature",
            "b) Pressure and temperature",
            "c) Concentration and speed",
            "d) Pressure and speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High-speed centrifuges are used in biochemical applications, the factors that affect are higher speeds and temperature control of the rotor chamber.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Which industry uses centrifuge test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sugar industry",
            "b) Oil industry",
            "c) Bakery industry",
            "d) Salt industry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ultracentrifuge has a maximum speed of 65,000 RPM. Intense heat is generated due to high speed thus the spinning chambers must be refrigerated and kept at a high vacuum. It is used for both preparative work and analytical work.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "What is the other name for screen centrifuge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low speed centrifuge",
            "b) High speed centrifuge",
            "c) Ultra centrifuge",
            "d) Conveyor discharge centrifuge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In horizontal bowl scroll discharge, centrifugal forces cause immediate sedimentation of the solids on the wall of bowl. The conveyor rotates in the same direction as the bowl, but at different speed, thus moving the solids near the conical end of the bowl.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Which centrifuge used for separating caffeine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low speed centrifuge",
            "b) Peeler centrifuge",
            "c) Ultra centrifuge",
            "d) Conveyor discharge centrifuge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oil industries uses centrifuge test. A Centrifuge test is a fully programmable process which allows automatic configuration of specified oil test parameters.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "What is the fixed angle of rotors in centrifuge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10° and 20°",
            "b) 14° and 40°",
            "c) 20° and 40°",
            "d) 34° and 48°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Screen centrifuge is also known as worm screen or conveyor discharge centrifuge. It is widely used for the separation of crystalline, granular or fibrous materials from a solid-liquid mixture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "What are the types of filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biological filtration",
            "b) Chemical filtration",
            "c) Mechanical filtration",
            "d) Mechanical, biological and chemical filtration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Filtration is responsible for moving and cleaning the tank water by removing insoluble impurities. The three main types of filtration are mechanical, biological and chemical filtration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "What is the media used in chemical filteration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soap",
            "b) Detergents",
            "c) Salt",
            "d) Activated carbons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The chemical method of filtration removes dissolved particulates from the water tank with the help of activated carbons, resins, and other adsorbents. Chemical filtration media helps to maintain water quality as unwanted dissolved matter adheres to it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "What is other name for biological filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen cycle",
            "b) Nitrogen cycle",
            "c) Carbon cycle",
            "d) Methane cycle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Biological filtration is the action of bacteria breaking down dangerous ammonia, converting them to nitrites, and then the nitrites to the less toxic nitrates. The process is also known as the nitrogen cycle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "What is residue in filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid portion after filtration",
            "b) Solid portion before filtration",
            "c) Liquid portion after filtration",
            "d) Liquid portion before filtration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The filtration aids in filtering unwanted materials from food and beverages. It separates desirable materials from ingredients, food and beverage products and waste streams. Concentrate ingredients such as tea or protein. Clarify and purify food and beverage products. It also recover aromas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "What type of mixture is separated by filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid-liquid mixture",
            "b) Liquid -liquid mixture",
            "c) Solid-solid mixture",
            "d) Solid- gas mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The residue is the solid portion obtained after a filtration process. The solid residue is trapped on the filter paper during the filtration. It could also signify that the residue is an undesired by-product of a chemical reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the driving force in filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum centrifuge",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Gravity",
            "d) Temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Carbon filtersremove the odor particles of the air and also neutralizing any odors that pass through. Activated carbon filters will not remove microbial contaminants like bacteria and viruses, calcium and magnesium, fluoride, nitrate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "What is the law behind filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Darcy’s law",
            "b) Henry’s law",
            "c) Dalton’s law",
            "d) Newton’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Filtration is used for separating heterogeneous mixture. It is usually used for separating a solid-liquid mixture. It removes suspended solid matter from a liquid, by passing through the pores of filter. The liquid passed through the filter is termed as the filtrate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "What is the advantage of vacuum filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficiency",
            "b) Faster than other filtration equipment",
            "c) Cost effective",
            "d) Low power cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vacuum filtration is used to collect a desired solid, normally in recrystallization for the collection of crystals. These are faster than gravity filtration, because the solvent and air is forced through the filter paper by the using reduced pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Why is cotton wool used in filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Remove fine particles",
            "b) Moderately coarsely particles",
            "c) Big particles",
            "d) Uniform particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Centrifugation controls the influence of the centrifugal force for the separation. Centrifugation filtration is a process that depends on rotation to separate high density substances from low density substances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "What is membrane filters made up of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose acetate",
            "b) Resins",
            "c) Positively charge ions",
            "d) Negatively charge ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cotton wool is used for filtering of moderately coarse particles. The disadvantage is presence of fine cotton hair in the filtrate. This is avoided by wetting the cotton wool plug with liquid before using it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "What is the disadvantage of the filter press?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The filtering media can be used repeatedly",
            "b) Operation and maintenance is simple",
            "c) It requires less space",
            "d) It is used where the proportion of solid in the liquid to be filtered is about 5% or less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The membrane filters are made of cellulose acetate and other cellulose derivatives, nylon and polyvinyl chloride. These are primarily used to remove microorganism and very fine particles from solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Where is Meta filters used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water treatment",
            "b) Metal recovery",
            "c) Clarification of syrups",
            "d) Oil recovery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The advantages of filter press are filtering media can be used repeatedly. Operation and maintenance is simple. It requires less space. It provides a large surface area for filtration. Efficient washing of cake is possible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "What is hot filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prevent virus during filtration",
            "b) Prevent bacteria during filtration",
            "c) Minimize crystal formation during filtration",
            "d) Prevent yeast during filtration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sintered filters are made of borosilicate glass. Borosilicate glass is finely Powdered sieved and desired particle size are separated. It is then packed into a disc mould and heated to a temperature where adhesion takes place between the particles. Finally the disc is then fused to a funnel of suitable shape and size.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "What is cold filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To quickly cool a solution",
            "b) Prevent bacteria during filtration",
            "c) Minimize crystal formation during filtration",
            "d) Prevent yeast during filtration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Meta filters have significant strength and therefore it can withstand the high pressure. The corrosive liquids can be filtered without any problem. It is a cost-effective filter. Cake is removed effectively without any difficulty.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "What is filter medium resistance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resistance by solids retained on filter",
            "b) Resistance by liquid",
            "c) Resistance due to pressure",
            "d) Resistance due to concentration gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Filter medium resistance is the resistance due to the solid particles which forms the cake and also the filter medium. It helps in measuring the average ability of solid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "What is the primary method of filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Straining",
            "b) Sedimentation",
            "c) Centrifuge",
            "d) Diffusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A particle is removed by straining when its size is larger than the size of the opening or the size of the pore in a filter bed. The primary method of filtration is straining.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "What are the compressible cake forming materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand",
            "b) Crystals",
            "c) Salt",
            "d) Cupric oxides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A filter cake is formed by metal hydroxide particles substances that are retained on a filter are called compressible cake forming materials. Examples are Ferric hydroxide, cupric oxide and aluminum oxide.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "What is present in filter medium in depth filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose",
            "b) Positive charge ions",
            "c) Salt",
            "d) Negative charge ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The filter medium consist of 0.5 to 3 m bed of coarse grains, layer of a few centimeters of fibers, cellulose sheets and a layer of granular filter aid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "What is the step involved in filter cake removal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Washingand de-liquoring",
            "b) Washing and adjusting temperature",
            "c) Washing and adjusting pressure",
            "d) De-liquoring and adjusting temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cake filtration is combined with washing and de-liquoring of the filter cake. The purpose of washing is to remove the mother liquor left behind in the cake after filtration when this liquid is regarded as contaminant or recovered as a valuable substance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "What is the demerit of de-liquoring by gas pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less efficacy",
            "b) Less efficiency",
            "c) Crack formation",
            "d) Time consumption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the de-liquoring is done by gas pressure, cracks may appear which let pass the washing liquid. In any case, de-liquoring should be avoided before the washing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "What happens when de-liquoring is done by compression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cake becomes impermeable",
            "b) Less efficiency",
            "c) Crack formation",
            "d) Time consumption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If de-liquoring is done by compression the cake becomes impermeable. Therefore the squeezing pressure for intermediate de-liquoring should be lower than the pressure for washing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "What are the incompressible cake forming materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand",
            "b) Ferric hydroxide",
            "c) Salt",
            "d) Cupric oxides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Filter cakes which are composed of inorganic material with large size are incompressible materials. Some of the examples are sand and crystals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "What is added to increase the permeability of filtrate cake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filter aid",
            "b) Salt",
            "c) Sand",
            "d) Ammonia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Filter aids are inert powders which are added in the filtration unit to the liquid to be filtered and this increases the porosity and permeability of the cake.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "What is the pore size in nano filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-10 nanometers",
            "b) 10-50 nanometers",
            "c) 50-100 nanometers",
            "d) 100-150 nanometers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nano-filtration is a membrane filtration based method that uses nanometer sized through pores that pass through the membrane. These membranes have pore sizes from 1-10 nanometers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "What is the pore size in micro filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Around 0.1 micron",
            "b) Around 0.01 micron",
            "c) Around 0.001 micron",
            "d) Around 0.0001 micron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A microfiltration filter has a pore size around 0.1 microns, so therefore when water undergoes microfiltration, microorganisms are removed, but viruses remain in the water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "What is the pore size in ultra-filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Around 0.1 micron",
            "b) Around 0.01 micron",
            "c) Around 0.001 micron",
            "d) Around 0.0001 micron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An ultrafiltration filter has a pore size around 0.01 microns. Ultrafiltration would remove larger particles and also remove some viruses. It is a membrane filtration process where hydrostatic pressure forces a liquid against a semi permeable membrane.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "What is the pore size in membrane filter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.12–0.25 μm",
            "b) 0.22–0.45 μm",
            "c) 0.32–0.55 μm",
            "d) 0.52–0.65 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Membrane filter has the pore size of 0.22–0.45 µm with thickness 150 µm, restricts the passing through activity of Pseudomonas aeruginosa and other bacterial species.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "What is filtration medium resistance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resistance by cake",
            "b) Resistance by filter medium",
            "c) Resistance by solution",
            "d) Resistance by cake and filter medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ultrafiltration, hydrostatic pressure forces liquid against a semi permeable membrane. Suspended solids and solutes of high molecular weight are retained whereas the water and low molecular weight solutes pass over the membrane.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Which principle is behind filtration medium resistance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Darcy’s law",
            "b) Henry’s law",
            "c) Dalton’s law",
            "d) Newton’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The filter medium resistance is the resistance due to the solid particles which forms the cake and also the filter medium. It has the meaning of the measure of the average ability of solid particles to pass through a filter medium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "What controls the filtration medium resistance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure drop alone",
            "b) Flow rate alone",
            "c) Both pressure drop and flow rate",
            "d) Cake thickness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Darcy’s law is used to determine the specific cake resistance and filtration medium resistance from the filtration. It is an equation that defines the ability of a fluid to flow through a porous media.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "How does filter medium resist?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Due to pressure difference",
            "b) Due to temperature difference",
            "c) Due to concentration difference",
            "d) Due to concentration and temperature difference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both pressure drop and flow rate controls the resistance due to the solid particles which forms the cake and also the filter medium. It also resists the influence of the force due to pressure difference across the filter medium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "What happens when the net driving force is positive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Net fluid filtration takes place",
            "b) Net fluid reabsorption takes place",
            "c) Net fluid filtration stops",
            "d) Net fluid filtration stops"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The net driving force for fluid movement is the net pressure gradient is known by the sum of the individual hydrostatic and oncotic pressures. When the net driving force is positive, there is net fluid filtration takes place.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "What happens when the net driving force is negative?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Net fluid filtration takes place",
            "b) Net fluid reabsorption takes place",
            "c) Net fluid filtration stops",
            "d) Net fluid filtration stops"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The net driving force is the net pressure gradient for a fluid movement. It is calculated as the sum of the individual oncotic and hydrostatic pressures. When net driving force is negative, there is net fluid reabsorption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "How does pressure drop at initial stage of filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure drop is small",
            "b) Pressure drop is large",
            "c) Does not depend on pressure drop",
            "d) At equilibrium throughout the process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The filter media exhibit a resistance to flow, which is increased by the solids deposit in the pores. For constant solids concentration at the inlet and constant retention the increase in this pressure drop with time is constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "When does the pressure difference increase in filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If the constant rate is maintained",
            "b) If the cake thickness decreases",
            "c) If the cake thickness increases",
            "d) There is no pressure difference throughout the process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the early stages of the filtration cycle, the pressure drop across the filter medium is small and filtration proceeds at constant rate. As the cake increases, the process becomes more and more a constant pressure one.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "What is capillary pressure curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A plot of saturation of the cake versus pressure difference",
            "b) A plot of saturation of the cake versus temperature difference",
            "c) A plot of concentration of the filtrate versus temperature difference",
            "d) A plot of concentration of the filtrate versus pressure difference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the thickness of the cake increases the resistance to flow of filtrate increases and rate of filtration gradually decreases. If rate is maintained to be constant then pressure difference driving force will increase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "What law is applicable when liquid velocity through the pores is low and pore size is small?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poiseuille’s law",
            "b) Newton’s law",
            "c) Gauss’s law",
            "d) Dalton’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A filter press uses increased pump pressure to maximize the filtration rate.Filter presses work in a batch manner. It is used in liquid/solid separation. It separates the solids and liquids using pressure filtration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "What is the main driving force for the filtrate flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference between the atmospheric pressure and the pressure in the equipment",
            "b) Atmospheric pressure only",
            "c) Partial pressure only",
            "d) Difference between the atmospheric pressure and the partial pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A plot of saturation of the cake versus pressure difference in an equilibrium state is called capillary pressure curve. It is used in reservoir engineering primarily for calculating initial fluid contacts and transition zones.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "How is flow rate calculated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Driving force + total resistance",
            "b) Driving force – total resistance",
            "c) Driving force x total resistance",
            "d) Driving force / total resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Flow rate is defined as the volume of fluid which passes per unit time. The flow rate in the filtration can be calculated as the ratio of the driving force to total resistance offered by the filter cake.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "How does the increase in filter cake affect the flow rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase then decrease",
            "b) Increase",
            "c) Decrease",
            "d) Does not depend"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A filter cake is formed by the substances that are retained on a filter. The filter cake grows in the course of filtration. With increasing layer thickness, the flow resistance of the filter cake increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "What law is applicable when the flow rate is laminar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poiseuille’s law",
            "b) Newton’s law",
            "c) Gauss’s law",
            "d) Dalton’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Filtration rate is directly proportional to the difference in pressure and inversely proportional to the fluid viscosity and to the hydraulic resistance of the cake and filter medium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "What is the relationship between temperature and filtrate volume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Indirectly proportional",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) Does not depend"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An increase in temperature increases the filtrate volume. This reduces the viscosity of the filtrate and therefore the filtrate volume also increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "What is the demerit of increase in filtrate volume during filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solvent recovery",
            "b) Time consumption",
            "c) Efficiency",
            "d) Power consumption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Disadvantages of increased filtrate volume are solvent recovery and flammability issues. The use of surfactants such as sulphosuccinates can increase filtration rates and reduce equilibrium cake moisture during gas de-liquoring.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "What is constant rate filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q=dV/dt is kept constant",
            "b) Q=dt/dV is kept constant",
            "c) Q=dp/dt is kept constant",
            "d) Q=dp/dV is kept constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The constant rate filtration Q=dV/dt is kept constant. The pressure drop is to be increased in order to overcome the increasing opposition due to cake build-up.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the factor that controls the rate of filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Particle Size of Solids.",
            "b) Ratio of slimes to coarser particles.",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Feed solids concentration."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Factors that control the rate of filtration are particle size of solids, ratio of slimes to coarser particles, filter aids, feed solids concentration, filter thickening, slurry pH and flocculation of fine solids\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "What is the relationship between concentration and filtrate volume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Indirectly proportional",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) Does not depend"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As concentration of the solids increases in the suspension, there is an increase in thickness of the filter cake. The filtration rate mainly depends on the viscosity of the slurry. Due to presence of solids in the suspension, a resistance force called viscosity is taken into consideration during the filtration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "What is rate of filtration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure of filtrate per unit volume",
            "b) Volume of filtrate collected per unit time",
            "c) Pressure of filtrate per unit time",
            "d) Volume of solution per unit time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Filtration rate is inversely proportional to concentration of the solution. When the solids are present in a very low concentration the filtration is high and rapid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "What are the size reduction laws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rittinger’s Law",
            "b) Kick’s Law",
            "c) Bond’s Law",
            "d) Bond’s Law, Rittinger’s Law, and Kick’s Law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are three physical laws that describe the energy required for size reduction. They are the Bond’s Law, Rittinger’s Law, and Kick’s Law. The size reduction is a unit operation where a set of conditions are performed until the size specified is achieved.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which mechanism is utilized when particle concussion by a single rigid force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact",
            "b) Compression",
            "c) Shear",
            "d) Tear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In impact force mechanism, the particle concussion by a single rigid force where usually hammer is used to create such force. It is a force that provides a shock in a relatively short period of time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "What is the mechanism of nut cracker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact",
            "b) Compression",
            "c) Shear",
            "d) Tear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the compression force the particle are disintegrated by two rigid forces. The nutcracker is based on this mechanism. Compression Force is the uses the power, exertion and pressure against an object which results in squeezing, squashing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "What is shear force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Force acting in direction parallel to surface of a body",
            "b) Force acting in direction perpendicular to surface of a body",
            "c) Force acting in direction longitudinal to surface of a body",
            "d) Force acting in direction vertical to surface of a body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shear force is the force acting in direction parallel to surface of a body, it is produced when the particle is compressed between the edges of two hard surfaces moving tangentially.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Why is uniform particle size important?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Color improvement",
            "b) Product stability",
            "c) Flavor improvement",
            "d) Color and flavor improvement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Size reduction is defined as the adding the energy to a material to make large pieces smaller. Particle size is important for product stability. It is achieves a quality end product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a size reduction unit operation in liquids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Milling",
            "b) Mixing",
            "c) Grinding",
            "d) Homogenization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Homogenization is a size reduction unit operation in liquids. It is used to produce a mixture of two mutually non-soluble liquids into homogenized solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "What are the factors affecting size reduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape and size",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Pressure",
            "d) Viscosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shape and size are the two important factors that affect size reduction unit operation. Size reduction is a process in which the particle size of a solid is made smaller and is applied in which particles of solids are made into smaller pieces.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "What is a hammer mill used for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crush larger pieces into small pieces",
            "b) To compress the raw materials",
            "c) Break down of liquefied emulsions",
            "d) Break smaller pieces into fine powder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A hammer mill is a mill which is used to shred or crush larger material into smaller pieces by the repeated blows of little hammers. It creates impact force.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "What is size reduction equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adding energy to a material to make large pieces smaller",
            "b) Removing energy to a material to make large pieces smaller",
            "c) Adding energy to a material to make small pieces larger",
            "d) Removing energy to a material to make small pieces larger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The size reduction is a unit operation where a set of conditions are performed until the size specified is achieved. It is based on the adding of the energy to a material which in turn produces smaller pieces from large pieces.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "What is use of edge runner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To crush the pieces",
            "b) To compress the pieces",
            "c) To tear the pieces",
            "d) To shear the pieces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Edge runner is a machine consisting of heavy steel rolls set on a horizontal shaft rotating round a pan that is used for crushing stone, fibrous matter for paper making  or other material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "What is the principle of particle size distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Based on light scattering",
            "b) Based on the pressure exerted by particles",
            "c) Based on the pressure exerted by equipment",
            "d) Based on the temperature exerted by particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The particle size distribution is based on the principle that when a ray of light is scattered by a set of particles, then the angle of scattering of light is indirectly proportional to the size of the particle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "What is Kick’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amount of energy required to tear the given material",
            "b) Amount of energy required to crush the given material",
            "c) Amount of energy required to compress the given material",
            "d) Amount of energy required to break the given material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The kick’s law is defined as the amount of energy required to crush a given amount of material to a specified fraction of its original size is the same, regardless of the original size.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "What is Rittinger’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Energy required is directly proportional to the increase in surface area",
            "b) Energy required is indirectly proportional to the increase in surface area",
            "c) Pressure required is directly proportional to the increase in surface area",
            "d) Pressure required is indirectly proportional to the increase in surface area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Rittinger’s law is stated as the energy required for reduction in particle size of a solid is directly proportional to the increase in surface area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "What is Bond’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work required is directly proportional to the surface to volume ratio",
            "b) Work required is indirectly proportional to the surface to volume ratio",
            "c) Energy required is directly proportional to the surface to volume ratio",
            "d) Energy required is directly proportional to the surface to volume ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bond’s law states that the work required to produce particles from large particle size is directly proportional to the square root of the surface-to-volume ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "Which of the following law determine energy requirement in size reduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kick’s law, Bond’s law",
            "b) Rittinger’s law, Bond’s law",
            "c) Rittinger’s law and Kick’s law",
            "d) Kick’s law, Bond’s law, Rittinger’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Crushing efficiency is defined as the ratio of surface energy created by crushing during crushing to the energy absorbed by the solid. Single layer particle crushing was taken to be 100% efficient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Which of the law is used for coarse grinding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rittinger’s Law",
            "b) Kick’s Law",
            "c) Bond’s Law",
            "d) Bond’s Law, Rittinger’s Law, and Kick’s Law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Determination of energy required in size reduction is generally done using Kick’s law or Rittinger’s law. The Rittinger’s law is stated as the energy required for reduction in particle size of a solid is directly proportional to the increase in surface area. The kick’s law is defined as the amount of energy required to crush a given amount of material to a specified fraction of its original size is the same, regardless of the original size.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Which of the law is used for fine grinding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rittinger’s Law",
            "b) Kick’s Law",
            "c) Bond’s Law",
            "d) Bond’s Law, Rittinger’s Law, and Kick’s Law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Kick’s law is used for coarse grinding when the size ratio of original material to end materials is 8:1. The kick’s law is defined as the amount of energy required to crush a given amount of material to a specified fraction of its original size is the same, regardless of the original size.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Which of the law is used for intermediate grinding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rittinger’s Law",
            "b) Kick’s Law",
            "c) Bond’s Law",
            "d) Bond’s Law, Rittinger’s Law, and Kick’s Law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rittinger’s Law is defined as the energy required for reducing the size of the solid particle is directly proportional to the increase in surface area. Rittinger’s Law is used for fine grinding.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "What is other name for attrition mill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolling compression mill",
            "b) Burr mill",
            "c) Jaw crusher",
            "d) Hammer mill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The working principle of the jaw crushers is motorized by a diesel or gas motor, the jaw crusher brakes materials in a crushing chamber. The materials are pushed inside the chamber from the top opening and when crushed they are released through the bottom opening.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Which of the following forces acts in ball mill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravitational force",
            "b) Centrifugal force",
            "c) Gravitational and centrifugal forces",
            "d) Does not depend on any force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is also known as burr mill. Grains are rubbed between the grooved flat faces of rotating circular disks where one plate is stationary and fixed with the body of the mill while the other one is rotating disk. Material is fed between the plates and is reduced by crushing and shear.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "What is the working principle of ball mill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact and attrition",
            "b) Compression and attrition",
            "c) Shear and compression",
            "d) Tear and impact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ball mills, product is released by the gravitational pull and drop to the bottom and the centrifugal force keeps the ball in contact with the mill wall. Due to centrifugal force, if the speed of rotation of mill is faster, the balls are carried to more distance therefore critical speed is required for rotational speed at which centrifuging occurs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "What is the working principle of triple roller mill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact",
            "b) Compression",
            "c) Shear",
            "d) Tear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Reduction Ratio is defined as the ratio of the feed size to the product size in any crushing operation. It is very useful in determining mechanism of crusher and type of size reduction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Which of the following machine is not used for fine grinding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jaw crushers",
            "b) Ball mill",
            "c) Hammer mill",
            "d) Attrition mill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ball mill works on the principle of impact and attrition. Size reduction is done by impact as the balls drop from near the top of the shell. A ball mill consists of a hollow cylindrical shell rotating about its axis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "What is the working principle of hammer mill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact",
            "b) Compression",
            "c) Shear",
            "d) Tear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A triple roll mill is a machine that uses shear force which is created by three horizontally positioned rolls rotating in the opposite directions and also with different speeds relative to each other. This is done in order to refine, mix, disperse and homogenize viscous materials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which of the following forces acts in attrition mill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact and crush",
            "b) Compression and impact",
            "c) Shear and crush",
            "d) Tear and impact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ball mill, Hammer mill and attrition mill are used for fine grinding whereas the jaw crushers, crusher rolls and gyratory crushers are used for coarse grinding.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Why hexane is used for extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy oil recovery",
            "b) Higher boiling point",
            "c) Easy separation",
            "d) Catalyst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hexane is commonly used for oil extraction because of the easy oil recovery, narrow boiling point and also has exceptional solubilizing capability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "What is solvent extraction process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Separate components based boiling point",
            "b) Separate compounds based on their relative solubility",
            "c) Separate components at lower temperature",
            "d) Separated through evaporation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solvent extraction is oil separation technique which is used to separate compounds based on their relative solubility in two dissimilar immiscible liquids, usually water and an organic solvent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Which of the following method uses odorless fats as solvent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2 Extraction",
            "b) Maceration",
            "c) Enfleurage",
            "d) Cold Press Extraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the enfleurage extraction method, petals are placed between layers of purified animal fat, where it gets saturated with flower oil, and alcohol. It is used to recover citrus oils from fruit peels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "What is maceration extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immersing a plant in a liquid",
            "b) Separate compounds based on their relative solubility",
            "c) Separate components at lower temperature",
            "d) Separated through evaporation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A maceration extraction consists of preserving contact between the plant and liquid for a period of time. It is an extractive technique that is conducted at room temperature where plant is immersed in a liquid like water, oil, alcohol.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "What is the other name for expression method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2 Extraction",
            "b) Maceration",
            "c) Enfleurage",
            "d) Cold Press Extraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cold presses are typically mechanically operated. Cold pressing usually produces a lower yield, but higher quality of oil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "What solvents are used to extract essential oils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Petroleum ether",
            "b) Ammonia",
            "c) Water",
            "d) Distilled water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Expression is method is also called as cold pressed method of extraction where there is no heat needed for extracting essential oil. In this process, the oil is forced from the material under high mechanical pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "How to increase the extraction efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crush the material",
            "b) Dissolve in water",
            "c) Dissolve in distilled water",
            "d) Dry the material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Essential oils are extracted by using solvents like ethanol, petroleum ether, hexane, and methanol. They have easy oil recovery, narrow boiling point and also have exceptional solubilizing capability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "How do you remove hexane from oil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum distillation",
            "b) CO2 Extraction",
            "c) Maceration",
            "d) Enfleurage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To increase the extraction efficiency the material should be crushed so that the components are easily dissolved into the solvent. This also results in low time consumption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "What is de-husking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improving the quality of husk",
            "b) Removing the husk",
            "c) Reducing the quality of husk",
            "d) Removing bran but the husk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the husk from rough paddy rice is removed, it is called as rice. The paddy grains are fed betweentwo abrasive surfaces that move at different speeds where the husks are removed by frictional force. Husk accounts for 20% of the paddy weight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "What is removed during polishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Husk and bran",
            "b) Germ and bran",
            "c) Bran and endosperm",
            "d) Endosperm and husk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: White rice is formed by eliminating the germ and the bran layer from the paddy. The bran layer is removed from the kernel through abrasive polisher. Bran removal accounts for 8-10% of the total paddy weight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "What is Mist polishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spraying water mist on rice",
            "b) Removing fungi on rice",
            "c) Removing bran",
            "d) Removing endosperm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mist polishing is the process of spraying afine mist of water with the dust. The mist is retained on the surface of the whitened rice. It improves the gloss of rice without reducing milling yield.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "What affects the milling potential of rice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contact time and quality",
            "b) Efficiency and quantity",
            "c) Milled rice recovery and quality",
            "d) Quantity and milled rice recovery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The milling potential of rice depends on the performance of the milled rice recovery and quality.  These milling potentials can be due to type of rice, quality condition of rice and pre-milling processes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the rice milling equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Huller mills",
            "b) Disc separator",
            "c) Sheller-Huller mills",
            "d) Sheller-Cone Polisher mills"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The  Rice  milling  is  the  process  that  helps  in  removal  of  hulls  and  bran’s  from  paddy  grains  to produce polished rice. It uses huller mills, sheller-Huller mills and sheller-Cone Polisher mills.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "What is milling degree?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Related to barn",
            "b) Related to husk",
            "c) Related to germ",
            "d) Related to endosperm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Paddy is converted into rice after the removal of husk. Therefore, paddy is the rice with husk. Rice is an annual crop.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "How is sludge removed from sedimentation tank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scraper",
            "b) Air",
            "c) Vacuum devices",
            "d) Scraper and vacuum devices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Milling degree is related to barn where it is defined as the measure of the amount of bran removed from the brown rice.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "What is the role of aspirators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To remove husks",
            "b) To remove bran",
            "c) To remove germ",
            "d) To remove endosperm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Sludge is removed from the sludge zone in sedimentation tank by scraper or vacuum devices which move along the bottom. Low flow velocities are allowed to enter the sludge zone, or else the sludge could be swept up and out of tank.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Which of the following step is not included in the pulse milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loosening of husk",
            "b) Parboiling",
            "c) De-husking",
            "d) Splitting of pulses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In pulse milling the steps involved are loosening of husk, dehusking and splitting of pulses. Whereas in the rice milling, parboiling is done to increase its nutrition value, change the texture of cooked rice and decrease the breakage in milling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "What is pitting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impart scratches and cracks on hard seed coat.",
            "b) Removing pits",
            "c) Removal of fine particles by chelating agents",
            "d) Removal of large particles by air bubbles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pitting is a method used to impart scratches, cracks and dents on its hard seed coat. This facilitates the easy migration where diffusion of oil and water in between the husk and cotyledons takes place.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "What is the soaking period for pulses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 to 8 hours",
            "b) 2 to 6 hours",
            "c) 2 to 4 hours",
            "d) 1 to 2 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wet method of pulse processing includes cleaning to remove dust, dirt, chaff, stone pieces, immature grains and other seeds. The easy to dehusk pulses are soaked into water for a period of 2 to 8 hours.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "What treatment should be given to pulses which are hard to dehusk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soak with hot water",
            "b) Apply red earth",
            "c) Soak with cold water",
            "d) Apply black soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wet method of pulse processing involves cleaning to remove dust, dirt, chaff, stone pieces, immature grains and other seeds. The easy to dehusk pulses are then soaked into water for a period of 2- 8 hrs whereas husks which are difficult to dehusk are treated with red earth. The pulses are subsequently dried and then subjected to dehusking and splitting to obtain Dal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "What is the drying temperature of pulses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 26-48°C",
            "b) 60-120°C",
            "c) 80-135°C",
            "d) 100-120°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mechanically heated air dryers are also used for pulse milling.  The temperature of heated air for drying ranges from 60-120°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Which are the important steps involved in deciding the total recovery of pulses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loosening of husk",
            "b) Parboiling",
            "c) Dehusking",
            "d) Splitting of pulses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An emery roller machine is used for cracking the husk layer and for rubbing of clean pulses passing through it. This is used to remove the husk from cotyledons in order to help oil penetration in the following unit operations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Which of the component is reduced when pulses are soaked?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phytic acid",
            "b) Nitric acid",
            "c) Potassium oxide",
            "d) Nitrous oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Loosening of husks is very important step in pulses milling as it decides the total recovery and quality of milled dal. Loosening of husk is achieved in two different ways they are wet method and dry method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not included in secondary processing of pulses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roasting",
            "b) Polishing",
            "c) De-husking",
            "d) Splitting of pulses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step involved is the soaking in water which is prepared for pulses. The soaking reduces the oligosaccharides of the raffinose family and also reduces the amount of phytic acid in pulses.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "What is emulsification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process of separating two or more miscible liquids",
            "b) Process of dispersing two or more immiscible liquids",
            "c) Process of dispersing two or more miscible liquids",
            "d) Process of separating two or more immiscible liquids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Emulsification is the process of dispersing two or more immiscible liquids together to form a semi-stable mixture. It helps in stabilization of the product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "What type of emulsion is milk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oil in water",
            "b) Water in oil",
            "c) Water in water",
            "d) Oil in oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In every emulsion there is a continuous phase that suspends the droplets of the other element which is known as dispersed phase. In oil-in-water emulsion, the continuous phase is the water and the dispersed phase is the oil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "What type of emulsion is butter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oil in water",
            "b) Water in oil",
            "c) Water in water",
            "d) Oil in oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In every emulsion there is a continuous phase that suspends the droplets of the other element which is known as dispersed phase. In water-in-oil emulsion, the continuous phase is the oil and the dispersed phase is the water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of homogenization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emulsification",
            "b) Evaporating",
            "c) Heating",
            "d) Freezing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The purpose of homogenization is emulsification where it breaks down fat molecules in milk and resists separation. Without homogenization process, fat molecules in milk will rise to the top and form a layer of cream.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "What type of emulsion is mayonnaise?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temporary",
            "b) Semi-permanent",
            "c) Permanent",
            "d) Semi- temporary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are three types of emulsions they are temporary, semi-permanent, and permanent. An example of a temporary emulsion is simple vinaigrette while mayonnaise is a permanent emulsion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "What are factors that can destabilize an emulsion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Droplet size",
            "c) Droplet-size distribution",
            "d) Temperature, droplet size and droplet-size distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Factors that can affect stabilization of an emulsion are heavy polar fractions, solids, including organic and inorganic materials, temperature, droplet size and droplet-size distribution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "What increases the viscosity of emulsion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stabilizers",
            "b) Catalysts",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The viscosity is improved by stabilizers in the continuous phase of emulsions. Mobility of the droplets and their collision rate decreases. Therefore, stabilizers improve the stability of emulsions by hydrodynamic effects.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "What is creaming in emulsions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Migration of the dispersed phase of an emulsion",
            "b) Emulsion separation into its separate ingredients",
            "c) Migration of the continuous phase of an emulsion",
            "d) Emulsion reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Creaming is defined as the migration of the dispersed phase of an emulsion, under the influence of buoyancy. It occurs when isolated oil droplets combine where it sinks to the bottom in w/o emulsions or rises to the top of an o/w emulsion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "What is cracking in emulsions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Migration of the dispersed phase of an emulsion",
            "b) Emulsion separation into its separate ingredients",
            "c) Migration of the continuous phase of an emulsion",
            "d) Emulsion reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cracking in emulsion is defined as the separation of emulsified product into its separate ingredients where the oil and water are clearly separated and will not recombine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "How to determine type of emulsion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conductivity test and boiling test",
            "b) Conductivity test and distillation",
            "c) Dilution test and boiling test",
            "d) Dilution test and conductivity test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Emulsion Type is determined by two tests, they are dilution Test where o/w emulsion is diluted with water and w/o emulsion is diluted with oil. Conductivity test is done where electrodes are used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "What is meat emulsion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finely chopped meat mixture",
            "b) Emulsifiers added to meat",
            "c) By product of meat industry",
            "d) Stabilizers added to meat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A finely chopped meat mixture is usually called as meat emulsion. It consists of solid fat particles dispersed in a mixture of water and many fibrous particles, including connective tissue and muscle fibers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Why is tumbling of meat recommended?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Avoid foaming",
            "b) Increases efficiency",
            "c) Increase efficacy",
            "d) Decreases power consumption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tumblers are containers in the form of a cylinder rotating around the axis. Tumbling under vacuum is recommended to avoid foaming and to improve color stability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "What is the temperature of pasteurization for meat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 73°C",
            "b) 89°C",
            "c) 63°C",
            "d) 65°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pasteurization is normally defined as a method of preserving food by heating it to temperatures under 100°C. It destroys the microbes and temperature of pasteurization for meat is 73°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "What is evisceration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removing internal body parts of bird",
            "b) Removing feathers",
            "c) Cleaning the skin of bird",
            "d) Preservation technique of bird"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During meat processing, meat products are subject to specific heat treatment. This is done to increase shelf-life by reduction of micro-organisms, obtain desirable organoleptic characteristics, to preserve nutritive value and improve digestibility of the product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "What is giblet harvester?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removes the viscera from the body cavity",
            "b) Separates the heart, liver, and gizzard from the rest of the viscera",
            "c) Trim and clean gizzards",
            "d) Cut the neck of the bird"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Evisceration is defined as removal of the internal organs of birds. After evisceration, the birds are placed in chiller baths of water and anti-microbial agents are added to reduce pathogen loading.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "What is arranger in meat processing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removes the viscera from the body cavity",
            "b) Separates the heart, liver, and gizzard from the rest of the viscera",
            "c) Trim and clean gizzards",
            "d) Cut the neck of the bird"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The liver, gizzard, and heart are separated by giblet harvester from the rest of the intestines by a saw. Then these organs are conveyed to a wash table where a prime cleaning is done.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "What is the gizzard table operator in meat processing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removes the viscera from the body cavity",
            "b) Separates the heart, liver, and gizzard from the rest of the viscera",
            "c) Trim and clean gizzards",
            "d) Cut the neck of the bird"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Arranger removes the intestines from the body cavity and are arranged them for inspection. The initial removal is often skilled by the automatic vent opening mechanism. The arranger is also called as presenter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "What gas is used for gas stunning in meat processing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Argon",
            "b) Helium",
            "c) Carbon dioxide",
            "d) Ammonia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The gizzard table operators manually trim and clean the gizzards. They are then placed in an automatic splitting machine where they are opened up and washed in the gizzard peeler station.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "What is other name for batch pasteurization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vat Pasteurization",
            "b) HTST pasteurization",
            "c) UHT pasteurization",
            "d) Cold pasteurization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vat Pasteurization is also known as the holding method or batch pasteurization. Every particle of milk or cream is heated in equipment at 63°C and hold for 30 minutes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "What happens when milk is pasteurized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduces the bacterial population",
            "b) Destroys spores",
            "c) Impart color",
            "d) Impart flavor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pasteurization is not similar to sterilization. Pasteurization reduces the bacterial population of a liquid and destroys the organisms that may cause spoilage and human disease. Spores are not affected by the pasteurization process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "What happens when milk is sterilized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduces the bacterial population",
            "b) Destroys spores",
            "c) Impart color",
            "d) Impart flavor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pasteurization is not similar to sterilization. Spores are not affected by the pasteurization process. But the sterilization process destroys the spores of the bacteria by inactivating them.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "What is the chilling temperature of milk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2°C",
            "b) 3-4°C",
            "c) 5-6°C",
            "d) 6-7°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chilling of milk is done by quick cooling of the raw milk to adequately low temperature. So that the growth of microbes present in milk is inactivated. In chilling process, the temperature of milk should be around 3 – 4°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "What is the temperature of ultra-pasteurization for milk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 125 – 138°C",
            "b) 115 – 120°C",
            "c) 63°C",
            "d) 63 – 65°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ultra-pasteurization temperature is 125 – 138°C for 2-4 seconds. Sterilization of milk in container is 115 – 120°C for 20-30 minutes. LTLT pasteurization of milk is 63°C for 30 minutes and for thermisation it is 63 – 65°C for 15 seconds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "What is bactofugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process of removal of microorganisms from milk using centrifugal force",
            "b) Process of removal of yeast and fungi from milk using centrifugal force",
            "c) Process of removal of microorganisms from milk using gravitational force",
            "d) Process of removal of yeast and mold from milk using gravitational force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bactofugation is the process of removal of microorganisms from milk using centrifugal force. It is a special form of separation of microbes, mainly spore formers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "Which of the following dryer used to manufacture milk powder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spray dryer",
            "b) Cabinet tray dryer",
            "c) Pneumatic dryer",
            "d) Fluidized bed dryer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spray dyer is used to produce powder from the solution. It dries the solution stream and separates the solute and evaporates the solvent and forms vapor. The solid particles are collected in a cyclone or drum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "What is the temperature of LTLT pasteurization for milk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 125 – 138°C",
            "b) 115 – 120°C",
            "c) 63°C",
            "d) 63 – 65°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ultra-pasteurization temperature is 125 – 138°C for 2-4 seconds. Sterilization of milk in container is 115 – 120°C for 20-30 minutes. LTLT pasteurization of milk is 63°C for 30 minutes and for thermisation it is 63 – 65°C for 15 seconds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "What is skimming efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The amount of fat that can be separated from milk",
            "b) The amount of skim milk that can be separated from whole milk",
            "c) The amount of fat that is added to milk",
            "d) The amount of skim milk that is added to whole milk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The amount of fat that can be separated from milk and it depends on the design of the separator, the flow rate of milk and the size distribution of the fat globules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "What is the temperature of thermisation for milk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 125 – 138°C",
            "b) 115 – 120°C",
            "c) 63°C",
            "d) 63 – 65°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ultra-pasteurization temperature is 125 – 138°C for 2-4 seconds. Sterilization of milk in container is 115 – 120°C for 20-30 minutes. LTLT pasteurization of milk is 63°C for 30 minutes and for thermisation it is 63 – 65°C for 15 seconds.\n"
    }
]